I want to understand. First of all,
आई वांट टू अंडरस्टैंड। फर्स्ट ऑफ ऑल,
what do you think about this 11a
व्हाट डू डू यू थिंक अबाउट दिस 11a
Miracle? its this this
मिरेकल? इसका इस इस
You don't think it's a little strange? Meaning
यू डोंट थिंक इट्स अ लिटिल स्ट्रेंज? मतलब
What are the chances of someone surviving?
क्या चांसेस होते हैं किसी के बचने के?
Brother, no one is left, only that man is left. So,
भाई, कोई नहीं बचा, वही बंदा बचा है। तो,
I don't know if there was a guy in 11 before
आई डोंट नो क्या 11 में पहले भी एक बंदा
Yes, he was saved. This one survived too, brother,
था, वो बच गया था। यह भी बच गया, भाई,
What do you mean God has to save him, save him
क्या मतलब भगवान को बचाना होगा उसको बचा
Took it. This crash happened earlier also in the same 11
लिया। पहले भी ये क्रैश में वही 11 में भी
It's saved. Was left on 11A. this is the same emergency
बचा है। 11A पे बचा था। ये वही इमरजेंसी
The exit window is the side seat. I slept
एग्जिट विंडो साइड सीट रहती है जो। सो आई
no this much that the seat above the wings
नो दिस मच कि विंग्स के ऊपर की जो सीट
happens, from there a structurally sufficient
होती है, वहां से ना एक स्ट्रक्चरली काफी
The ship becomes stronger from there. but this case
स्ट्रांग होता है जहाज वहां से। बट इस केस
I just fell completely down Terry
में तो सिर्फ वो पूरा ही गिरा ना टेरी तो
If I survived then I have no idea brother how I survived
बची तो नो आईडिया भाई कैसे बच गया मतलब
What is strange and what does it mean
क्या स्ट्रेंज स्ट्रेंज और मतलब ही इज़
Walking out of it playing video
वॉकिंग आउट ऑफ इट वीडियो प्ले कर रहा हूं
Brother, he is jumping out of the fire balloons
भाई वो उछल के निकल रहा है आग के गुब्बारे
and it seems as if it is going on
में से और ऐसा लगाता हुआ सा चल रहा है
Like what in the brother what is his life
लाइक व्हाट इन द भाई उसकी क्या जिंदगी
What would the rest of the people think, brother?
होगी वो क्या सोचता होगा भाई बाकी लोग
Imagine his body burning next to his seat
सोचो उसके सीट के बगल वाला उसकी बॉडी जल
It's been four yes and she has it here too
गई चार हो गई हां और उसको यहां पे भी
There was no fracture even in the finger
फ्रैक्चर नहीं दिया नहीं उंगली में भी
Insane means friend can you pull up
इनसेन मतलब मतलब यार क्या कैन यू पुल अप
His visual? I mean, I don't know if anyone
हिज विज़ुअल? मतलब पता नहीं अगर किसी ने
I have not seen this. Do you not know who you are talking about
नहीं देखा है ये। पता है ना किसकी बात कर
I am the one who survives, I mean I
रहा हूं मैं जो सर्वाइव में मतलब मुझे
It seems that friend God has to save someone
लगता है यार भगवान को जिसको बचाना होता है
No, I would have saved him. anything means yes
ना उसको तो बचा ही देता। कुछ भी मतलब हां
Here it is. And he just walks out. no brother
ये रही। एंड ही जस्ट वॉक्स आउट। भाई ना
He has a fracture in his leg or something. Meaning
इसको पैर में फ्रैक्चर है ना कुछ है। मतलब
The guy is able to walk, friend. it's in his mind
चल पा रहा है बंदा यार। इसके दिमाग में ये
he can brother it looks like he came out of a crash
ही कैन भाई लग रहा है कि क्रैश से निकला
This has happened. brother in car accident
हुआ है ये। भाई गाड़ी के एक्सीडेंट में
I have seen worse people than this, brother. Oho
मैंने इससे बुरे लोग देखे हैं भाई। अरे
Brother to whom yes.
भाई जिसको हां।
Look at this. Yes. so this is where it stops
ये देखो। हां। सो दिस इज वेयर इट्स स्टॉप
Generating left that's going down.
जनरेटिंग लेफ्ट वो नीचे जा रहा है।
I have also heard brother that double engine
मैंने ये भी सुना है भाई कि डबल इंजन
Being a failure is one in a billion
फेलियर होना इज वन इन अ बिलियन मैं तो
I would say it will be trillion of billion. I have
कहूंगा बिलियन का ट्रिलियन होगा। मैंने तो
Didn't see it. Why is it like this? why are you two
नहीं देखा। ऐसा क्यों है? व्हाई आर टू
The engine is so secure that both of them cannot fail
इंजन सो सिक्योर कि वो दोनों फेल नहीं हो
Can. friend first no trans atlantic
सकते। यार पहले ना ट्रांस एटलांटिक
Flights and Pacific flights four engines
फ्लाइट्स और पेसिफिक की फ्लाइट्स चार इंजन
Ships with these used to run. if you look now at boeing 340
वाले जहाज चलते थे। अगर अब देखो 340 बोइंग
Travel 747 so the regulation said that friend four
ट्रेव 747 तो रेगुलेशन कहती थी कि यार चार
If one of the engines is made of three or two flowers, then
इंजन बनाते एक भी फ्ल तीन है दो फुले तो
then we said our technology so advanced that
देन वी सेड आवर टेक्नोलॉजी सो एडवांस्ड कि
Two engines will never fail at the same time
दो इंजन तो एक साथ कभी फेल होंगे ही नहीं
we saw when boeing triple 7 was made for him
हम सो व्हेन बोइंग ट्रिपल7 वाज़ मेड उसको
Direct approval was given that you can fly over
सीधा अप्रूवल दे दिया कि यू कैन फ्लाई ओवर
There is no water because there is no chance two engines one
वाटर बिकॉज़ है ही नहीं चांस दो इंजन एक
We have made it so much that we fail together
साथ फेल हो जाए हमने बनाया इतना वी आर
If you can't advance, you can't fail so much
एडवांस ना हो नहीं कर सकते फेल तो इतना
There is more trust on technology that two engines
ज्यादा ट्रस्ट है टेक्नोलॉजी पे कि टू इंज
Cannot fail and there is no operational reason
कैन नॉट फेल एंड कोई ऑपरेशनल रीज़न भी नहीं
maybe because i mean if my car engine ends
हो सकता क्योंकि मतलब इफ माय कार इंजन एंड
I'm using a very stupid example can
आई यूजिंग अ वैरी स्टूपिड एग्जांपल कैन
fail any time what is so special about to
फेल एनी टाइम व्हाट इज सो स्पेशल अबाउट टू
I am not feeling my love my engines are in such a state
इंज नॉट फीलिंग यार इंजंस आर डिज़ इन सच अ
that there is a lot of redundancy
वे कि उसमें रिडंडेंसी बहुत सारी होती है
And that's why they are so expensive right
एंड दैट्स व्हाई दे आर सो एक्सपेंसिव राइट
Now if you own a Maruti
अब अगर आप एक Maruti
Do you buy a car and a Rolls Ryce?
का कार लेते हो और एक Rolls Ryce लेते हो
So there is redundancy in that, so both
तो उसमें रिडेंडेंसी तो चलती है तो दोनों
Brother, both A to B will be delivered. Right?
भाई A टू बी दोनों पहुंचा देंगी। राइट?
Which has more safety? in an expensive car
सेफ्टी किसमें ज्यादा है? महंगी गाड़ी में
It must be that your air bag has come out, friend
होगी ना कि यार तुम्हारा ये एयर बैग निकल
will come. This will happen. you must escape the sirens
आएगा। ये हो जाएगा। तुम्हें सायरन बच
Will go. If you fall asleep it will set an alarm
जाएगा। तुम्हें नींद आएगी तो वो अलार्म कर
will give. The car will stop automatically. So safety
देगा। अपने आप गाड़ी रोक देगा। तो सेफ्टी
Majors are built into the system. we have given
मेजर्स आर बिल्ट इनू द सिस्टम। हम तो दी
R set of the art machines. Billions Of
आर सेट ऑफ द आर्ट मशीनंस। बिलियंस ऑफ
Dollars have been spent to make such machines.
डॉलर्स हैव बीन स्पेंड टू मेक सच मशीनंस।
has that been another case of a dual engine
हैज़ दैट बीन अनदर केस ऑफ़ अ ड्यूल इंजन
FAILURE EVER IN AVIATION HISTORY? can you
फेलियर एवर इन एवीएशन हिस्ट्री? कैन यू
Check Dual Engine Failure in Aviation
चेक ड्यूल इंजन फेलियर इन एविएशन
History. Brother it is a dual engine but
हिस्ट्री। भाई डुअल इंजन हुए हैं लेकिन
Like the stall is done or the birds have come. By the way
जैसे स्टॉल हो गया या बर्ड्स आ गई। वैसे
It has happened. I didn't even know this happened brother
हुआ है। ये तो पता ही नहीं चला ना भाई हुआ
What? It's called a flame out. Right?
क्या? इट्स इट्स कॉल्ड अ फ्लेम आउट। राइट?
Ok. it's a flame out that's going on and
ओके। इट्स अ फ्लेम आउट कि चल रहा है और
It stopped. It never happened like that. Some?
बंद हो गया। वैसा तो नहीं हुआ कभी भी। कुछ
All the indicators must have gone to zero
ऑल दी इंडिकेटर्स मस्ट हैव गॉन टू जीरो
It is in front. yes all the bells rang ton ton ton
सामने है। हां सब टन टन टन घंटी बजी गई
It will be completed. and when both ends fail all the
होगी पूरी। और व्हेन बोथ इंज फेल ऑल दी ऑल
The NECESSARY PANELS The screen in front of you.
दी एनसीएटर पैनल्स आपके सामने स्क्रीन है।
Everything Goes Dark Except Captain Side
एवरीथिंग गोज़ डार्क एक्सेप्ट कैप्टन साइड
Only the rats which used to be there, the rat came.
का सिर्फ रैट्स जो होता था ना रैट आया।
The rat only moves that much. what is rat
रैट सिर्फ उतना ही चलता है। रैट क्या है
Brother? Dude, it's a ram air turbine. Good.
भाई? यार रैम एयर टरबाइन होता है। अच्छा।
so it's a small fan which drops down
सो इट्स अ स्माल फैन व्हिच ड्रॉप्स डाउन
from the belly of the aircraft when there
फ्रॉम द बेली ऑफ़ द एयरक्राफ्ट व्हेन देयर
is there no electrical supply to the
इज़ नो इलेक्ट्रिकल सप्लाई टू द
Aircraft. me and that too a particular
एयरक्राफ्ट। हम और वो भी एक पर्टिकुलर
Runs up to speed. like there's a lot of talk
स्पीड तक चलता है। जैसे बहुत बात हो रही
If it is rat then rat is electrical
है कि रैट हो गया तो रैट इलेक्ट्रिकल
When I saw it in my childhood it looked like this
जब मेरे पास वो देखा होगा बचपन में वो ऐसा
The fan used to come. we used to do it outside the car
पंखा आता था। हम कार के बाहर करते थे तो
That toy seller used to move around on his own. we we
वो अपने आप घूमता था खिलौने वाला। हम हम
So the wind is blowing around the rat, brother. Rat Koi
सो रैट को हवा घुमा रही है भाई। रैट कोई
There isn't an engine like that. The rat is small
वैसा इंजन नहीं होता। रैट छोटा सा होता है
and it requires a minimum air speed
और उसको उसको एक मिनिमम एयर स्पीड चाहिए
It is there to perform the function. Ok. So
होती है फंक्शन करने के लिए। ओके। तो
Below as you land in the Airbus
एयरबस में जैसे ही आप लैंड करते हो बिलो
149 ns that gives even less power. Then you touch
149 न्स वो और कम पावर देता है। फिर आप टच
If you turn it down it stops immediately.
डाउन करते हो तो एकदम ही बंद हो जाता है।
So the wind is blowing it around. he by himself
तो उसको हवा घुमा रही है। वो अपने आप से
No one is generating power by taking any fuel.
कोई फ्यूल लेके पावर जनरेट नहीं कर रहा।
Hum to rat aya aircraft speed 184
हम तो रैट आया एयरक्राफ्ट की स्पीड 184
There were knots. If he is going down then reduce the speed
नॉट्स थी। वो नीचे जा रहा है तो स्पीड कम
It must be happening. So what did the rat do?
हो रही होगी। तो रैट ने भी क्या ही काम
Must have done it. Then the aircraft is on batteries
किया होगा। फिर तो एयरक्राफ्ट ऑन बैटरीज
Done. which would be two 25 volt batteries
हो गया। जो दो 25 वोल्ट की दो बैटरीज होती
It is in the air bus. I don't know how much it costs
है एयर बस में। आई डोंट नो इसमें कितने की
Is. Hmm. so very minimal
है। हम्म। तो बहुत ही मिनिमम
The pilot will have controllability. this fan
कंट्रोलेबिलिटी होगी पायलट के पास। इस फैन
What is the purpose of a rat? this is the rat
का क्या पर्पस रहता है रैट? यही तो रैट है
No? yes what is its purpose? So
ना? हां इसका पर्पस क्या होता है? तो
when lets say you have no so two engines
व्हेन लेट्स से यू हैव नो सो दो इंजन हो
Went. Right? The engines have generators.
गए। राइट? इंजंस में जनरेटर होते हैं।
Generator one generator two. if we fail in exam then
जनरेटर वन जनरेटर टू। हम इंज फेल तो
The generator is also not working. From lats
जनरेटर भी काम नहीं कर रहा। लेट्स से
Both generators provide AC power. Now
दोनों जनरेटर पे एसी पावर देते हैं। अब
Where does the ship get its electrical supply from?
जहाज को इलेक्ट्रिकल सप्लाई कहां से
Will I get it? he gives a rat then he goes down through the
मिलेगी? रैट देता ना फिर वो नीचे थ्रू द
Rotation through the rotation. He gives very little
रोटेशन थ्रू द रोटेशन। वो बहुत कम देता है
Brother, that. it is just that it will power one
भाई वो। इट इज़ जस्ट कि इट विल पावर वन
Hydraulics and Your Bare Minimum Systems
हाइड्रोलिक एंड योर बेयर मिनिमम सिस्टम्स
It will work. good gear up she don't go
विल वर्क। अच्छा गियर अप वो नहीं जाती
It would require a lot of power to gear up
उससे गियर अप के लिए बहुत पावर चाहिए होती
and you don't want to waste gear up
है एंड यू डोंट वांट टू वेस्ट गियर अप
You just have to land in it
लोगे आप उसमें आपको लैंड ही तो करना है
safely right right right right right then
सेफली राइट राइट राइट राइट राइट तो
Everything Goes Off Captain's PFD Walk
एवरीथिंग गोज़ ऑफ कैप्टन की एक पीएफडी चल
This must have been his stand-by instrument
रही होगी एक उसका स्टैंड बाय इंस्ट्रूमेंट
It must be going on and that's it brother in the name of God
चल रहा होगा और बस कि भाई भगवान का नाम
Take it and land it, it has so much power
लेके लैंड करा दो इतनी पावर होती है एंड
then the captain probably gives a maid a
देन द कैप्टन प्रोबेब्ली गिव्स अ मेड ए
call boss everything is closed do something
कॉल कि बॉस सब कुछ बंद हो गया कुछ करो
well there is a question like me
अच्छा देयर इज़ अ क्वेश्चन जैसे मेरे
After the video people said that I
वीडियो के बाद लोगों ने बोला कि जो मैं
should I tell you yes yes please tell me that
बता दूं मैंने हां हां प्लीज मेरे को वो
If you give me a summary then friend, one in the aircraft
समरी भी दो तो यार एयरक्राफ्ट में एक
The system is AD DSB at every point
सिस्टम होता है एडी डीएसबी एट एव्री पॉइंट
of time instantly it sends out
ऑफ टाइम इंस्टेंटेनियसली इट सेंड्स आउट
The Signal That's How ATc Comes to Know
सिग्नल दैट्स हाउ एटी एटीसी कम्स टू नो
your position your height your speed and
योर पोजीशन योर हाइट योर स्पीड एंड
Everything and there is a third party company
एवरीथिंग एंड देयर इज़ अ थर्ड पार्टी कंपनी
cold radar 24
कॉल्ड रेडार 24
radar 24 if you pull up radar 24 he will pull you up
रेडार 24 इफ यू पुल अप रेडार 24 वो आपको
of all the aircraft in the world
पूरे वर्ल्ड में सारे एयरक्राफ्ट की
Shows the position live, where and what is going
पोजीशन दिखा देता है लाइव कहां पे क्या जा
Where is he not going then Radar 24
रहा है कहां नहीं जा रहा तो रेडार 24 ने
This data was made live and it came to us
यह डाटा लाइव किया कि हमारे पास यह आया था
Whatever 30 seconds it took from Air India 171
एयर इंडिया 171 से जितना भी 30 सेकंड वो
I was in the flight so they were saying that yaar it
फ्लाइट में था तो वो कह रहे हैं कि यार इट
Took a really long time to lift off from the
टूक रियली लॉन्ग टाइम टू लिफ्ट ऑफ फ्रॉम द
Runway. so let's say this is what
रनवे। सो लेट्स से दिस इज दिस इज व्हाट
The distance you take when you have both inches
डिस्टेंस यू टेक व्हेन यू हैव बोथ इंज
Running. hum if you have one engine fail you will
रनिंग। हम इफ यू हैव वन इंजन फेल यू विल
Take Slightly Long Distance. power is low
टेक स्लाइटली लॉन्ग डिस्टेंस। पावर कम हो
Went. This ship travelled a greater distance than that
गई। इस जहाज ने उससे भी ज्यादा डिस्टेंस
Took it. That is what the data is suggesting.
लिया। दैट इज़ व्हाट द डेटा इज़ सजेस्टिंग।
So it's V1, friend. V1 is my decision
तो V1 हो गया यार। वी1 इज़ माय डिसीजन
Speed. Ok? before V1 if i had any
स्पीड। ओके? V1 के पहले अगर मेरे पास कोई
major problem occurs late if i lose n
मेजर दिक्कत होती है लेट से इफ आई लूज एन
Engine before V1 hum i will reject take off
इंजन बिफोर V1 हम आई विल रिजेक्ट टेक ऑफ
i can stop i can stop you have enough
आई कैन स्टॉप आई कैन स्टॉप यू हैव इनफ
Runway to stop after V1 if engine fails
रनवे टू स्टॉप वी1 के बाद अगर इंजन फेल
if it happens then I don't have enough runway to stop
होता है तो आई डोंट हैव इनफ रनवे टू स्टॉप
ok i have to take off after v1
ठीक है वी1 के बाद मेरे को टेक ऑफ करना ही
we are here so i am flying
करना है वी आर इज़ सो मैं फ्लाई कर रहा हूं
I have my hand here on the first lever
हम मेरा हाथ यहां पे फर्स्ट लीवर पे है एक
I have it in my hand I can do pull ups
मेरे हाथ में योग्य है मैं पुल अप करता
hun so my first officer gives the call 100
हूं सो माय फर्स्ट ऑफिसर गिव्स द कॉल 100
nots 100 nots means that now I am I
नॉट्स 100 नॉट्स मींस कि अब आई एम आई
Entering a high speed regime. where things are
एंटिंग अ हाई स्पीड रिजीम। थिंग्स आर
Critical Now. No problem with high speed
क्रिटिकल नाउ। हाई स्पीड में कोई दिक्कत
If it is there then it is critical. Below 100 knots
होगी तो क्रिटिकल है। 100 नॉट्स के नीचे
So I can even solve a small problem
तो मैं साला छोटी भी प्रॉब्लम आई कैन
Reject. I will come back after getting the go back corrected.
रिजेक्ट। गो बैक सही करा के वापस आऊंगा।
I'm go minded at over 100 knots.
100 नॉट्स के ऊपर आई एम गो माइंडेड।
Now when I reach we one he gives a call we
नाउ व्हेन आई रीच वी वन ही गिव्स अ कॉल वी
one the important step i i remove my
वन द इंपॉर्टेंट स्टेप आई आई रिमूव माय
Hands from the Thrust Layers. because mistake
हैंड फ्रॉम द थ्रस्ट लेयर्स। बिकॉज़ गलती
Don't reject it even from there. Because Incent
से भी रिजेक्ट ना कर दो। क्योंकि इंसेंट
It would have happened. ok ok ok ok. Yes. Some?
होता ना। अच्छा ओके ओके ओके ओके। हां। कुछ
It happened that the bell rang or he said something. Sir I
हुआ घंटी बजी या उसने कुछ बोला। सर आई
it's a very crypto i remove my hand
इट्स अ वैरी क्रिप्टो आई रिमूव माय हैंड
from the first sleeves even by his mistake
फ्रॉम द फर्स्ट स्लीव्स उसकी गलती से भी
Don't reject me I'm 100% gone
मुझे रिजेक्ट नहीं करना आई एम 100% गो
minded so after v1 i am go minded
माइंडेड तो वी1 के बाद मैं गो माइंडेड हूं
Even if the engine fails, we are here
चाहे इंजन फेल भी हो जाए वी आर पे आई
start rotating wheel of pay is my
स्टार्ट रोटेटिंग व्हील ऑफ पे इज माय
Lift off rotating edge in the engine start
लिफ्ट ऑफ रोटेटिंग एज इन द इंजन स्टार्ट
I start I start ok you start
आई स्टार्ट आई स्टार्ट अच्छा यू स्टार्ट
I will also do pulling of pulling ups pull ups
पुलिंग ऑफ पुलिंग अप पुल अप भी करूंगा
A little over the top but the point is where I leave my
थोड़ा ऊपर लेकिन द पॉइंट वेयर आई लीव माय
ground is wheel off okay okay so
ग्राउंड इज व्हील ऑफ अच्छा ओके ठीक है तो
the engine is there so the plane has taken off
इंजन तो वो तो जहाज तो टेक ऑफ किया है तो
So everything was fine before V1, right?
मतलब वी1 के पहले तो सब ठीक था ठीक है ना
For V1 then we are sure that before V1 all
वी1 के तो वी आर श्योर कि वी1 के पहले सब
It was ok. Got it. Now what happened after V1
ठीक था। गॉट इट। अब जो हुआ वी1 के बाद हुआ
yes brother. That's right. So my theory is that
है भाई। ठीक बात। तो जो मेरी थ्योरी है जो
As far as I understood from my mind
जितना मुझे समझ में आया अपने दिमाग से
A little bit so I am saying that friend V1
थोड़ा बहुत तो मैं कह रहा हूं कि यार वी1
After that one of its engines failed. Got it.
के बाद उसका एक इंजन फेल हुआ। गॉट इट।
Yes. Ok? And he rotated. thats
हां। ठीक है? और उसने रोटेट किया। दैट्स
why he took little lager to lift off from
व्हाई ही टूक लिटिल लगर टू लिफ्ट ऑफ फ्रॉम
The Ground. Right? Now he rotated it so
द ग्राउंड। राइट? अब उसने रोटेट किया तो
His speed decreased. and then another thing bro
स्पीड उसकी कम हुई। एंड देन दूसरी चीज भाई
This is not an everyday story. Now he is the captain
ये रोज का कहानी तो है नहीं। अब वो कैप्टन
Came to him. Friends retire even once
उसके पास आया। एक बार भी यार लोग रिटायर
They do it. Not a single engine fails.
कर जाते हैं। एक भी इंजन फेल नहीं होता।
Retire with 25-25,000 hours.
25-25,000 घंटे साथ रिटायर कर जाते हैं।
If people don't happen, nothing happens. and in the sim
लोग नहीं होता कुछ नहीं होता। और सिम में
Dude you have practiced enough times. In the sim
यार यू प्रैक्टिस्ड इनफ टाइम्स। सिम में
What happens? as we sit and talk
क्या होता है? जैसे हम बैठे बात कर रहे
Are. An instructor will come and give a briefing
हैं। एक इंस्ट्रक्टर आएगा ब्रीफिंग करेगा
Every one hour. Gaurav today we had an engine failure
हर एक घंटे की। गौरव आज हम एक इंजन फेल
do. One engine failed for me I am a V1
करेंगे। एक इंजन फेल तेरे को मैं वी1 के
I will give it first. I'll give it to you after a V1. V1's
पहले दूंगा। एक वी1 के बाद दूंगा। वी1 के
First you have to reject it. Maintain
पहले तूने रिजेक्ट करना है। मेंटेन
Central Line. Give a call. if there is a fire
सेंट्रल लाइन। गिव अ कॉल। अगर फायर है तो
Will evacuate. Happened after V1. then dead
इवाकुएट करेगा। वी1 के बाद हुआ। देन डेड
Foot dead engine. maintain the central line of
फुट डेड इंजन। मेंटेन दी सेंट्रल लाइन ऑफ
The Nose. see your ship and then take
द नोज़। देखना यौर ना करे जहाज एंड देन टेक
The Auto Pilot Trims the Aircraft and
द ऑटो पायलट ट्रिम द एयरक्राफ्ट एंड
Aftill 400ft No Action Just Gear A
आफ्टिल 400 फीट नो एक्शन जस्ट गियर अ
plena and then give a maid a call tell him
प्लेना एंड देन गिव अ मेड अ कॉल टेल हिम
To Stand By and Reach the Acceleration Altitude
टू स्टैंड बाय रीच द एक्सलेशन ऑल्टीट्यूड
Level up and then clean up complete procedure
लेवल अप एंड देन क्लीन अप पूरा प्रोसीजर
I'm revising okay okay okay
मैं रिवाइज कर रहा हूं ठीक ठीक ठीक ठीक
Alright brother, when I'm sitting in the plane
ठीक ठीक तो भाई जब मैं बैठा हूं जहाज में
I know it will give in swimming, yes, yes
स्विम में तो मुझे पता है ये देगा हां हां
In a real situation, even a little bit
रियल सिचुएशन में तो यार थोड़ी सी भी एक
The bell bursts in the man's ship
घंटी बचती फट जाती है इंसान की जहाज में
I may be the one who started by the
हम तो मे बी दे वर स्टार्टेड बाय दी
The effect was that one engine failed during take off
इफेक्ट कि यार एक इंजन फेल हो गया टेक ऑफ
did some reach 100 feet
किया 100 फीट पे पहुंचे होंगे कुछ
something unusual must have happened to him there
अनयूजुअल हुआ होगा उनके के साथ देयर
attention must have been that friend what happened
अटेंशन मस्ट हैव बीन कि यार क्या हुआ क्या
If it happens then you gear up at 100 feet and
हुआ तो 100 फीट पे आप गियर अप लेते हो एंड
you put gear up is landing air landing
यू पुट गियर अप इज़ लैंडिंग एयर लैंडिंग
air there is a call out i'm flying hill
एयर देयर इज़ अ कॉल आउट आई एम फ्लाइंग हिल
he will say positive climb and only after
ही विल से पॉजिटिव क्लाइम एंड ओनली आफ्टर
His call I'll say gear up and this has
हिज कॉल आई विल से गियर अप एंड दिस हैज़
happened to me in the same that guy
हैपेंड मी विद मी इन द सेम उस बंदे ने
If you don't say positive climate then I will gear up
पॉजिटिव क्लाइम नहीं बोला तो मैं गियर अप
I will not say it, I will initiate that call got
नहीं बोलूंगा ही विल इनिशिएट दैट कॉल गॉट
It He Must Not Have Said Positive Climb
इट ही मस्ट हैव नॉट सेड पॉजिटिव क्लाइम
Because when there is a positive climate my
बिकॉज़ जब पॉजिटिव क्लाइम होता है माय
Vertical speed is going up I'm climbing so
वर्टिकल स्पीड इज़ गोइंग अप आई एम क्लाइ तो
he might have seen a slight drop and you
उसको हल्का सा ड्रॉप दिखा होगा एंड यू
Only Say Positive When You Are
ओनली से पॉजिटिव क्लाइम व्हेन यू आर
Amative that this guy is becoming positive.
अमेटिव कि साला ये पॉजिटिव हो रहा है।
It must have looked to him like he was fickling.
उसको ऐसा दिखा होगा कि वो फिकल कर रहा है।
so you must have said that I will wait
तो यू मस्ट हैव सेड कि मैं वेट करता हूं
This is only becoming positive. I then I call
यह पॉजिटिव ही हो रहा है। मैं तब मैं कॉल
I will get it out. he wouldn't have called out
आउट करूंगा। उसने नहीं कॉल आउट किया होगा
Till then maybe I will give him something
तब तक हो सकता है देन आई एम उसका कुछ
There might have been some trouble. So friend, there is one in Boeing
दिक्कत हुई होगी। तो यार बोइंग में एक
There is a procedure that happens in any engine
प्रोसीजर होता है दैट कुछ भी इंजन में
A malfunction occurs. you have to secure that
खराबी होती है। यू हैव टू सिक्योर दैट
engine. And it should not get damaged. and one
इंजन। और डैमेज ना हो जाए। एंड एक
Such an incident has happened before in Gore
इंसिडेंट पहले ऐसा हो चुका है गोर में
At 3000 feet in Delhi. they lost engine one
दिल्ली में एट 3000 फीट। दे लॉस्ट इंजन वन
Due to birds. whatever engine got damaged
ड्यू टू बर्ड्स। वो इंजन डैमेज हुआ जो भी
hua in the process of securing the
हुआ इन द प्रोसेस ऑफ सिक्योरिंग दे
Secure the Wrong Engine. Oh shh it's done.
सिक्योर द रॉन्ग इंजन। ओ श ये हो चुका है।
Oh wow that plane didn't land. Yes
ओह वाओ वो प्लेन लैंड किया नहीं गया। हां
Brother that day the biggest accident happened in India
भाई उस दिन इंडिया में सबसे बड़ा हादसा
Would. But that did not happen. So Captain Senior
होता। बट वो हुआ नहीं। तो कैप्टन सीनियर
Was. Yes. And so this was
था। हां। और ये था तो
He cut the wrong reason brother first
उसने गलत रीजन काट दिया भाई ने फर्स्ट
The officer did. and there is a little tense situation
ऑफिसर ने। और थोड़ी टेंस सिचुएशन होती है
No. It is difficult to explain this in a podcast
ना। ये एक पडकास्ट में बैठ के समझाना थोड़ा
It becomes difficult. a jab in a cockpit
डिफिकल्ट होता है। एक कॉकपिट में एक जब
A little later, things move very fast. these 150
थोड़ा एंड थिंग्स मूव वैरी फास्ट। ये 150
Work would have been going on at the speed of 200 notes
200 नोट्स की स्पीड में काम हो रहा होता
Is. the ship is moving forward and you are falling
है। जहाज आगे जा रहे हो एंड यू आर फॉलिंग
There is a lot of work behind it. End
बिहाइंड और बहुत सारे काम होते हैं। एंड
Take off and landing is a critical phase.
टेक ऑफ इन लैंडिंग इज़ अ क्रिटिकल फेस।
Right? There are 1000 tasks to be done and even in that if
राइट? 1000 काम होते हैं और उसमें भी अगर
If you get stuck then those 1000 tasks are missed. These
आप स्टक हो गए तो वो 1000 काम छूट गया। ये
Was left. Then you are more stressed. so like this
छूट गया। फिर आप और टेंशन हो। तो ऐसा
They say friend that the first sense you lose is
बोलते हैं यार कि द फर्स्ट सेंस यू लूज़ इज़
The Sense of Hearing. We are here, right? you class
द सेंस ऑफ़ हियरिंग। हम है ना? आप क्लास
I am the teacher teaching or she is speaking
में टीचर पढ़ा रही है या वो बोल रही है
In your ears. But if your attention
आपके कानों में। लेकिन आपका ध्यान अगर
If it is happening somewhere then you will not hear it
कहीं हो रहा है तो फिर यू विल नॉट हियर
You. so he did every action in the cockpit with
यू। तो उसने एव्री एक्शन इन द कॉकपेट विद
Concerning critical systems is a backup
कंसर्निंग टू क्रिटिकल सिस्टम इज़ अ बैकअप
that you ah you're the captain. I am the first officer
कि आप अह आप कैप्टन हो। मैं फर्स्ट ऑफिसर
Am. So engine one has failed. I have to
हूं। सो इंजन वन हैज़ फेल्ड। आई हैव टू
Secure Engine Two. I will say captain confirm
सिक्योर इंजन टू। आई विल से कैप्टन कंफर्म
Number two. so you are supposed to look and
नंबर टू। सो यू आर सपोज्ड टू लुक एंड
confirm that i am holding the right and then
कंफर्म दैट आई एम होल्डिंग द राइट एंड देन
You said confirmed captain. So the guy saw it
यू सेड कंफर्म कैप्टन। तो उस बंदे ने देखा
Even after seeing it I said wrong. He said
भी देख के भी गलत ही बोल दिया। उसने कहा
Confirmed. He grabbed two. He had to cut the forest.
कंफर्म। उसने टू पकड़ा। उसको वन काटना था।
So the bird entered the forest. We are that flame
तो वन में तो चिड़िया घुस गई। हम वो फ्लेम
I am out. Two he caught the captain confirmed
आउट हो गया। टू इसने पकड़ा कैप्टन कंफर्म
and if it cuts it then the aircraft is in
और टू इसने काट दिया तो एयरक्राफ्ट इज इन
Flight without any engine. oh wow captain
फ्लाइट विदाउट एनी इंजन। ओ वाओ तो कैप्टन
He says this is Airbus' redundancy
वो कहता है कि एयरबस की ये रिडेंडेंसी है
So the spool was going down on engine number two and
तो स्पूल डाउन हो रहा था इंजन नंबर टू और
This is so if you have not come below 43%
ऐसा है कि 43% के नीचे अगर नहीं आए हो आप
If you put it again, it will come again. get up
दोबारा डाल दोगे तो दोबारा आ जाएगा। उठ
I will go again. He will get up. ok ok ok.
जाएगा दोबारा। उठ जाएगा। अच्छा ठीक ठीक।
Sir, just need to add fuel. yes right. Ok.
सर सिर्फ फ्यूल डालना है। हां राइट। ओके।
That's wind milling. just add fuel
वो इट्स विंड मिलिंग। सिर्फ फ्यूल डालना
Is. Ok. Got it. It is not so in this
है। ठीक है। गॉट इट। इसमें ऐसा नहीं है
At Boeing. Well, it is in Boeing only. Yes.
बोइंग में। अच्छा बोइंग में ही है। हां।
Correct. So he saw what was happening
ठीक। तो उसने देखा ये क्या-क्या हो रहा तो
The captain noticed because there was sound as well
कैप्टन का ध्यान गया बिकॉज़ साउंड भी होती
yes, everything happens. you lose also she
है सब कुछ होता है। यू लूज़ आल्सो उसने
If I put it again then I put it in another
दोबारा और डाल दिया तो डाला तो साला दूसरी
Bar start well fault occurred and it tore a bit more
बार स्टार्ट वेल फॉल्ट आ गई थोड़ी और फटी
He did that by pitching the aircraft down so that
उसने किया एयरक्राफ्ट पिच डाउन किया ताकि
wind milling ho again it came back then
विंड मिलिंग हो दोबारा फिर इट केम बैक देन
they land it back safely oh wow they did if
दे लैंड इट बैक सेफली ओह वाओ दे डिड अगर
If he is not there that day then another what
उस दिन वो नहीं होता तो फिर एक और व्हाट
Be in Delhi Be in Delhi Yes Think and Land
बी इन दिल्ली इन दिल्ली हां सोचो और लैंड
and why did he land near them brother
करते और वो क्यों लैंड हो गए भाई उनके पास
they were at 3000 feet they had the altitude
दे वर एट 3000 फीट दे हैड दी ऑल्टीट्यूड
these guys had altitude
था उनके पास इन लोग के पास ऑल्टीट्यूड
It was not there friend, I was at 400 feet, what could I do
नहीं था यार 400 फीट पे थे यार क्या कर
You can do it not at 400 feet but at 3000 feet
सकते हो आप 400 फीट पे नहीं अगर 3000 पे
What difference would it have made if it had happened, brother?
होता तो क्या डिफरेंस होता भाई क्या आप
manubar can you do something can you do a little something
मनुबर कर सकते हो थोड़ा सा कुछ कर सकते हो
Brother, I would say that Sabarmati is right there
भाई मैं तो कहता हूं यार साबरमती है वहीं
But if I had gone, something would have happened to Hasan
पे अगर चले जाते हसन वाला ही कुछ हो जाता
Something would have happened, there would have been a field somewhere
कुछ तो कुछ तो होता कि कहीं फील्ड होती
if there was a farm somewhere I would have dropped it right
कहीं खेत होता कहीं तो उतार देते राइट
right right right right right now in that case
राइट राइट राइट राइट राइट अब उस केस में
Friend, that incident which happened with Go Air
यार उस उस जो इंसिडेंट हुआ गो एयर का ना
I took that as well very conveniently.
उसको भी बड़ी कन्वीनिएंटली जितना मैंने
Narrated it to you or as much as the audience is watching
आपको नरेट किया या जितना ऑडियंस देख रही
By making a pilot error you close the chapter
है पायलट एरर करके आप चैप्टर क्लोज कर
can you do it brother yes you can
सकते हो कर सकते हो ना भाई हां कर सकते हो
yes, as much as I have just told you the facts
हां जितनी अभी अभी फैक्ट जितना मैंने तेरे
I told you yes ok but but friend
को बताया हां ठीक ठीक लेकिन लेकिन यार
there is that is not a purpose of
देयर इज दैट इज नॉट अ पर्पस ऑफ
Investigation. Those guys were bored at night
इन्वेस्टिगेशन। उन बंदों ने बोर से रात को
Had taken off.
टेक ऑफ किया था।
Had come to Delhi. Landed at 3:00. 5:00
दिल्ली आए थे। 3:00 बजे लैंड किए थे। 5:00
Then the departure was at 8 o'clock and we were going to Bombay.
बजे का फिर डिपार्चर था बॉम्बे जा रहे थे।
so now that's why the one who is now Air India's
सो नाउ इसीलिए वो जो अभी एयर इंडिया का
of scheduling which they can of
स्केेड्यूलिंग का जो उन्होंने कैन ऑफ
The bombs have been opened. Scheduling opens
बॉम्ब्स खोला है। स्ेड्यूलिंग खुलती है
Brother. What are you guys doing back there?
भाई। वहां तुम लोग कर क्या रहे हो पीछे?
Are you guys making a schedule like this?
क्या तुम लोग ऐसा स्केेड्यूल बना रहे हो?
Brother, the guy who took off at night 12:00
भाई जिस बंदे ने रात को टेक ऑफ किया 12:00
Landed at 3:00 and arrived at 5:00
बजे 3:00 बजे लैंड किया है और 5:00 बजे
I have taken off. it is not a very good time
टेक ऑफ करा है। इट इज नॉट अ वेरी गुड टाइम
To be attentive. You would even measure our fatigue
टू बी अटेंटिव। हम फटीग भी आप मेजर करते
yes. Is this a routine thing for the airline?
हो। क्या यह एयरलाइन का ऐसा रूटीन है कि
You are making the pilots fly like this.
तुम ऐसे ही फ्लाई करा रहे हो पायलट्स को।
Are you following the regulations?
क्या तुम जो रेगुलेशन है उसके हिसाब से
Are you even scheduling? how is the rostering going
स्ेड्यूल कर भी रहे हो? रोस्टरिंग कैसी चल
Is it happening? So that's why all these letters are opened
रही है? तो इसीलिए ये सब चिट्ठे खुलते हैं
And then it turns out friend it is more of a
और फिर निकलता है यार ये इट इज़ मोर ऑफ़ अ
part of what is your culture
पार्ट ऑफ कि तुम्हारा कल्चर क्या है
The airline's? I get it. Isn't it? If I
एयरलाइन का? आई गेट इट। है ना? अगर मैं
I am making you fly every night. So
तुमको रोज रात को फ्लाई करा रहा हूं। तो
It won't work, brother. I am also following
नहीं चलेगा ना भाई। मैं फॉलो कर भी रहा
Am. Because it is proving that psychedelics
हूं। क्योंकि इट इज़ प्रोविंग कि साइकेडियन
You are not very attentive in law. Psychadion
लॉ में यू आर नॉट वेरी अटेंट। साइकेडियन
Law is from 3 to 6 in the morning. Right?
लॉ इज़ फ्रॉम 3 टू 6 इन द मॉर्निंग। राइट?
No matter how much you sleep during the day, brother brain
तुम कितना भी दिन में सो लो भाई दिमाग
That much you are not that identical. so here
उतना यू आर नॉट दैट आइडेंटिव। तो यहां पे
What I am saying is that firstly on the ground
मैं क्या कह रहा हूं कि एक तो ग्राउंड पे
India failed. Let's Come Back Band.
फेल हुआ इंडिया। लेट्स कम बैक बैक बैंड।
Failed after a V1. He took off
एक वी1 के बाद फेल हुआ। उन्होंने टेक ऑफ
what happened and the same thing might have happened with the aircraft
किया एंड सेम चीज कुछ हुआ होगा एयरक्राफ्ट
his attention was diverted from the landing gear and
में उनका ध्यान लैंडिंग गियर से हटा और
He and Boeing have systems that you can use to power the engine
उसने और बोइंग में सिस्टम है कि आप इंजन
Do you secure it? and brother in airbust then
सिक्योर करते हो। और भाई एयरबस्ट में तो
Yes it is not a memory item. you book
है इट इज़ नॉट अ मेमोरी आइटम। आप किताब
When you open the iPad, everything comes out. And
खोलते हो या तो आईपैड सब कुछ आता है। और
It appears completely on your screen. Aircraft
आपकी स्क्रीन में पूरा आता है। एयरक्राफ्ट
Tells you what to do. it's that smart
टेल्स यू व्हाट टू डू। इट्स दैट स्मार्ट
and once you do it it knows what you have done
एंड वंस यू डू इट इट नोस व्हाट यू हैव डन
it will remove that from ji theek hai na got
इट विल रिमूव दैट फ्रॉम जी ठीक है ना गॉट
got it tuck it's way easy or boing me
गॉट इट टक ट इट्स वै ईजी या बोइंग में
It says this is a memory item, remember it, remember it
कहता है ये मेमोरी आइटम है याद रखो याद
If you keep it then there are some memory items like
रखो तो देयर आर सम मेमोरी आइटम्स लाइक
if i remember the whole airbus in airbus
एयरबस में पूरे एयर बस में इफ आई रिमेंबर
there are only nine memory items
देयर आर ओनली नाइन मेमोरी आइटम्स सिर्फ नौ
These are the things you have to remember, everyone else
ऐसी चीजें तुम्हें याद रखनी है बाकी सब
Brother, try to use your brain after looking at some books.
कुछ भाई किताब से देख के करना दिमाग लगाना
Memory is not good in this case brother
ही नहीं है अच्छा इस केस में भाई मेमोरी
If it is an item then it says memory item that
आइटम है तो वो मेमोरी आइटम बोलता है कि
let's assume the pilot flying is the captain
लेट्स अस्यूम पायलट फ्लाइंग इज़ कैप्टन
Pilot non flying and pilot monitoring
पायलट नॉन फ्लाइंग और पायलट मॉनिटरिंग
say is a first officer do action
बोलते हैं इज़ अ फर्स्ट ऑफिसर दो एक्शन
Two actions of the First Officer and two of the Captain
फर्स्ट ऑफिसर के दो एक्शन कैप्टन के तो
The captain says to turn off the thrust lever
कैप्टन कहता है कि थ्रस्ट लीवर उसको ऑफ कर
will give because the thrust levers are automatic
देगा क्योंकि थ्रस्ट लीवर उनकी ऑटोमेटिक
It moves. him off and then put thrust
मूव होती है। उसको ऑफ एंड देन पुट थ्रस्ट
Levers to idle. Thrust lever control
लीवर्स टू आइडल। थ्रस्ट लीवर का कंट्रोल
Always the pilot is flying and all that
ऑलवेज पायलट फ्लाइंग हैज़ और ये सब
Emergency Pilot Haze. So, an emergency occurred.
इमरजेंसी पायलट हैज़। सो इमरजेंसी हो गई।
This guy puts thrust lever to idle. pilot
दिस गाय पुट थ्रस्ट लीवर टू आइडल। पायलट
Non flying and pilot monitoring. his work
नॉन फ्लाइंग और पायलट मॉनिटरिंग। उसका काम
The fuel shut off valve is cut. we sleep
होता है फ्यूल शट ऑफ वेल्व कट। हम सो
Cutting off the fuel. and then there is an engine
कटिंग ऑफ द फ्यूल। एंड देन एक कोई इंजन
The secure or fire damage button is the push.
सिक्योर या फायर डैमेज बटन होता है द पुश।
So those are non-reversible actions. If this
सो दोज़ आर नॉन रिवर्सिबल एकशंस। अगर इसने
Number one has also been cut which we have failed and
नंबर वन का भी काटा जो फेल हुआ है हम और
That brother gave good engine fuel set of help
उस भाई ने गुड इंजन का फ्यूल सेट ऑफ हेल्प
If you cut it then both of them are gone, brother. Good
काट दिया तो दोनों गए ना भाई। अच्छा
write right right to that extant human
राइट राइट राइट टू दैट एक्सटेंट ह्यूमन
There might be an error. yes so to me what we are
एरर हो सकती है। हां तो मुझे जो हम अपने
I have included it in the video because brother its
मैंने वीडियो में इसमें क्योंकि भाई इसके
I don't understand anything other than
अलावा मुझे कुछ समझ में नहीं आ रहा क्या
It is possible after that it might happen again
हो सकता है। उसके बाद तो फिर हो सकता है
This must be wrong. Right? But as much as my knowledge
ये गलत ही हो। राइट? बट जितनी मेरी नॉलेज
I will try to analyse till that. so me
है आई ट्राई टू एनालाइज टिल दैट। तो मुझे
So, I understand that this is what happened, brother.
तो ये समझ में आ रहा है कि भाई ये हुआ
will be. and that's the only reason they could have
होगा। एंड दैट्स द ओनली रीज़न दे कुड हैव
It was in Gone Down Go Air that they
गॉन डाउन गो एयर में था कि उन्होंने
I posted it again, it's here but it's irreversible
दोबारा डाल दिया आ गया बट ये इरिवर्सिबल
Actually, because you are at 400 feet height.
है एक्चुअली क्योंकि आप 400 फीट पे ही हो
So you don't have time, hey it's irreversible
तो आपके पास टाइम नहीं अरे इरिवर्सिबल है
Be it 400 or 1000, it is irreversible
चाहे 400 हो चाहे 1000 हो ये इरिवर्सिबल
I cut off the fuel shut off valve and it started to fire
है फ्यूल शट ऑफ वाल्व काट दी और वो फायर
The button you pushed is irreversible
बटन जो पुश कर दिया आपने वो इरिवर्सबल है
He came back to the ground and the engineer was fine
वो फिर ग्राउंड में आके इंजीनियर ही ठीक
can do it well okay so if you have fuel
कर सकता है अच्छा ओके तो अगर आपने फ्यूल
If you close the valve you can't open it again
वाल्व बंद कर दिया तो आप दोबारा नहीं खोल
I can do that. Then there is another button which says Engine
सकते उसको। उसके बाद एक और बटन है जो इंजन
There is some damage to the button. well that's secure
डैमेज कुछ होता है बटन। अच्छा वो सिक्योर
The button is done. Yes. After that he is
बटन हो जाता है। हां। उसके बाद वो तो
what i have proposed this that may be that
व्हाट आई हैव प्रपोज्ड दिस कि मे बी दैट
must have happened but coming back to that if
मस्ट हैव हैपेंड बट कमिंग बैक टू कि अगर
Even if there is height, so there is a lawyer guy
हाइट होती भी सो देयर इज़ अ लॉयर हुस्
Handling my case also. he has filed
हैंडलिंग माय केस आल्सो। ही हैज़ फाइल्ड
Lot of PIL in Mumbai High Court. He Said
लॉट ऑफ़ पीआईएल इन मुंबई हाई कोर्ट। ही सेड
there are lots of buildings which should not
देयर आर लॉट ऑफ़ बिल्डिंग्स व्हिच शुड नॉट
Be there. Airports Authority of India has
बी देयर। एयरपोर्ट अथॉरिटी ऑफ़ इंडिया हैज़
Given left right center permission. where is he
गिवेन लेफ्ट राइट सेंटर परमिशन। वो कहां
Did you give it to me? Land is expensive in Mumbai.
से दे दी? लैंड इज़ एक्सपेंसिव इन मुंबई।
Hmm hmm. and you know nobody wants to leave
हम्म हम्म। एंड यू नो नोबडी वांट्स टू लीव
I will build 10 floors on the land,
लैंड कि वहां पे मैं 10 माले बनाऊंगा,
I will make five floors. It is not approved there
पांच माले बनाऊंगा। वहां अप्रूव्ड नहीं है
Because that is an airport area that is empty
क्योंकि वो एयरपोर्ट का एरिया है कि खाली
Should be. You will go to any other country
होना चाहिए। बाकी किसी देश में आप जाओगे
So it does not happen that the airport is finished.
तो ऐसा नहीं होता कि एयरपोर्ट खत्म हुआ।
A building has again been constructed on the perimeter wall. They
पेरीमीटर वॉल पे फिर बिल्डिंग बनी है। वो
It happens here. but then that
यहां हो जाता है। बट देन दैट
The builder thing is such a big society
बिल्डर थिंग इतना बड़ा सोसाइटी का वो है
that no one wants to talk about it
कि उस पे ना कोई बात करना चाहता है ना
Someone wants to get into it. take the matter
उसमें कोई घुसना चाहता है। बात तो लेके
Brother, same thing happened in Ahmedabad too.
भाई यही है कि अहमदाबाद में भी यही हुआ
No. I just woke up and asked sister, how come she is so beautiful
ना। अभी दीदी से जागा कि यार कैसे इतनी
How did big buildings come? If not even
बड़ी बिल्डिंग्स कैसे आ गई? अगर नहीं भी
There would have been a little forest and trees as well
होती, थोड़ा सा जंगल भी होता, पेड़-वेढ़े भी
Would have been. Brother, even trees would not have absorbed it
होते। भाई, पेड़ भी ना अब्सॉर्ब कर लेते
There is impact. if there were trees or forests
हैं इंपैक्ट को। अगर पेड़ या जंगल भी होते
No, hmm. There would have been damage, but we wouldn't have
ना, हम्म। डैमेज होता, बट वी वुड नॉट हैव
Lost so many lives. we lost everyone
लॉस्ट सो मेनी लाइफ्स। वी लॉस्ट एव्री
Life Actually. Only one is left. Butt so much loss
लाइफ एक्चुअली। एक ही बचा है। बट इतना लॉस
There isn't an off life. in case if this jungle
ऑफ़ लाइफ नहीं होता। इन केस अगर ये जंगल
or if it were an open field, would this land
होता या खुला मैदान होता तो क्या ये लैंड
Would? Yes, land. of crash landing
होता? हां, लैंड। क्रैश लैंडिंग का
It's a procedure, brother. The procedure remains
प्रोसीजर है ना भाई। प्रोसीजर रहता है हम
It's good to practice crash landing
प्रैक्टिस करते हैं क्रैश लैंडिंग अच्छा
Practice crash landings. No
क्रैश लैंडिंग में प्रैक्टिस करते हैं। नो
so you are telling me if here
सो यू आर टेलिंग मी अगर यहां पे
There are no buildings and if there is empty ground
बिल्डिंग्स नहीं होती और अगर खाली मैदान
If it had happened then all this wouldn't have happened. yes then take it off
होता तो ये सब नहीं होता। हां तो उतार
giving damage where the ship breaks landing
देते जहां जहाज टूटता लैंडिंग के डैमेज
If the wing breaks, we will save ourselves by evacuating
होती विंग-विंग टूटता इवाक्युएट करते बच
Would go.
जाते।
Good. What else? Brother it feels like that
अच्छा। और क्या? भाई हमें ऐसा लग रहा है
that once that visual comes and not now
कि एक बार जब वो विसुअल आता है ना कि अब
It's going straight like this. at that point
ये ऐसे सीधा जा रहा है। एट दैट पॉइंट
End. Nothing can be saved. at this point
खत्म। कुछ नहीं बच सकता। एट दिस पॉइंट
Like now your death sentence has been written.
लाइक अब आपका डेथ सेंटेंस लिख दिया गया।
but I didn't know if that was because a
बट मेरे को नहीं पता था कि अगर क्योंकि एक
There is a very famous story about Sali who
बड़ी फेमस स्टोरी है ना वो सली की जो उसने
The plane landed in Hutson. he became a
हटसन में लैंड किया था प्लेन। ही बिकम अ
hero after that and i thought that was the
हीरो आफ्टर दैट एंड आई थॉट दैट वाज़ द
The exception is that you can do something like this.
एक्सेप्शन कि आप ऐसा कुछ कर सकते हैं।
Water landing was exception. Good Water
वाटर लैंडिंग वाज़ एक्सेप्शन। अच्छा वॉटर
Landing is an exception. Ditching Procedure
लैंडिंग इज़ एक्सेप्शन। डिचिंग का प्रोसीजर
Yes bro proper. This is the procedure of ditching.
है ब्रो प्रॉपर। डिचिंग का प्रोसीजर है।
What happens in that? a you have to
व्हाट हैप्पेंस इन दैट? अ यू हैव टू
Secure the aircraft. first of all that
सिक्योर दी एयरक्राफ्ट। फर्स्ट ऑफ आल कि
What can you secure in the cockpit?
कॉकपिट में क्या-क्या सिक्योर कर सकते हो।
now i don't remember that much if one
अब मेरे को इतना याद नहीं है टू अगर एक
Add the bar. yes please write. Procedure
बार डालिए। हां प्लीज लिखना। प्रोसीजर
Airus 320 Dali QRH And So For Now
एयरस 320 डाली क्यूआरएच एंड सो फॉर नाउ
Your guess is that he first needs to remove the engine valve
योर गेस इज कि उसको पहले इंजन का वाल्व
He had to shut down the other engine
बंद करना था उसने दूसरे इंजन का कर दिया
The first engine had already gone off because that
पहला इंजन वैसे ही ऑफ हो चुका था बिकॉज़ वो
It took a long time to take off after V1
V1 के बाद टेक ऑफ किया है काफी टाइम एंड
so that led to dual engine failure that's your
सो दैट लेड टू डुअल इंजन फेलियर दैट्स योर
guess probably that's my guess i also
गेस प्रोबेब्ली दैट्स माय गेस आई आल्सो
think brother as a pilot you know what you will be
थिंक भाई एज अ पायलट यू नो वेदर दैट बी यू
Weather that be yes there is also a ditching button
वेदर दैट बी हां एक डिचिंग बटन भी होता है
I remember now yes that was the ditching
मुझे अब याद आ रहा है हां वो डालिए डिचिंग
Procedure Q QR Put QRH
प्रोसीजर क्यू क्यूआर पुट क्यूआरएच
QRH Quebec Romeo Hotel at Capitol
क्यूआरएच क्यूबेक रोमियो होटल कैपिटल में
Yes
हां
This quick reference hand will not come in this
इसमें आएगा नहीं वैसे क्विक रेफरेंस हैंड
yes look in this it came down quickly
हां इसमें देख नीचे आ गया ना क्विक
The reference handbook would be the complete procedure
रेफरेंस हैंड बुक वो पूरा प्रोसीजर होता
hey bro yes this out flow well stop it
है ब्रो हां यह आउट फ्लो वैल बंद करो ये
Everybody close this cabin or this is the exact
सब बंद करो ये कैबिन या दिस इज़ द एक्सैक्ट
Procedure Ditching Button Switch Airbus
प्रोसीजर डिचिंग बटन स्विच एयरबस
aircraft of ditching buttons and switches that
एयरक्राफ्ट ऑफ डिचिंग बटन और स्विच दैट
When activated automatically then ditching button
व्हेन एक्टिवेटेड ऑटोमेटिक तो डिचिंग बटन
If Airbus has made it, yes, then it is a procedure
अगर एयरबस ने बनाया है हां तो प्रोसीजर है
no bro yes right right right na outflew
ना भाई हां राइट राइट राइट ना आउटफ्ल्ल्व
This is the out flow valve which is your
ये आउट फ्ल्लो वैल्व होती है जो आपका
Cabin pressure to pressure ram air pressure
प्रेशर रैम एयर प्रेशर में कैबिन प्रेशर
Whatever is maintained, it maintains it
जो मेंटेन करते हैं ना उसको मेंटेन करती
It has to maintain proper cabin pressure
है उसको प्रॉपर कैबिन प्रेशर मेंटेन करना
is it planted ditching or unplanted ditching
है प्लांट डिचिंग है कि अनप्लांट डिचिंग
how are you bringing the crew inside joe
है कैसा है यू ब्रिंग द क्रू इनसाइड जो
lead crew hoti u brief her that now
लीड क्रू होती है यू ब्रीफ हर कि अब
We are ditching. so brace for
डिचिंग कर रहे हैं हम। सो ब्रेस फॉर
Impact is the command for ditching. you si
इंपैक्ट इज़ द कमांड फॉर डिचिंग। यू सि
like this and then all that procedure is done
लाइक दिस एंड देन ऑल दैट प्रोसीजर इज़ डन
Ditching ok very interesting. Post
डिचिंग ओके वैरी इंटरेस्टिंग। पोस्ट
Ditching actions are planned and unplanned ditching
डिचिंग एकशंस ये प्लंड अनप्लांड डिचिंग तो
everything happens. After end ditching
सब कुछ होता है। एंड डिचिंग के बाद
Mostly we just evacuate. Yes. So
मोस्टली हम इवेकुएट ही करते हैं। हां। सो
We brief the crew everything. The Crew Briefs
वी ब्रीफ द क्रू एवरीथिंग। क्रू ब्रीफ्स द
Passengers then she reshuffles that yaar emergency
पैसेंजर्स देन शी रिशफल्स कि यार इमरजेंसी
I will make the abled body sit at the exit
एग्जिट पे मैं एबल्ड बॉडी को बिठाऊं जो
Can you help me also? so de de de go through
मेरी हेल्प भी कर सकें। सो दे दे गो थ्रू
give all their procedure turn but ditching hota
दे ऑल देयर प्रोसीजर टर्न बट डिचिंग होता
Is. but from a sim experience if i say
है। बट फ्रॉम अ सिम एक्सपीरियंस इफ से आई
am at 33 and 29 which is generally what people
एम एट 33 और 29 व्हिच इज जनरली व्हाट पीपल
we are flying at and suddenly i begin to
आर फ्लाइंग एट एंड सडनली आई बिगिन टू
Experience and I will have to ditch it.
एक्सपीरियंस और मेरे को डिच करना पड़ेगा।
how much time do i have before i am touching
हाउ मच टाइम डू आई हैव बिफोर आई एम टचिंग
Around? so bro for every 1000 feet eye
अराउंड? सो ब्रो फॉर एव्री 1000 फीट आई
Can cover two nautical miles. so to him
कैन कवर टू नॉटिकल माइल्स। तो उसको
calculate if I am on 30000 then I
कैलकुलेट कर अगर मैं 30,000 पे हूं तो मैं
I can I have a distance of 160 nautical
आई कैन आई हैव अ डिस्टेंस ऑफ़ 160 नॉटिकल
Miles I can go left right two 2.3 60
माइल्स आई कैन गो लेफ्ट राइट टू टू 2.3 60
Nautical Miles Distance Wise and Time
नॉटिकल माइल्स डिस्टेंस वाइज एंड टाइम
wise because I have to brief you by briefing you
वाइज बिकॉज़ आपको ये ब्रीफ करना ब्रीफ करके
Give me all the instructions brother, I will be saved in that
सब इंस्ट्रक्शन देना उसमें भाई मैं बचा
I will take the plane, don't worry, yes there is a pilot
लूंगा जहाज को टेंशन मत लो हां एक पायलट
If you get 3000 feet of time
अगर तुम मैं 3000 फीट का टाइम मिला ना
I have had so much training that I
मुझे मेरी इतनी ट्रेनिंग हुई है कि मैं
If I save myself then I will have confidence in myself too
बचा लूंगा तो मुझे अपने ऊपर भी कॉन्फिडेंस
I have confidence in my training
है एक अपनी ट्रेनिंग पे कॉन्फिडेंस है
Sorry, I have confidence in my training
सॉरी एक अपनी ट्रेनिंग पे कॉन्फिडेंस है
and then my scanning starts that
एंड देन मेरी स्कैनिंग चालू हो जाती है कि
Where will I stay, I will land the ship and it will be like this
मैं कहां रहूं उतारूंगा जहाज को और वो ऐसा
Not even when I'm flying normally
नहीं है जब मैं नॉर्मली भी फ्लाई कर रहा
I am there and I don't have anyone at 60 miles
होता हूं ना और मुझे 60 माइल पे कोई ना
We will find an airport, friend, right?
कोई एयरपोर्ट मिल जाएगा ना यार हम राइट
Surely, somewhere, someone is telling me a little
श्योर कहीं ना कहीं कोई मुझे छोटी सी
You will find a field, right right right brother
फील्ड मिल जाएगी कोई राइट राइट राइट भाई
When ours is one and not inbuilt
जब हमारी जब एक एक होता है ना कि इनबिल्ट
some things happen i'm going over
हो जाती है कुछ चीजें मैं ऊपर जा रहा हूं
I'm going to Iran or I'm going to Turkey
मैं ईरान जा रहा हूं या मैं टर्की जा रहा
I'm going somewhere I'm going to Europe
हूं मैं कहीं जा रहा हूं मैं यूरोप जा रहा
I'm flying over some country
हूं मैं किसी देश के ऊपर से फ्लाई कर रहा
what do I do in my free time
हूं खाली टाइम में मैं क्या करता हूं तुम
What do you do in your free time, brother? That map
क्या करते हैं खाली टाइम में भाई वो मैप
let's take it out and see ok i can fly here
निकाल के देखते हैं अच्छा मैं यहां फ्लाई
I am doing it right now, if I fail then I
कर रहा हूं इस समय अगर फेल हो जाए तो मैं
I can go here, ok put it here
यहां जा सकता हूं यहां अच्छा डालियो यहां
How much time will it take so we keep doing this
पे कितना टाइम लगेगा तो वी कीप डूइंग दिस
calculation ok ok ok so it's not like that
कैलकुलेशन अच्छा अच्छा अच्छा सो ऐसा नहीं
We are sitting unprepared. right right
हम अनप्रिपेयर्ड बैठे हुए हैं। राइट राइट
Right right right right right. So we
राइट राइट राइट राइट राइट। तो हम
We are prepared every time. at everybody
प्रिपयर्ड होते हैं हर टाइम पे। एट एव्री
check point i calculate my fuel which
चेक पॉइंट आई कैलकुलेट माय फ्यूल कि जो
Is it matching what happened or not?
हुआ था जो है मैच कर रहा है कि नहीं।
Interesting. Ok. So, it means 10 hours like this
इंटरेस्टिंग। ओके। तो मतलब ऐसे 10 घंटे की
What will you do during the flight? What would you do?
फ्लाइट में क्या करोगे टाइम? क्या करोगे?
Yes. We also chatted a bit. brother what are you doing
हां। थोड़ी बातें भी कर ली। भाई क्या चल
I have done that too in my life, but only a little
रहा है लाइफ में वो भी कर लिया बट थोड़ा
Got the work done also. and that work is that
काम भी कर लिया। और वो जो काम तो दैट्स
How I know where I am going. I
हाउ आई नो कि मैं कहां जा रहा हूं। मैं
What options do you have basically.
क्या व्हाट ऑप्शंस यू आई हैव बेसिकली।
Right. Right right right. So like Pakistan
राइट। राइट राइट राइट। तो जैसे पाकिस्तान
I fly over the. I'm here bro
के ऊपर से फ्लाई करता हूं। मैं भाई यहां
So I will not take it off. see this after
तो नहीं उतारूंगा। ये देख इसके बाद
Where is the next airport coming? Straight
नेक्स्ट एयरपोर्ट कहां पे आ रहा है? सीधा
Brother, we will land you in Amritsar only, either Amritsar or
अमृतसर ही उतारेंगे भाई या तो अमृतसर या
Hey brother, things happen sometimes in Iran
ईरान बीच में अरे भाई कुछ कभी-कभी हो जाता
Is. Sometimes there's some trouble, right?
है। कभी-कभी कुछ दिक्कत होती है ना अरे
Brother, I will not get down here later
भाई यहां तो नहीं उतारूंगा आगे चलके
I will download it or I will download the page first. Yes
उतारूंगा या पेज पहले उतार दूंगा। हां
right so you always have that in mind that
राइट तो यू ऑलवेज हैव दैट इन माइंड कि
Sometimes it comes to your mind that I am not
होता है आपके दिमाग में कब कभी-कभी मैं ना
I would have been sitting idle like this, looking outside
ऐसे खाली बैठ रहा होता बाहर देख रहा होता
Am. So it's not like I'm looking outside.
हूं। तो ऐसा नहीं मैं बाहर निहार रहा हूं।
so i'm thinking what if i lose an engine
तो आई एम थिंकिंग व्हाट इफ आई लूज एन इंजन
Now. So this is going on in my mind.
नाउ। तो मेरा चल रहा होता है दिमाग में।
When I take off from Assam
जब मैं आसाम से टेक ऑफ करता हूं तो
There is a big island in the middle of the Brahmaputra
ब्रह्मपुत्र के बीच में बड़ा सा आइलैंड है
We do take off in the rain
हम तो टेक ऑफ करते हैं ना बारिशों में तो
I think it might be better if I drop it here
मैं सोचता हूं अच्छा यहां पे उतार सकता
hmm what does your mind keep on doing something or the other
हूं क्या चलता रहता है दिमाग कुछ ना कुछ
If the mischief continues, then brother, we will
खुफात चलती रहती है तो भाई हम इतना
We are prepared to land the ship
प्रिपेयर्ड होते हैं कि उतार देंगे जहाज
You will lose the landing in Ko and Crashing
को और क्रैशिंग में यू विल लूज़ द लैंडिंग
gear but everything else will kind of
गियर बट एवरीथिंग एल्स विल काइंड ऑफ़
Survive yes means people will survive anything
सर्वाइव हां मतलब लोग बच जाएंगे कुछ भी
I will loose but I am so damaged
लूज करूंगा मैं लेकिन मैं इतना डैमेज ऑफ
Property may be damaged but there is damage of life
प्रॉपर्टी हो सकता है बट डैमेज ऑफ लाइफ
It won't happen that much because brother is the most
उतना नहीं होगा गॉट इट क्योंकि भाई सबसे
I'll protect myself first right?
पहले तो मैं अपने आप को बचाऊंगा ना हां
Sure if I survive I will be behind
श्योर अगर मैं बच जाऊंगा ऊंगा तो पीछे
Those left behind will be saved. And I have my own
वाले पीछे बच जाएंगे। और मेरे को तो अपनी
Life is dear to me. right then for yourself
जान प्यारी है ही। राइट तो अपने को तो
I will definitely save you. Sure sure, right?
बचाऊंगा ही बचाऊंगा। श्योर श्योर है ना?
So that's why you tell yourself first
तो इसीलिए बोलते हैं सबसे पहले अपने को
Save because if you are saved everyone will be saved.
बचाओ क्योंकि आप बच गए सब बच जाएंगे।
well so in this case attitude was also
अच्छा तो इस केस में एटीट्यूड वाज़ आल्सो
no issue because you are only at 400 meters
एन इशू क्योंकि आप 400 मीटर पे ही हो तो
If you are at 400 feet then you cannot do anything
आप 400 फीट पे ही हो तो आप कुछ कर ही नहीं
Got it. 400 ft Ahmedabad Elevation 200 ft
पाए। 400 फीट अहमदाबाद एलिवेशन 200 फीट
And 65 is what reports are saying they were
एंड 65 इज़ व्हाट रिपोर्ट्स आर सेइंग दे वर
At. So you were at 400 feet. 400 feet or something
एट। सो 400 फीट पे थे आप। 400 फीट तो कुछ
It doesn't exist. You don't have the time.
है ही नहीं। टाइम ही नहीं है आपके पास।
Such a heavy ship. so you are the heaviest at tech
इतना भारी जहाज। सो यू आर हैविएस्ट एट टेक
Off, right? Right.
ऑफ, राइट? राइट।
You burn 55 tons of fumes at landing then
यू यू बर्न 55 टन्स ऑफ फ्यू एट लैंडिंग तो
You then became at least 55 tonnes lighter. here it is
आप तब एटलीस्ट 55 टन हल्के हो गए। यहां तो
That too is fuel and they are carrying fuel
वो भी फ्यूल है और वो फ्यूल लेके चल रहे
Yes you are. That's why that firewall became so big
हो आप। तभी तो उतना बड़ा वो फायर वाल बना
Because that fuel is fuel. 55 60 tonne
क्योंकि वो फ्यूल फ्यूल है। 55 60 टन का
So the fuel is on you. hum hum what do you
तो फ्यूल है आप पे। हम हम व्हाट डू यू
think about who captain smith is and this
थिंक अबाउट ये जो कैप्टन स्मिथ है एंड दिस
This is my observation. Ok? I Purely
इज़ माय ऑब्जरवेशन। ठीक है? आई प्योरली
From somebody sitting on this side. You x
फ्रॉम समबडी सिटींग ऑन दिस साइड। आप एक्स
Aviation ex pilot that captain steve probably
एवीएशन एक्स पायलट वो कैप्टन स्टीव शायद
Isn't that his name, Captain Steve?
यही नाम है ना उनका कैप्टन स्टीव?
actually can you also check which pilots are this
एक्चुअली कैन यू आल्सो चेक जो पायलट्स इस
His experiences during the flight were
फ्लाइट में थे उनके दे वर एक्सपीरियंस
7 8000 hours 8000 were not pilots but captains
पायलट्स नहीं 7 8000 घंटे 8000 थे कैप्टन
The first officer of the 1100 hours were yes so
के फर्स्ट ऑफिसर के 1100 घंटे थे हां तो
That means it is experienced only, yes
मतलब एक्सपीरियंस्ड ही होता है ये हां
right so i think pilot guy is probably more
राइट तो आई थिंक पायलट आदमी शायद इज मोर
Likely to be like this issue happened in pilot
लाइकली टू बी लाइक ये पायलटरी में इशू हुआ
Maybe like this one from Captain Steve
हो सकता है जैसे शायद कैप्टन स्टीव का ये
say they used flaps instead of non
कहना है कि उन्होंने गैर के बजाय फ्लैप्स
or slats please explain something to me
या स्लैट्स कुछ मेरे को समझाना आप
What to Say Exactly
एक्जेक्टली क्या कहना है
But I am sure that if you are an engineer
बट आई ऍम श्योर कि अगर आप किसी इंजीनियर
If you talk to him, he will find the engineering fault
से बोलोगे वो इंजीनियरिंग फ़ौल्ट निकालेगा
If you speak to an airliner, the airline
आप किसी एयरलाइनर से बोलोगे तो एयरलाइन
Like these are whistle blowers. it might also
जैसे ये विसल ब्लोअर्स हैं। इट माइट आल्सो
be a proximity think about what you do
बी अ प्रॉक्सिमिटी थिंक कि आप व्हाट डू यू
Think for? You Know
थिंक फॉर? यू नो
But what did Captain Steve say that
बट व्हाट व्हाट डिड कैप्टन स्टीव से कि
there has been some error in the sense that
देयर हैज़ बीन सम एरर इन द सेंस कि
They didn't put those wheels up or anything
उन्होंने वो व्हील्स ऊपर नहीं करे या कुछ
yes I think there was a video of him where
हां आई थिंक उनका एक वीडियो आया था जहां
But they say that
पे वो कहते हैं कि
So flap landing has to be done air up
सो फ्लैप लैंडिंग एयर अप करना होता है
After take off positive climb gear up. So
आफ्टर टेक ऑफ पॉजिटिव क्लाइम गियर अप। सो
In this case, the gear itself takes the flaps up.
इनसे ऑफ़ गियर ही टूक द फ्लैप्स अप।
so flap is something which generates more
तो फ्लैप इज समथिंग व्हिच जनरेट्स मोर
Lift at a slower speed. I am but that
लिफ्ट एट अ स्लोअर स्पीड। हम तो बट वो
I don't think that would have happened bro because
मुझे नहीं लगता ब्रो ऐसा हुआ होगा क्योंकि
and i made a video also about that end
एंड आई मेड अ वीडियो आल्सो अबाउट दैट एंड
I don't even know why he said that
मुझे भी नहीं पता उन्होंने ऐसा क्यों कहा
Because there were three or four reasons for that. one is the gear
बिकॉज़ उसके तीन चार रीज़न थे। एक तो गियर
Nor does it happen further. so if i am the first
ना आगे होती है। सो इफ आई एम द फर्स्ट
Officer I have to reach out. end flap right here
ऑफिसर आई हैव टू रीच आउट। एंड फ्लैप यहीं
It happens on pay. So it is not the case that both buttons
पे होता है। तो ऐसा नहीं कि दोनों बटन
I will make mistakes here and there. So
बगल-बगल में मैं मिस्टेक कर दूंगा। तो
number one reason that number two even by mistake
नंबर वन रीज़ दैट नंबर टू गलती से कर भी
Doge na Jahaz will sing 50 feet and then
दोगे ना जहाज विल सिंग 50 फीट एंड देन
Start It Again Slime Won't Go Down
अगेन स्टार्ट इट स्लाइम नीचे नहीं जाएगा
Because we call it Murphy's Law
हम क्योंकि ये वो मर्फीज़ लॉ बोलते हैं ना
that something which has a probability to go
कि समथिंग व्हिच हैज़ अ प्रोबेबिलिटी टू गो
wrong will go wrong this happened this happened
रॉन्ग विल गो रॉन्ग ये हुआ हुआ है ये हुआ
We have new ships with us
है हमारे साथ जहाजों में राइट नए-नए
The first officer comes and makes a mistake
फर्स्ट ऑफिसर आते हैं वो कर देते हैं गलती
If you do it in sim also then and the
सिम में भी कर देते हैं तो एंड दी
Aircraft Surfaces Are Electronically
एयरक्राफ्ट सरफेससेस आर इलेक्ट्रॉनिकली
simulated but they move with hydraulic
सिमुलेटेड बट दे मूव विद हाइड्रोलिक
pressure and it takes time that pressure
प्रेशर एंड इट टेक्स टाइम कि वो प्रेशर
Gaya, they are moving. it's a big motor
गया वो मूव हो रहे हैं। इट्स अ बिग मोटर
It rotates. So do the flap at zero
वो रोटेट होती है। तो फ्लैप जीरो पे करो
It comes slowly. so this happened to me
धीरे-धीरे आती है। तो मेरे साथ हुआ बंदा
had put flaps zero. I said brother
ने डाल दिया था फ्लैप ज़ीरो। मैंने कहा भाई
What are you doing? I pulled it again.
क्या कर रहा है? दोबारा खींच दिया मैंने।
He has come. what is a flap brother? Brother he
वो आ गया। फ्लैप क्या होता है भाई? भाई वो
The wing which stays like this keeps moving.
विंग जो ऐसा रहता है मूव करता रहता है।
Sir that's above the wing, that's the angle of the wing
विंग के ऊपर सर वो तो विंग का वो एंगल
Let me change it. ok ok ok.
चेंज कर देते हैं। अच्छा अच्छा अच्छा।
because whatever we land on
क्योंकि जो हम लोग लैंड करते हैं उसके
Times become straight. same for the track
टाइम सीधे हो जाते हैं। ट्रैक के लिए वही
There is a flap. That's fine. so what is the flap
फ्लैप होता है। वो ठीक है। तो फ्लैप क्या
He says that friend even at low speed it gets more
कहता है कि यार कम स्पीड पे भी ज्यादा
It generates lift. good you are
लिफ्ट जनरेट करता है वो। अच्छा यू आर
Landing at slow speed but you want more
लैंडिंग एट स्लो स्पीड बट यू वांट मोर
So what is the disadvantage of lift?
लिफ्ट तो इसीलिए डिसएडवांटेज क्या है
The drag is greater. Ok? so then if
ड्रैग ज्यादा होता है। ठीक है? तो तो अगर
What will happen if I straighten the flaps?
मैं फ्लैप सीधे कर भी दूंगा तो होगा क्या
That will basically increase the drag. a little bit
कि बेसिकली ड्रैग बढ़ जाएगा। थोड़ी सी
Your lift must be loose, friend. But if the engine
लिफ्ट लूज होगी आपकी यार। लेकिन अगर इंजन
He is running at full power and overtaking
फुल पावर पे चल रहे हैं वो ओवरटेक कर
will take it. He will pull it off, brother. means going like this
लेगा। वो खींच देगा भाई। मतलब ऐसे जा रहे
Yes you are. It will happen. Then you will go upstairs. talk
हो आप। ऐसा होगा। फिर ऊपर चले जाओगे। बात
I didn't understand it, it was a flash, friend. And
समझ में फ्लैश थोड़ी ना हो गया यार। और
What are slats? So the slats wing
स्लैट्स क्या होते हैं? तो स्लैट्स विंग
are in the front and flats are at the back. So
के आगे होते हैं फ्लैट पीछे होते हैं। तो
Yaar is slat slabs system. one comes
यार स्लैट स्लैब्स सिस्टम होता है। एक आता
yes this one is coming. Yes. so they increase the
है ये एक आता है। हां। सो दे इंक्रीज़ द के
Chamber of the Wing. So the Bernoulli principle is
चेंबर ऑफ़ द विंग। तो बर्नोलीज़ प्रिंसिपल
You must have read it. Didn't he read it? Bernoulli's
पढ़ा होगा। वो नहीं पढ़ा क्या? बर्नोलीज़
Yes. Bernoulli I know about him. yes so
हां। बर्नोली मेरे को पता है उसके। हां तो
It is that one, right? So wing it happens like this right yes.
वही है ना। तो विंग ऐसा होता है ना हां।
So the stage moves faster from top than from bottom
तो ऊपर से स्टेज जाता है नीचे से धीमा तो
In physics he can change the shape of the wing
फिजिक्स के तो वो विंग का शेप चेंज कर
Gives. yes i see and it increases the
देता है। हां आई सी एंड इट इंक्रीसेस द
Lift. I am amazing. ok at least. Now
लिफ्ट। आई एम असुमिंग। अच्छा एट लो। अब
Like this was Flight 171 Air India 171, right?
जैसे ये फ्लाइट 171 एयर इंडिया 171 था ना?
Now when will its investigation take place? that when
अब इसकी भाई इन्वेस्टिगेशन कब होगी? कि कब
is pay like when will we get any kind of
इस पे लाइक व्हेन विल वी गेट एनी काइंड ऑफ़
Certainty because we are still in theory
सर्टेनिटी बिकॉज़ वी आर स्टिल इन थ्योरी
land and the dominant theory is that it's a
लैंड एंड द डोमिनेंट थ्योरी इज़ दैट इट्स अ
Double engine failure right that's a dominator
डबल इंजन फेलियर राइट दैट्स अ डोमिन
Now I know from some YouTube videos I
नाउ आई नो फ्रॉम सम YouTube वीडियोस आई
have seen sometime that there is a black in it
हैव सीन समटाइम कि इसमें देयर इज़ अ ब्लैक
The Box That Is Always Recovered which probably contains
बॉक्स दैट इज़ ऑलवेज रिकवर्ड जिसमें शायद
Audio recording or punching in the machine
ऑडियो रिकॉर्डिंग या जो मशीन में पंचिंग
all that happened and then there is something else
हुई है वो सब एंड देन देयर इज़ समथिंग एल्स
called an acr ams cvr cvr meaning
कॉल्ड एन एसीआर एएमएस सीवीआर सीवीआर मतलब
something like this there is some equipment which
कुछ इस तरीके के देयर इज़ सम इक्विपमेंट जो
those who come out of the cockpit
कॉकपिट में से निकल के आते हैं जिनके
Now investment is done on this basis. Cause
बेसिस पे अब इन्वेस्ट िगेशन होती है। कॉज
The nail is down.
नेल डाउन किया जाता है।
What is the timeline and something like that?
व्हाट इज द टाइमलाइन एंड समथिंग लाइक दैट?
when would we know about something like that
व्हेन वुड वी नो अबाउट समथिंग लाइक दैट
would you expect for this to be the case
वुड यू एक्सपेक्ट फॉर टू बी इन दोज़
Things? yaar initial report i think 30
थिंग्स? यार इनिशियल रिपोर्ट आई थिंक 30
It should come in days. but i was surprised
डेज में आ जानी चाहिए। बट आई वास सरप्राइज
to know who will give the CVR and DFDR
टू नो कि वो जो सीवीआर और डीएफडीआर सो दे
R to boxes. CVR & DFDR.
आर टू बॉक्सेस। सीवीआर एंड डीएफडीआर।
CVR is cockpit voice recorder. Ok? So
सीवीआर इज़ कॉकपेट वॉइस रिकॉर्डर। ओके? सो
When I used to fly, there used to be last two
जब मैं फ्लाई करता था तब उसमें लास्ट टू
Communication for hours was recorded.
आवर्स तक की कम्युनिकेशन रिकॉर्ड होती थी।
Now it can even last for 25 hours. be advance
अब 25 घंटे की भी हो जाती है। एडवांस हो
Everything is gone. And then there is a DFDR
गया सब कुछ। एंड देन देयर इज अ डीएफडीआर
including whatever happened on your flight
जिसमें कि आपके फ्लाइट में जो भी हुआ है
Some such action has taken place which was done by the pilots
ऐसा कुछ एक्शन हुआ है जो कि पायलट्स ने
I did not take it but I do software internally too
नहीं लिया बट सॉफ्टवेयर इंटरनली भी करते
Are. Everything is recorded. His
हैं। सारा कुछ रिकॉर्डेड होता है। उसका
Pitch Bank Roll Engine Power How Much Fuel
पिच बैंक रोल इंजन की पावर कितना फ्यूल
Gone are the left, right, everything. well it's locked
गया लेफ्ट राइट सब कुछ। अच्छा वो लॉक है
Complete. He is completely locked. what did the aircraft
पूरा। वो पूरा लॉक है। एयरक्राफ्ट ने क्या
At what speed did you take off? What happened? Meaning
किस स्पीड पे टेक ऑफ किया? क्या हुआ? मतलब
There is very extensive data on flights.
बहुत एक्सटेंसिव डेटा होता है फ्लाइट का।
We both have to recover.
हम हम तो वो दोनों रिकवर करने होते हैं।
That was done. but then surprisingly they said
वो हो गए थे। बट देन सरप्राइजिंगली दे सेड
That it got a little more damaged. So we
कि ये थोड़ा डैमेज ज्यादा हो गया। तो हम
Cannot process this. He also worked in the U.S.
इसको प्रोसेस नहीं कर सकते। उन्होंने यूएस
sent it to him
भेज दिया उसको
So that was a bit shocking that Boeing
तो वो थोड़ा सा शॉकिंग था कि यार बोइंग का
There is a ship and you sent it there
जहाज है और वहीं पे आपने उसको ही भेज दिया
So only now will we know the conflict of
तो अब तो ही पता लगेगा कॉन्फ्लिक्ट ऑफ़
Interest type of right but then good thing
इंटरेस्ट टाइप का राइट बट देन अच्छी बात
Is this also true or is it the case when M Cash is at fault
ये भी है या फिर एक कि जब एम कैश का फौल्ट
If it happened then its investigation was also done there
हुआ था तो वहां उसकी इन्वेस्टिगेशन भी
It happened there and then they did the right
वहीं पे हुई थी एंड देन दे डिड द राइट
investigation i think its mcsh's fault
इन्वेस्टिगेशन आई थिंक जो एमcsh का फॉल्ट
what happened was lioner went down and ethiopian also
हुआ था लायनर वेंट डाउन एंड इथोपियन आल्सो
Went down Boeing 737 but it had no address
वेंट डाउन बोइंग 737 का लेकिन उसमें पता
what is nts also which is de r
है क्या है एनटीएस भी जो है दे आर
independent organization they don't fall
इंडिपेंड ेंट ऑर्गेनाइजेशन दे डोंट फॉल
under the government of there here who is your
अंडर द गवर्नमेंट ऑफ देयर यहां पे जो अपनी
AAIB
है एएआईबी
That government is under the civil action government
वो गवर्नमेंट सिविल एशन गवर्नमेंट के अंडर
If she comes then the fight has been going on for a long time
आती है तो बहुत टाइम से फाइट चल रही है
Make him independent, my friend, that government
उसको इंडिपेंडेंट कर दो आप यार उस सरकार
is under some administration
के अंडर है किसी एडमिनिस्ट्रेशन के अंडर
if it is under some minister then things
है किसी मंत्री के अंडर है तो फिर चीजें
change can happen change can happen so I came
चेंज हो सकती है चेंज हो सकती है सो आई
was talking to this captain amit singh his
वास टॉकिंग टू दिस कैप्टन अमित सिंह उनका
He is a big expert, 18000 hours and now he is
बड़े एक्सपर्ट हैं 18000 घंटे एंड अभी वो
safety pay he has dedicated his life to
सेफ्टी पे दे ही हैज़ डेडिकेटेड ह लाइफ टू
Flight safety says investigation is on
फ्लाइट सेफ्टी कहते हैं इन्वेस्टिगेशन पे
he is also in touch tell the people of AIB
ही इज़ आल्सो इन टच एआईबी के लोगों से कह
Yes sir, the engine has failed. Both
रहे हैं हां सर ये तो इंजन फेल है। दोनों
The engine has failed. Both engines have failed. and when
इंजन फेल है। दोनों इंजन फेल हैं। एंड जब
If there is an impact then at the time of impact
इंपैक्ट होता है तो इंपैक्ट के टाइम पे वो
Why do you study? why is there a seal
क्यों स्टडी करते हो आप? वहां सील क्यों
do you do it? Because you have to see
कर देते हो? क्योंकि आपको देखना होता है
What was the situation at the time of impact?
कि इंपैक्ट के टाइम पे क्या सिचुएशन थी?
What was the condition of the engine blades? if you
इंजन ब्लेड्स की क्या सिचुएशन थी? अगर आप
Engine blades Engine was running at the time of
इंजन ब्लेड्स इंजन वाज़ रनिंग एट द टाइम ऑफ़
The impact must be moving around. and if you turn around
इंपैक्ट तो घूम रहा होगा। और घूम के अगर
If there is an impact then a different type of deflation will occur
इंपैक्ट होगा तो अलग टाइप से डिफेशन आई
It will be. If it is not working it will be idle
होगी। अगर वो नहीं चल रहा होगा आइडल होगा
So it will fall just like that. then there will be damage below
तो ऐसे ही गिरेगा। तो नीचे का डैमेज होगा
The top one won't have blades. if yes then it is ok
ऊपर का नहीं होगा ब्लेड्स। है तो ठीक इट
Gives a lot of information. so over there
गिव्स अ लॉट ऑफ़ इनफार्मेशन। तो वहां पे
Information came that the engine blades were not
इनफार्मेशन आई कि इंजन ब्लेड्स वर नॉट
impacted mean at the time of crash engine
इंपैक्टेड मतलब एट द टाइम ऑफ़ क्रैश इंजन
Was not running. Ok. Both both. both engines
वाज़ नॉट रनिंग। ओके। बोथ बोथ। बोथ इंजन
He crashed because of failure. Yes. They
फेलियर की वजह से वो हुआ क्रैश। हां। वो
keep on saying yes dual engine failure dual
बोलते भी रहे हां ड्यूल इंजन फेलियर ड्यूल
Engine failure. They will not change the report overnight
इंजन फेलियर। वो ना रातोंरात रिपोर्ट चेंज
It's done. When it gets published they say
हो गई। जब पब्लिश हो के आया तो कहते हैं
Inger running. that pilot some how put it in a
इंजर रनिंग। वो पायलट सम हाउ पुट इट इन अ
Stall. and he drove deep so
स्टॉल। और उसने डीप ड्राइव कर दी इसलिए
It crashed. But the deep drive will definitely take place
क्रैश हो गया। पर डीप ड्राइव तो लग ही
It is not there anymore. Didn't it hurt? deep drive then
नहीं रही है। नहीं लगी ना? डीप ड्राइव तो
It is not visible at all brother. No. No. I
विज़िबल ही नहीं है भाई। नहीं नहीं। मैं
Talking about Ghatkopar crash, sorry cash wale cash
घाटकोपर क्रैश की बात सॉरी कैश वाले कैश
Yes yes this was a crash in Ghatkopar
हां हां ये घाटकोपर में एक क्रैश हुआ था
There was another one like this in Mumbai long back
मुंबई में बहुत पहले उसमें ऐसा ही एक और
crash was discuss in my video so much
क्रैश था डिस्कस इन माय वीडियो तो बहुत
Earlier there was a union minister, he was a ship
पहले एक यूनियन मिनिस्टर थे वो थे थे जहाज
I say that the report says that the
में तो वो कहता है रिपोर्ट कहता है कि द
pilot
पायलट
Went into the cloud he lost situational
वेंट इंटू क्लाउड ही लॉस्ट सिचुएशनल
Awareness itself could not control the aircraft
अवेयरनेस ही कुड नॉट कंट्रोल द एयरक्राफ्ट
and it went down again in the same way
एंड इट वेंट डाउन फिर उसी में शुरू में
When you explain the report you list all
व्हेन यू एक्सप्लेन द रिपोर्ट यू लिस्ट ऑल
What was the situation that day? So meteorological
कि सिचुएशन उस दिन क्या था? तो मेटोलॉजिकल
There is also a page of. it is saying in
का भी पन्ना होता है। उसमें कह रहा है
There is no weather at all. In Hum and Conclusion
साला वेदर ही नहीं है। हम और कंक्लूजन में
He is saying that he entered the cloud. so weather
कह रहा है कि बादल में घुस गया। तो वेदर
If not, then which cloud is it? we we so
ही नहीं तो फिर कौन सा बादल हुआ? हम हम तो
Please give me those reports which are made as well, my friend
वो रिपोर्ट्स जो बनती है वो भी यार दे आर
Not made so that future accidents can be
नॉट मेड सो दैट फ्यूचर एक्सीडेंट्स कैन बी
Avoided in India. what they are made to save
अवॉयडेड इन इंडिया। वो दे आर मेड टू सेव
Someone. We are not getting any benefit from this
समवन। हम तो कुछ फायदा थोड़ी ना इस
Of the investigation.
इन्वेस्टिगेशन का।
Then friend, it is a very dark situation
फिर यार मतलब काफी डार्क सिचुएशन ही है
Brother. It is dark brother.
भाई। डार्क तो है भाई।
does it mean where is the respite? I am thinking
है मतलब कहां रेस्पाइट है? मैं सोच रहा
yes that this conversation means some time
हूं कि इस कन्वर्सेशन में मतलब कुछ देर
has to be some leg to hold on to you know
हैज़ टू बी समी लेज टू होल्ड ऑन टू यू नो
I think India as a developing country V
आई थिंक इंडिया एज अ डेवलपिंग कंट्री वी
don't necessarily want these kinds of things
डोंट नेसेसरली वांट दीज़ काइंड ऑफ़ थिंग्स
neither domestically nor for public
नाइदर डोमेस्टिकली नाइदर फॉर पब्लिक
Safety nor for international visibility.
सेफ्टी नॉर नॉर फॉर इंटरनेशनल विज़िबिलिटी।
meaning it does not board as well in any
मतलब यह इट डज़ नॉट बोर्ड अस वेल इन एनी
It doesn't make sense either internally or internationally. and like
सेंस ना इंटरनली ना इंटरनेशनलली। और लाइक
I'm sitting with an ex pilot somebody who
आई एम सिटींग विथ एन एक्स पायलट समबडी हुज
scene aation so closely somebody who is known to
सीन एिएशन सो क्लोजली समबडी हू इज नोन टू
take his voice to the courts and the public
टेक हिज वॉइस टू कोर्ट्स एंड द पब्लिक
wherever he thinks fit and he is telling
व्हेनएवर ही थिंक्स फिट एंड ही इज टेलिंग
me there is nothing to like there is no
मी देयर इज नथिंग टू लाइक देयर इज नो
There Are Silver Linings to the Clouds Literally
सिल्वर लाइनिंग टू द क्लाउड लिटरली हैं
what what
क्या क्या
Brother
भाई
So it's a double engine failure in this case
तो ये इस वाले केस में डबल इंजन फेलियर है
because it's clear we know that double
क्योंकि वो क्लियर है हमें पता है कि डबल
There is engine failure brother look at me
इंजन फेलियर है यार भाई देखो जितना मुझे
I have experience of 9-10 years now
एक्सपीरियंस है नाउ 9 10 साल का
I don't understand hot core I may be
मुझे हॉट कोर समझ में नहीं आ रहा आई मे बी
Tot Li Rong seems to have become quite strong.
टोट ली रोंग कुछ एकदम ही तगड़ा हो गया हो।
Like right now we are talking about software
जैसे अभी बात कर रहे हैं कि सॉफ्टवेयर
Is there a problem or is it the fuel?
प्रॉब्लम हो गई या फिर फ्यूल
There are fuel shut off valves. Yes. Is
फ्यूल शट ऑफ वेल्व्स होती हैं। हां। है
No? So when you're in the car,
ना? तो जब आप कार में होते हैं,
They are hitting the accelerator. you are
एक्सेलरेटर मार रहे होते हैं। यू आर
basically controlling the amount of gas that
बेसिकली कंट्रोलिंग द अमाउंट ऑफ़ गैस दैट
Is entering the engine. ok ok ok. End
इज़ एंटरिंग द इंजन। ठीक ठीक ठीक। एंड
Petrol gets vaporised. With the Air
पेट्रोल वेपराइज होता है। एयर के साथ
You get a mix. there is a fuel air
मिक्स मिलता है। देयर इज़ अ फ्यूल एयर
Mixture that goes inside the engine. Fuel Set
मिक्सचर दैट गोज़ इनसाइड द इंजन। फ्यूल सेट
of the wire that controls how much fuel is
ऑफ वायरल दैट कंट्रोल्स हाउ मच फ्यूल इज़
Going inside the engine. You added power. Take
गोइंग इनसाइड द इंजन। आपने पावर डाली। टेक
If you turn it off then you will get power only then it will take off
ऑफ किया तो पावर मिल रही होगी तभी टेक ऑफ
Did. and then they said there was some
किया। एंड देन दे सेड देयर वाज़ सम
Problem which cuts the AC buses in the
प्रॉब्लम व्हिच कट दी एसी बसेस इन द
Aircraft. so when the ac buses are
एयरक्राफ्ट। सो व्हेन दी एसी बसेस आर
qudd that fuel set of valve is
क्वड्ड दैट फ्यूल सेट ऑफ वेल्व इज़
Controlled by the AC buses. So he is absolutely
कंट्रोलोल्ड बाय द एसी बसेस। तो वो एकदम
It was reset from . There were batteries in flight
से रिसेट हुई। फ्लाइट में बैटरीज होती
Are. but it takes one second to switch on to
हैं। बट इट टेक्स वन सेकंड टू स्विच ऑन टू
The Batteries. so that's why that fuel shut up well
द बैटरीज। तो इसलिए वो फ्यूल शट अप वेल
went into close position because their
क्लोज पोजीशन में चली गई क्योंकि उनकी
The default position is close. but i don't buy
डिफ़ॉल्ट पोजीशन क्लोज है। बट आई डोंट बाय
That. because I think that dude is Boeing
दैट। क्योंकि मुझे लगता है कि यार बोइंग
must have thought this much that if my AC
ने इतना तो सोचा ही होगा कि अगर मेरा एसी
Well, I failed in the air also. so that
बस फेल चलो एयर में भी हो गया। तो वो
I think the fuel will shut off, it will not shut off
फ्यूल आई थिंक शट ऑफ वेल बंद नहीं होगी वो
also in such a critical fuzz because critical
भी इतने क्रिटिकल फज़ में क्योंकि क्रिटिकल
The aircraft in the fuzz also knows it is critical
फज़ में एयरक्राफ्ट को भी पता है क्रिटिकल
He is very fuzz and he takes care of himself too
फज़ है वो बहुत खुद का भी ख्याल रखता है वो
he will not do it, meaning even if he has to fail
नहीं करेगा मतलब अगर उसको फेल होना भी है
Neither a safe way to fail is to fail in an open
ना तो अ सेफ वे टू फेल इज़ फेल इन अ ओपन
Position Rather Than to Fail in a Closed
पोजीशन रादर देन टू फेल इन अ क्लोज्ड
position or right that consumes more fuel
पोजीशन या या राइट कि ज्यादा फ्यूल चला
Let it go, that's not a problem, yes my fuel
जाए वो दिक्कत नहीं है हां मेरा फ्यूल
If it overflows then that is not a problem
ओवरफ्लो हो जाए वो दिक्कत नहीं है तो आई
Think even if it fails but it is still going on
थिंक अगर वो फेल होता भी तो बट ये चल रही
hay rumours but
है रूमर्स बट
Brother, should I tell you the truth? I don't understand anything.
भाई मैं सही बताऊं मेरे को कुछ समझ में
are you not coming i am also eagerly
नहीं आ रहा है क्या आई एम आल्सो इगरली
Waiting to See What Has Happened Do You Land
वेटिंग टू सी व्हाट हैज़ हैपन डू यू लैंड
send any creedence to joe conspiracy land
सेंड एनी क्रीडेंस टू जो कॉनस्परेसी लैंड
is there any meaning around it, look there are two types
है इसके अराउंड कि कोई मतलब देखो दो टाइप
This is a conspiracy. Ok? a conspiracy then
के कंस्परेसी है। ठीक है? एक कंस्परेसी तो
This is the whistle blower regarding Boyan from a long time
ये है कि बोयन को लेके बहुत टाइम से विसल
Blowing is going on. that there are safety
ब्लोइंग चल रही है। दैट देयर आर सेफ्टी
This is particularly with this airliner. The
इशज़ पर्टिकुलरली विथ दिस एयरलाइनर। द
second is that this has been done to tarnish
सेकंड इज़ कि दिस हैज़ बीन डन टू टर्निश
India's Image. Correct. and frankly the
इंडियास इमेज। करेक्ट। एंड फ्रैंकली द
the second one i am less likely to believe because
सेकंड वन आई एम लेस लाइकली टू बिलीव बिकॉज़
I think India's media sector
मेरे को लगता है इंडिया का मीडिया सेक्टर
Even if people are talking on informal Twitter
चाहे वो इनफॉर्मल Twitter पे लोग बोल रहे
Or a formal journalist, a little paranoid
हो या फॉर्मल जर्नलिस्ट हो थोड़ा पैरानॉइड
Is. It takes all our time to find someone
है। हमें सारा टाइम लगता है हम में कोई
He is interested in fingering. and so on
उंगली करने में इंटरेस्टेड है। एंड इतना
Perhaps no one thinks about India.
कोई शायद इंडिया के बारे में नहीं सोचता।
There might be some people in some rooms
हो सकता है कुछ कुछ कमरों में कुछ लोग
Do you think about India? but large
इंडिया के बारे में सोचते हो। बट लार्जली
neither any public nor any public offices of the
ना कोई जनता ना कोई पब्लिक ऑफिसिससेस ऑफ़ द
The world is concerned about India
वर्ल्ड आर कंसर्नड अबाउट अरे इंडिया की
What an image. so this one still seems to me
क्या इमेज है। तो मेरे को यह वाला फिर भी
It looks a bit inflated. One
थोड़ा ऐसा लगता है कि इनफ्लेटेड है। एक
A Sense of Self is a Continuous
सेंस ऑफ़ सेल्फ एक एक कंटीन्यूअस
The inferiority complex that India has
इनफीरियरिटी कॉम्प्लेक्स जो इंडिया को है
Which is now becoming a superiority complex
जो अब सुपीरियरिटी कॉम्प्लेक्स बन रहा है
This is his manifestation. Butt with Boeing
उसकी मैनिफेस्टेशन है। बट बोइंग के साथ
Many question marks are associated. My
काफी क्वेश्चन मार्क्स एसोसिएटेड है। मेरे
who thinks there might actually be questions there
को लगता है वहां पे एक्चुअली सवाल हो सकते
They are there but there will be no one to pick them up. yes it is
हैं पर कोई उठाने वाला नहीं होगा। हां हो
you can bro because
सकते हैं ब्रो बिकॉज़
The US economy depends on Boeing
बोइंग के ऊपर तो यूएस इकॉनमी टिकी हुई है
No. They are not just Boeing. give me
ना। दे आर नॉट जस्ट बोइंग। दे आर मैंने
He probably bought Lockett Martin.
लॉकेट मार्टिन उन्होंने शायद खरीद लिया।
If I am not wrong. it's a very big company
इफ आई नॉट रोंग। इट्स अ वेरी बिग कंपनी
End
एंड
There are couple of law makers who are initially
देयर आर कपल ऑफ लॉ मेकर्स हु आर इनिशियली
ET Boeing. now they are in congress so they
एट बोइंग। नाउ दे आर इन कांग्रेस सो दे
have like has power they have power boing a has
हैव लाइक है पावर दे हैव पावर बोइंग ए हैज़
Power So
पावर सो
He had an I think facility somewhere
उनकी एक आई थिंक कहीं पे एक फैसिलिटी थी
They have made a new facility in South
साउथ में दे हैव मेड अ न्यू फैसिलिटी इन
Taxis followed there a guy had a camera
टैक्सेस फॉलोडा वहां पे एक बंदे ने कैमरा
He had also taken some videos with him
लेके भी घुस गया था उसने कुछ वीडियो भी
I had made it, check the whistle taxes, friend
बनाया था चेक करो विसल टैक्सेस यार कुछ
This is one of their facilities
ऐसा उनकी एक तो उनकी फैसिलिटी
The same was in the North or Mid US and one down there too
वही नॉर्थ या मिड यूएस में थी एक नीचे भी
They built a new facility there
उन्होंने नई फैसिलिटी वहां पे किसी वहां
But someone had entered with a camera on a search
पे कोई कैमरा लेके घुस गया था एक पे सर्च
You should do that, he installed a hidden cam
करना ना वो तेरे को उसने हिडन कैम लगाया
And then he took it and entered inside
था एंड देन वो लेके घुस गया था अंदर
because he also had something like that but there are
क्योंकि उसको भी कुछ था ऐसा बट देयर आर
couple of whistle blowers who have called
कपल ऑफ विसल ब्लोअर जिन्होंने बुला है
Yes for Boeing and what are the problems?
बोइंग के लिए हां और क्या प्रॉब्लम्स
I have pointed it out, do you know friend, that this
पॉइंट आउट करी है डू यू नो यार कि ये जो
They are taking approvals from FA in such a hurry
अप्रूवल्स ले रहे हैं एफए से ये जल्दबाजी
I am taking it and FA is also giving approval
में ले रहे हैं एंड एफए भी अप्रूवल्स दे
And he's doing a little arm twisting as well
रहा है और वो थोड़ा सा आर्म ट्विस्टिंग भी
they approve the FA because they
कर देते हैं अप्रूव एफए की क्योंकि वो
Such a big good FS Federation of Joe
इतने बड़े हैं अच्छा एफएस फेडरेशन ऑफ़ जो
Here is DC, well there is Federal
यहां पे डीसी है अच्छा वहां का फेडरल
Aviation Administration yes ok ok and brother
एिएशन एडमिनिस्ट्रेशन हां ठीक ठीक और भाई
The world sees the FA like this, if the FA
दुनिया एफए को ऐसे देखती है ना अगर एफए ने
If our DG approves then if FA
अप्रूव हमारा डीजी से तो अगर एफए ने
If the DCP approves it, then he will say yes
अप्रूव कर दिया ना डीसीआ तो बोलेगा हां
It is approved, approve sir, approve, approve yes
अप्रूव है अप्रूव सर अप्रूव अप्रूव हां
yes DDCA has no technical knowledge that
हां डीडीसीए हैज़ नो टेक्निकल नॉलेज कि वो
new regulations by yourself or something
अपने से खुद से नए रेगुलेशंस या फिर अ कुछ
If we can do research then we will do what the FIA says
रिसर्च कर सके तो हम तो जो एफआईए बोलता है
Sir, we accept your orders after tying the bandage on our wrist
हम तो सर आपकी पट्टी बांध के मान लेते हैं
Just think, someone comes to audit the FI.
आप सोचो ना एफआई में ऑडिट करने आता है
Brother, DGCA gives us ratings, yes
हमें रेटिंग देते हैं भाई डीजीसीए को हां
Well that's how competent it is
अच्छा कि ये कितना कॉम्पिटेंट है अच्छा
ok ok ok one thing is done IO when
अच्छा अच्छा अच्छा एक तो हो गया आईओ जब
Sometimes brother, some things happen
मैंने कभी-कभी भाई कुछ चीजें होती है ना
what you find out makes you feel weird and
जो आपको पता चलती है आपको अजीब लगता है और
Then for so many years and everybody else you
फिर वो इतने सालों तक और सब लोग आपके
Around you, you think this is the norm
आसपास वो तो आपको लगता है ये नॉर्म ही
if it happens then why do you become okay with it
होगा तो फिर आप ओके क्यों हो जाते हो उस
When I reacted to the thing I said
चीज से जब मैं रिएक्शन में आया मैंने कहा
FA is the body of their country, we
एफए तो उनके देश की बॉडी है हम तो हमें
why is he giving rating or rating
रेटिंग क्यों दे रहा है वो या तो रेटिंग
be it such a thing or an international organization
ऐसी चीज हो या फिर इंटरनेशनल ऑर्गेनाइजेशन
ho as she is she is also an I K.O. but she is someone
हो जैसे है वो भी आई केओ है हम बट वो किसी
I don't give rating to everyone like F.A. Choudhary
को रेटिंग नहीं देता एफ ए चौधरी बनके सब
Goes to countries and gives ratings to everyone
देशों में जाके सबको रेटिंग देता है
America has an old belief that yes, it is right to become a Chaudhary.
अमेरिका का पुराना है चौधरी बनने का हां
So he comes and gives us ratings and now
तो वो रेटिंग देता है हमें आके और अब
your improvement has been done otherwise five 6
तुम्हारी इंप्रूव हो गई है अदरवाइज पांच 6
Till a year ago I used to keep it in level three
साल पहले तक तो मैं लेवल थ्री में रखता था
They. We are now at level two. Yes. that level
वो। अब हम लेवल टू में हैं। हां। वो लेवल
When I kept it in three, I used to say that friend yes
थ्री में रखता था तो कहता था कि यार हां
We have more flights to your country than this
तुम्हारे देश में हम इससे ज्यादा फ्लाइट
I will not send it because of your safety
नहीं भेजेंगे क्योंकि तुम्हारी सेफ्टी
It is very weak. He used to limit flights
बहुत कमजोर है। वो फ्लाइट्स लिमिट करता था
And for us also there are limited flights there.
और हमको भी जैसे फ्लाइट्स लिमिटेड ही वहां
Slots were available for sending.
भेजने को स्लॉट मिलते थे।
yes, what is this? Do it up. there have been
हां, क्या है ये? ऊपर करियो। देयर हैव बीन
Reports of Boeing whistle blurs racing
रिपोर्ट्स ऑफ बोइंग विसल ब्लर्स रेसिंग
Safety Concerns and Some How to Die and Face
सेफ्टी कंसर्न्स एंड सम हाव डाइड और फेस
Legal action. one whistle blower john bard was
लीगल एक्शन। वन विसल ब्लर जॉन बार्ड वास्
Found Dead and Was Self-Inflicted
फाउंड डेड एंड वास सेल्फ इन्फ्लिक्टेड
Wound. After Giving Evidence Against Boeing
वूंड। आफ्टर गिविंग एविडेंस अगेंस्ट बोइंग
Another whistle blower Sam Salepore. Testified
अनदर विसल ब्लोअर सैम सलेपोर। टेस्टिफाइड
before a US Senate committee about
बिफोर अ यूएस सेनेट कमिटी अबाउट
Manufacturing Shortcuts in 77 and 7 87
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग शॉर्टकट्स इन 77 एंड 7 87
The aircraft was a 7 87 or a 787 FS
एयरक्राफ्ट ये 7 87 था ना 787 द एफएस
Investigating Quality Claims Made By
इन्वेस्टिगेटिंग क्वालिटी क्लेम्स मेड बाय
some whistle blowers some Boeing whistle blows have
सम विसल ब्लोअर्स सम बोइंग विसल ब्लोस हैव
Come Forward with Serious Allegations
कम फॉरवर्ड विथ सीरियस एलगेशंस
Who went with the camera in this, did you find it friend
इसमें कैमरा लेके कौन गया मिला क्या यार
I saw that, there is no evidence, but that
वो मैंने देखा था एविडेंस नहीं है बट वो
This is what we are talking about. Good John Bard
इसी की बात कर रहे हैं। अच्छा जॉन बार्ड
that John Burnett's might have blown up
की जॉन बर्ननेट की हो सकता है वो उड़ा
He might have given it in full from the internet
दिया हो ना पूरा उन्होंने इंटरनेट से वो
It was a long time ago but there is still a whistle
काफी पहले की बात थी बट देयर इज़ हां विसल
Brother brothers here and in Air India
लॉर्स है ब्रो यहां पे और एयर इंडिया में
also there was another whistle lower i think he will release in 2022
भी एक और विसल लोअर था आई थिंक उसने 2022
something in
में कुछ
He had done that Air India's Triple 7 which
करा था उसने कि एयर इंडिया के ट्रिपल7 जो
They are not coming here from the US
यूएस से यहां पे आ रहे हैं दे आर नॉट
Compliant with the oxygen requirement on
कंप्लायंट विद द ऑक्सीजन रिक्वायरमेंट ऑन
The board should be of 15 minutes or 12 minutes
बोर्ड कुछ 15 मिनट की होनी चाहिए 12 मिनट
Taking it all, something like this was happening with us. so then you
लेके ऑल रहे हैं कुछ ऐसा साथ था। सो तो आप
If you come to India from the US, there are three or four routes
यूएस से इंडिया आते हो तो तीन चार रूट्स
It can be done by you, right? So he was saying that
बनते हैं ना आपके। तो वो कह रहा था कि
You cannot take an extended flight over water
एक्सटेंडेड फ्लाइट ओवर वाटर आप नहीं कर
Can. Because you have less oxygen. We
सकते। बिकॉज़ कम ऑक्सीजन है आपके पास। हम
With in some two or three aircraft. that's it
विद इन सम टू और थ्री एयरक्राफ्ट्स। सो ही
told called the dispatch said you give please
टोल्ड कॉल्ड दी डिस्पैच सेड यू गिव प्लीज
Fire a new routing for me. so they weren't
फायर अ न्यू रूटिंग फॉर मी। सो दे वर नॉट
Happy with him ki yaar last minute pe
हैप्पी विथ हिम कि यार लास्ट मिनट पे
The flight got delayed. you did extra work
फ्लाइट डिले हो गई। तुमने एक्स्ट्रा काम
I gave it. so when he landed he was called
दे दिया। तो व्हेन ही लैंडेड ही वास कॉल्ड
something happened to him and i don't know about him
अप कुछ उसका हुआ एंड उसको आई डोंट नो उसकी
There was friction with Corey management. Then
फ्रिक्शन हुई कोरी मैनेजमेंट के साथ। फिर
I fired him, what did you do but then
उसको फायर कर दिया क्या कर दिया बट देन
His case is going on in Bombay High Court
उसका केस चल रहा है बॉम्बे हाई कोर्ट में
And some Bombay High Courts also gave some rulings
और कुछ बॉम्बे हाईको ने भी कुछ रूलिंग दी
thi hum you shoulda pull it up aa jayega
थी हम यू शुड वा पुल इट अप आ जाएगा
actually look it up air india whistle bower
एक्चुअली लुक इट अप एयर इंडिया विसल बोवर
Triple 7 Oxygen Requirement Add Now
ट्रिपल7 ऑक्सीजन रिक्वायरमेंट डाल अभी
It was trending on Twitter as well
Twitter में भी वो ट्रेंड कर रहा था
Because what happens when such accidents happen
क्योंकि क्या है जब ऐसे एक्सीडेंट्स होते
right bro so for the past 5-6 years those people who
हैं ना ब्रो तो पिछले 5- 6 साल से जो लोग
it happens to me that yes it happens to me now
के साथ हुआ होता है कि हां अब तो मेरे साथ
It also happened that all those people come forward there
भी हुआ था वो सारे लोग सामने आते हैं देयर
There are sufficient videos that the AC is not working
वर सफिशिएंट वीडियोस कि एसी नहीं चल रहे
or the entertainment setup is not working
या एंटरटेनमेंट सेटअप नहीं चल रहा इज अ
Customer version of it not with us
कस्टमर वर्जन ऑफ इट ना कि हमारे साथ ये
The problem has occurred. yes yes this
प्रॉब्लम हो चुकी है। हां हां ये
Exactly this one is a whistle blower pilot race
एक्सैक्टली दिस वन अ विसल ब्लोर पायलट रेस
Concerns about the emergency oxygen
कंसर्न्स अबाउट दी इमरजेंसी ऑक्सीजन
Supply on Air India Boeing 7 of 12 minutes
सप्लाई ऑन एयर इंडिया बोइंग 7 12 मिनट का
right yes 12 minutes 12 minutes oxygen supply
है ना हां 12 मिनट 12 मिनट ऑक्सीजन सप्लाई
the pilot this amount of was insufficient for
द पायलट दिस अमाउंट ऑफ़ वाज़ इनसफिशिएंट फॉर
Sep operation. So if you know this,
सेप ऑपरेशन। तो अगर ये बता पता है इनका
What is? Hey Sir, this one has two engines
क्या है? इनका है अरे सर दो इंजन चलते हैं
No. Was there a failure in 10 years? take it
ना। 10 साल में फेलियर हुआ क्या? ले जाओ
Even today. and as a pilot my job is bhaiya yes
आज भी। एंड एज़ अ पायलट माय जॉब इज़ भाई हां
Hasn't happened for 10 years. It happened today. Right
10 साल से नहीं हुआ। आज हो गया तो। राइट
Right right right right. you once
राइट राइट राइट राइट। आपको तो एक बार
probability yes you want one failure for
प्रोबेबिलिटी हां यू वांट वन फेलियर फॉर
Everything to go. he is saying that sir 12
एवरीथिंग टू गो। वो कह रहा है कि सर 12
It will not give oxygen for a minute and why
मिनट का नहीं देगा ये ऑक्सीजन एंड व्हाई
12 minutes? because at the level you fly
12 मिनट? क्योंकि तुम जिस लेवल पे फ्लाइट
Are you planning to be late level 410390
को प्लान कर रहे हो लेट से लेवल 410390
The safe altitude from there is 10,000
वहां से सेफ ऑल्टीट्यूड है 10,000 तो
I don't need supplemental for Rs 10,000
10,000 में आई डोंट नीड सप्लीमेंटल
Oxygen. From there I can reach 10,000 in 12 minutes
ऑक्सीजन। वहां से मैं 10,000 12 मिनट में
I will not be able to come. I will come in 16 minutes. So 4
नहीं आ पाऊंगा। 16 मिनट में आऊंगा। तो 4
what would you do for a minute? First
मिनट के लिए तुम क्या क्या करोगे? पहले
Apply yours and then apply your childs. Brother is the one
अपना लगाएं फिर बच्चे का लगाएं। भाई है ही
No, nothing will be included in it. Right
नहीं उसमें क्या कुछ आएगा ही नहीं। राइट
Right right right right. oh right right right
राइट राइट राइट राइट। ओह राइट राइट राइट
Right. so and as a passenger you are like this
राइट। तो एंड एज अ पैसेंजर यू आर लाइक ये
It never happened to me. Yes, right. I am
कभी हुआ नहीं मेरे साथ। हां, राइट। आई एम
See never seen but will you take off without it?
सी नेवर सीन बट विल यू टेक ऑफ विदाउट इट?
Or, Right Exactly. No, right? Or. Right.
या, राइट एक्जेक्टली। नहीं ना? या। राइट।
The DDCA was asked to investigate and
द डीडीसीए वास् आस्क टू इन्वेस्टिगेट एंड
Determine this is a case going on in the court
डिटरमिन यह एक केस चल रहा है कोर्ट में चल
This is happening brother. And the court also reprimanded him
रहा है भाई यह। और कोर्ट ने भी इसको फटकार
I had applied quite a lot.
लगाई थी अच्छी खासी।
So, are you sure that this is the second option for me?
तो, ही सेड कि नहीं यार, यह मेरे को दूसरा
Give you a lower level by filing the routing
रूटिंग फाइल करके दो आप और नीचे का लेवल
File it and give it. If you are filing late
फाइल करके दो। इफ यू आर फाइलिंग लेट से
390, 39,000 feet, give me 330. So that's me
390, 39,000 फीट, गिव मी 330. सो दैट आई
Can descend on to 10, 10,000 in time.
कैन डिसेंड ऑन टू 10, 10,000 इन टाइम।
Hmm. Maybe nothing will happen. Right? Butt Eye
हम्म। मे बी नथिंग विल हैपन। राइट? बट आई
Will not take their chances, right? Right? So
विल नॉट टेक देयर चांस, राइट? राइट? सो
what's in 330? It will consume more fuel.
330 में क्या है? ज्यादा फ्यूल लगेगा।
Good. The routing took long. the higher you go
अच्छा। रूटिंग लंबी लगी। द हायर यू गो द
You should not use laser fuel bro. ok ok ok
लेसर फ्यूल यू यूज़ ना ब्रो। ओके ओके ओके
Because the distance became smaller. Yes? No.
बिकॉज़ द डिस्टेंस बिकम स्मॉलर। हां? नहीं।
The air is less dense as you go up. Fair.
एयर इज लेस डेंस एस यू गो अप ना। फेयर।
For me cruising at a higher level is
फॉर मी क्रूसिंग एट हायर लेवल इज
Beneficial. my so jet engines are performing
बेनिफिशियल। माई सो जेट इंजंस आर परफॉर्म
To their design to perform at high levels.
टू देयर डिजाइन टू परफॉर्म एट हाई लेवल्स।
Yes. So you get good performance on top.
हां। तो ऊपर अच्छी परफॉरमेंस मिलती है।
I will use less fuel. There will be less traffic
मैं फ्यूल कम यूज़ करूंगा। ट्रैफिक कम होगा
I will reach there soon. direct to me
मैं जल्दी पहुंच जाऊंगा। मेरे को डायरेक्ट
Routing will be found. Right. so right this plus
रूटिंग मिल जाएगी। राइट। तो राइट दिस प्लस
Last minute delay is and because friend
लास्ट मिनट डिले इज़ एंड क्योंकि यार
They have five or six routes in dispatch too.
डिस्पैच मे बी उनके ना पांच छह रूट्स
We get ready. It is not so that they
तैयार होते हैं। ऐसा नहीं कि उनको बैठ के
Hit enter and it came out. now they have to say an end
एंटर मारा निकल आया। नाउ दे हैव टू स एंड
then really work hard and join points
देन रियली वर्क हार्ड एंड जॉइन पॉइंट्स
And then calculate time and fuel. complete all
एंड देन कैलकुलेट टाइम एंड फ्यूल। पूरा सब
Something new has to be done. we sleep they were not
कुछ नया करना पड़ता है। हम सो दे वर नॉट
Happy that you are using your brain. We
हैप्पी कि तुम दिमाग लगा रहे हो अपना। हम
This is how it has been going on here for the last 10 years
ऐसे ही चलता है यहां पे 10 साल से ऐसे ही
It is happening. You are new here. that is an attitude
हो रहा है। तुम नए आए हो। वो एक एटीट्यूड
I didn't mean I didn't mean
नहीं था हम हम मैं नहीं नहीं आई मीन
anybody who worked any job anywhere in
एनीबडी हुज वर्क्ड एनी जॉब एनीवेयर इन
India in any sector and know
इंडिया किसी भी सेक्टर में और पता है
All the people in India at some point
इंडिया में जितने भी लोग हैं एट सम पॉइंट
in their lives they have had a touch
इन देयर लाइफ्स दे हैव दे हैव हैड अ टच
Point With
पॉइंट विद
Some government, everybody understands your pain
किसी सरकार एवरीबडी अंडरस्टैंड्स योर पेन
Everyone has had a touch point with them once
सबका एक बार एक उनको टच पॉइंट हुआ है दे
no if anyone knows what the system is like
नो कि सिस्टम कैसा है क्या है तो किसी को
there is no need to explain it so
एक्सप्लेन करने की जरूरत भी नहीं है तो यू
Let us understand that this is our background
दे अंडरस्टैंड कि ये हमारा बैकग्राउंड
Cultural attitude to
कल्चरल एटीट्यूड टू
work say that and
वर्क कह लो कि और
means this is the same attitude that you work for three months
मतलब यह वही एटीट्यूड है कि तीन महीना काम
I will not do it. summer holidays are over
नहीं करेंगे। गर्मियों की छुट्टियां पूरी
I will celebrate. We are comfort loving people. A on High
मनाएंगे। हम आराम पसंद आदमी हैं। अ पर हाई
This thing is a must at critical safety junctions
क्रिटिकल सेफ्टी जंक्चर्स पे ये चीज एज अ
We as consumers do not expect that
कंज्यूमर हम नहीं एक्सपेक्ट करते हैं कि
These flights operate in this manner. as a
ये फ्लाइट्स इस तरीके से चलती हैं। एज अ
Consumer We Say Good Seat Recline
कंज्यूमर हम कहते हैं अच्छा सीट रिक्लाइन
It is not happening. Ok issue the bathroom is not working.
नहीं हो रही। ओके इशू बाथरूम नहीं चल रहा।
ok issue like that is what we know. we don't
ओके इशू लाइक दैट इज व्हाट वी नो। वी डोंट
See that this is the level of the issue. yes bro when
सी दैट दिस इज द लेवल ऑफ़ इशू। हां ब्रो जब
Earlier some guy had said that the flu in Delhi
ये पहले एक किसी बंदे ने हु फ्लू दिल्ली
Ahmedabad sector he pointed this out
अहमदाबाद सेक्टर उसने ये पॉइंट आउट किया
then i was like these things
था देन आई वास लाइक यार दिस थिंग्स दे
don't affect safety hmm but then I
डोंट अफेक्ट सेफ्टी हम्म बट देन मैंने
When I thought again I said it or obviously
दोबारा जब सोचा ना मैंने कहा या ऑब्वियसली
They don't affect safety but you are an airline
दे डोंट इफेक्ट सेफ्टी बट आप एयरलाइन
why are you running it is a business you
क्यों रन कर रहे हो इट इज अ बिज़नेस यू
Want to Earn Money for Your Customers You
वांट टू अर्न मनी फॉर योर कस्टमर्स यू
want to package things right that they buy
वांट टू पैकेज थिंग्स राइट दैट दे बाय
Right So If You Don't Have Enough Money and Will to
राइट सो इफ यू डोंट हैव एनफ मनी और विल टू
make those things right on that safety you
मेक दोज़ थिंग्स राइट उस सेफ्टी पे तुम
What money are you investing, still
क्या ही पैसा लगा रहे हो वो तो फिर भी
Background became background, no one cared
बैकग्राउंड हो गया बैकग्राउंड ना किसी को
It is not visible at all. Right right? when i eat
दिखता ही नहीं। राइट राइट? जब मैं खाना
I am going to eat, it's good for me
खाने जा रहा हूं, मेरे अच्छा ही
Garnishing is coming. and in the kitchen
गार्निशिंग आ रही है। और किचन में तो
The insects are roaming around. Do I know? Right
कीड़े घूम रहे हैं। मुझे क्या पता? राइट
Right right. Right. The food here is also good
राइट राइट। राइट। यहां तो खाना भी अच्छा
I am not coming. Yes, right, right. what is below
नहीं आ रहा। हां, राइट राइट। नीचे क्या ही
Did it happen brother? right right right right right right right
हुआ भाई? राइट राइट राइट राइट राइट राइट
Right right. Brother, you have this flight
राइट राइट। भाई आपने ये फ्लाइट जो ये
Malaysian Airlines had 370 about it
मलेशियन एयरलाइंस थी 370 उसके बारे में
Have you ever done that to pass your time? do you know
कभी आपने वो करा था टाइम पास? पता है आपको
What happened? Hey, some data has come out.
क्या हुआ था? अरे कुछ डाटा तो सामने आया
So do you know what he said? He did tell something
तो पता क्या बोला? उन्होंने कुछ बताया ही
No. Yes, they did say something from the front
नहीं। हां, उन लोगों ने सामने से तो कुछ
No, tell me. Maybe someone from the aviation end
नहीं बता। एिएशन एंड से शायद इसमें कोई
There was not much interest. Give it all quiet.
ज्यादा इंटरेस्ट नहीं था। दे ऑल क्वाइट।
I watched a documentary on Netflix.
Netflix की एक डॉक्यूमेंट्री देखी थी।
Hmm. So, I will look into it thoroughly and tell you,
हम्। तो, उसमें पूरा देख बताएंगे बताएंगे,
I will tell you. He doesn't tell me anything, bastard. They
बताएंगे। कुछ नहीं बताता साले। उन्होंने
I dragged it for one and a half hour. like in ancient alien
1ढ़ घंटा खींच दिया। जैसे एंशंट एलियन में
You used to do it earlier. I'll tell you this right now
करते थे ना पहले की। अभी आपको बताएंगे ये
How did it become? And coming to the end. Yes. sees
बना कैसे। और एंड तक आते-आते। हां। देखता
I am not a Netflix fan. I saw that
नहीं हूं Netflix वगैरह। मैंने देखी वो
By taking out time. He didn't tell anything
टाइम निकाल के। कुछ उन्होंने बताया नहीं
What happened. I think Action History
क्या हुआ। मेरे ख्याल से एएशन हिस्ट्री
which is the biggest question mark in
में सबसे जो सबसे बड़ा क्वेश्चन मार्क है
I think it is the same. that what happened? How
मेरे ख्याल से वही है। कि क्या हुआ? कैसे
Happened? Where did that flight go? How did you get it?
हुआ? वो फ्लाइट गई तो गई कहां? मिली कैसे?
Hey it went off the radar. can't be a brother
अरे रडार से चली गई। भाई हो ही नहीं सकता
It should go off the radar like this.
रडार से चली जाए ऐसे।
Look, they are saying that there is a black spot on the radar
देख वो कह रहे हैं ब्लैक स्पॉट है रेडार
What can't happen? Oh all over the world
का हो ही नहीं सकता। अरे पूरी दुनिया में
What's going on? to the US satellite
क्या चल रहा है? अमेरिका की सेटेलाइट को
I know everything. Yes, that is correct. so that date
सब पता है। हां सही बात है। तो वो डेट
You might not be giving it. yes it is not right
नहीं दे रहे होंगे। हां राइट हो ही नहीं
He can. It is not possible that that flight is
सकता वो। हो ही नहीं सकता वो फ्लाइट कहां
I will tell you that I have arrived. Do you know what it is?
आ गई बताना होगा। तेरे को पता है क्या है?
MA 370 which was that flight from Malaysia
एमए 370 जो एक वो फ्लाइट थी मलेशिया से
It was fly curry. was going to China and Indian
फ्लाई करी थी। चाइना जा रही थी और इंडियन
She disappears completely over the ocean.
ओशन के ऊपर कंप्लीटली वो गायब हो जाती है।
What conspiracy theories are there about him?
उसके ऊपर तो क्या कॉनस्परेसी थ्योरीज है
Brother. Brother, pick up all the aliens, villains
भाई। भाई एलियन विलियन सब की एलियन उठा के
They took away the white people. You don't know this
ले गए व्ईट लोगों को। तेरे को नहीं पता ये
All. Documentary. Yes.
सब। डॉक्यूमेंट्री। हां।
documentaries thousands of aliens were in it
डॉक्यूमेंट्रीियां हजारों उसमें एलियन थे
Or some Chinese stuff could be put in it, or
या उसमें कुछ चाइना कुछ खुफिया सामान जा
Had been. There were US CI agents in it.
रहा था। उसमें यूएस के सीआई एजेंट्स थे।
He got it taken down that what a lot
उन्होंने टेक डाउन करा दी कि क्या बहुत
There is more conspiracy in it and that
ज्यादा उसमें कांस्परेसी और वो
Some of its parts were found. Yes. Australia
कुछ पार्ट्स मिले उसके। हां। ऑस्ट्रेलिया
Met near. Yes. Near Australia. And
के पास मिले। हां। ऑस्ट्रेलिया के पास। और
Where is she going from? It is said here
वो कहां से कहां जा रही है। कहते हैं यहां
I went there and wandered around like this. Madagascar
पे जाके ऐसे घूम गई। मेडागास करो के फिर
Came here. Why did you go? Do you know how you got there
यहां आई। क्यों गई? वहां कैसे घूमी पता ही
No, nothing. And they say it feels so much
नहीं कुछ। और कहते हैं इसको इतना तो फील
It was not possible for him to go there. Exactly
नहीं था कि वहां तक जा पाए वो। एक्सक्ट्ली
This was also an issue. not that much fuel
ये भी एक इशू था। इतना तो फ्यूल ही नहीं
that he is going somewhere around Australia
है कि वो ऑस्ट्रेलिया के आसपास कहीं जा
Got it. Why does it happen? 2000 check it. I think
पाए। क्यों होता है? 2000 चेक कर। आई थिंक
2018-17 is around this time.
2018-17 इसी टाइम के आसपास की बात है।
This is from the last 10 years. already do.
पिछले 10 साल की बात है। पहले ही है।
Just write MA 370 to Malaysia. some more
मलेशिया को एमए 370 लिख दे बस। कुछ और
I don't know, you will find out only one thing.
नहीं पता तेरे को एक ही चीज़ पता लगेगी।
I
मैंने
This is one of the most famous plane crashes in my opinion.
ये एक मेरे ख्याल से बड़ा फेमस प्लेन क्रैश
This is the one from Andes. It fell in the Andes in the 60's.
है एंडीज वाला। एंडीज में गिरा था 60 में।
In plaid 60's maybe. I don't know in between
प्लेड 60 में शायद। बीच में पता नहीं
Why can't I remember now that my
क्यों मेरे को याद नहीं आ रहा अब कि मेरे
Why did he get interested in these things then?
को क्यों इंटरेस्ट आ गया था इन चीजों तब
yes i saw this 370 has ma 370 all 27
मैंने हां ये देख 370 हैज़ एमए 370 ऑल 27
2014 Flank from Kollampur to Beijing
2014 फ्लैंक फ्रॉम कोलालमपुर टू बीजिंग
and it just went somewhere where koppal where
एंड इट जस्ट वेंट समवेयर कहां कोप्पल कहां
beijing and where australian coast and where
बीजिंग और कहां ऑस्ट्रेलियन कोस्ट और कहां
Where had you come from after roaming around in Madagas and
मेडाग में कहां घूम के कहां से आई थी और
It is said that it fell into the Indian Ocean
मिला कहते है इंडियन ओशन में गिरा क्या
it doesn't make any sense nobody knows really
हुआ कोई सेंस नहीं है नोबडी नोस ट्रूली
what happened
व्हाट हैपेंड
Hey, there is some search and rescue for that too
अरे उसकी तो सर्च एंड रेस्क्यू भी कुछ
They did not find it, then search and rescue started
मिला नहीं उन्होंने फिर सर्च एंड रेस्क्यू
I remember they had shut it down but they didn't find anything
बंद करदिया था याद है कुछ नहीं मिला उनको
Search and rescue is now so big that the Indian Ocean
सर्च एंड रेस्क्यू अब इतना बड़ा इंडियन ओशन
What did you say you would look for
क्या कहा ढूंढोगे तुमको
something at the last radar point
कुछ तो लास्ट रेडार पॉइंट पे
By the way civil radars are different.
बाय द वे सिविल रेडार्स अलग होते हैं।
Military radars are different. when we people
मिलिट्री रेडार्स अलग होते हैं। हम लोग जब
we fly under civil radars
फ्लाई करते हैं वी आर अंडर सिविल रेडार्स
But the military is always watching you. donation
बट मिलिट्री इज़ ऑलवेज वाचिंग यू। देन
Communicate with you but god is watching you. So
कम्युनिकेट विद थू बट देव वाचिंग यू। तो
Someone must be watching him 110%.
कोई ना कोई तो उसको देख ही रहा होगा 110%।
Right? you can not disappear from this
राइट? यू कैन नॉट डिसअपीयर फ्रॉम दिस
Planet. Even If You Crash You Don't
प्लेनेट। इवन इफ यू क्रैश यू डोंट
probably disappear from a raider
प्रॉब्ली डिसअपीयर फ्रॉम अ रेडर
Immediately. you can't yes means when that
इमीडिएटली। यू कैन नॉट हां मतलब जब वो
It crashed and then you left, so that last dot
क्रैश हुआ फिर आप चले गए तो वो लास्ट डॉट
So yours will stay there. I told you
तो आपकी वहां पे रहेगी। आई टोल्ड यू
ADSB is out. ADSB Out and In.
एडीएसबी आउट होता है। एडीएसबी आउट एंड इन।
So it is not always in your control.
तो वो हमेशा आप आपका कंट्रोल में नहीं है
They. it is sending infection out at everyone
वो। इट इज सेंडिंग इनफेशन आउट एट एव्री
Instantaneous time. He keeps sending it.
इंस्टेंटेनियस टाइम। वो भेजता ही रहता है।
well and military radars are much much more
अच्छा और मिलिट्री रेडार्स आर मच मच मोर
Superior. Meaning, they leave no black spot
सुपीरियर। मतलब वो कोई ब्लैक स्पॉट छोड़ते
Not there. How do you like the flights you take?
नहीं है। हाउ डू ये जैसे जो फ्लाइट्स आप
People make fun of me. how do they compare to
लोग उड़ाते हो। हाउ डू दे कंपेयर टू
Military aircrafts?
मिलिट्री एयरक्राफ्ट्स?
what we fly is basically point a
हम जो उड़ाते हैं वो तो बेसिकली पॉइंट ए
Carrying two point B passengers
टू पॉइंट बी पैसेंजर्स को लेके जा रहे
Are. militaries perform their own sorties
हैं। मिलिट्रीज दे परफॉर्म देयर ओन सॉर्टज
And missions and all. You just saw what
एंड मिशनंस एंड ऑल। अभी आपने देखा है जो
They took out this B2 and sent it to Iran
ये बी टू इन्होंने निकाल के ईरान भेजे
What do they look like, friend?
क्या देखने में तो क्या लगते हैं यार वो
Plains people, did you see B2?
प्लेनेंस वाले तूने देखे बी टू क्या
This game is at the next level, this is so
नेक्स्ट ही लेवल एक तो ये गेम साली इतनी
Geopolitics is next level isn't it brother 19
जिओपॉलिटिक्स नेक्स्ट लेवल है ना भाई 19
Or do they have some ships like that and only
या कुछ ऐसे ही जहाज है इनके पास और सिर्फ
they have it and no one else has it there were 21
उनके पास है और किसी के पास नहीं है 21 थे
There have been a few crashes, two crashes and one in Goa
एक आध क्रैश हो गए दो क्रैश है एक गोवा
Somewhere else in Guwahati one aircraft
में कहीं और हां गुवा में वन एयरक्राफ्ट
This one is two billion brother and this bomb too
इज टू बिलियन ये वाला भाई ये जो बॉम्ब भी
This bomb is thrown, it creates a hole first
फेंकता है ना ये बॉम्ब पहले गड्ढा करता है
Down for a long time and then several feet below the ground
बहुत देर नीचे और फिर कई फीट नीचे जमीन
The Called Bunker Busters bunker explodes in
में फटता है कॉल्ड बंकर बस्टर्स बंकर
There are busters and it is made a complete
बस्टर्स होते हैं एंड इट इज़ मेड ए पूरा द
The aircraft is a wing. it's basically a
एयरक्राफ्ट इज अ विंग। इट्स बेसिकली अ
Wing. It's a wing. See if there is something in this
विंग। इट्स अ विंग। देख तू अगर कुछ इसमें
He is not there. I mean if you are normal
वो नहीं है। मतलब अगर तू नॉर्मल
If the aircraft sees, then the rudder in the aircraft
एयरक्राफ्ट देखेगा तो एयरक्राफ्ट में रडर
It is there, isn't it, brother? Tale
होता है ना भाई रडर। टेल
There is no tail. And what kind of science is this
कोई टेल नहीं है। एंड ये क्या साइंस लगाए
which only they know because tale
जो इन्होंने इनको ही पता है क्योंकि टेल
Without it the aircraft cannot fly.
के बिना एयरक्राफ्ट फ्लाई नहीं कर सकता।
What will be the function of the tail? Your control.
टेल का क्या फंक्शन रहेगा? योर कंट्रोल।
So there are three moments. Pitch up, pitch
तो देयर आर थ्री मोमेंट्स। पिच अप, पिच
Down, roll as it turns and yours. yo
डाउन, रोल जैसे टर्न करता है एंड योर। यो
is the most important. If yo were not
इज द मोस्ट इंपोर्टें। अगर यो नहीं होता
Then I don't know how you are doing it
तो फिर उसमें पता नहीं कैसे कर रहे हैं यो
how to maintain it, you must be doing something there
कैसे मेंटेन कुछ तो कर रहे होंगे देयर
must be some surfaces or many small ones
मस्ट बी सम सरफेससेस या छोटी-छोटी बहुत
This radar must have been installed on all the planes
सारी प्लेन पे लगा रखी होंगी और ये रडार
I don't even come to check who is B2.
में भी नहीं आता ना चेक कर बी टू कौन
It is manufactured by Lockid
बनाता है इज इट मैन्युफैक्चर बाय लॉकीड
Lockid will probably be a B-2 aircraft
लॉकीड होगा शायद बी टू एयरक्राफ्ट
Manufacturer
मैन्युफैक्चरर
North Spirit Manufacturers North
नार्थ स्पिरिट मैन्युफैक्चरर्स नार्थ
Northrop Hugh Aircraft
नार्थोप हग एयरक्राफ्ट
wow i have never even heard northp
वाओ आई हैव नेवर इवन हर्ड नार्थप
but as a prime contractor with boring
बट एस अ प्राइम कांट्रेक्टर विद बोरिंग
Hughes and What
ह्यूज एंड व्हाट
[music]
[संगीत]
Interesting but they have technology
इंटरेस्टिंग बट दे दे हैव टेक्नोलॉजी
which they do not the world even does not know
व्हिच दे डू नॉट द वर्ल्ड इवन डजंट नो
I am convinced that this is a UFO
इनके पास आई एम कन्विंस कि जो ये यूएफओ
Sightings to whatever extent they occur
साइटिंग्स टू व्हाटएवर एक्सटेंट होती है
10 to 20% of those cases might be like this
उसमें से 10 से 20% केसेस ऐसे होते होंगे
They must have been looking for a flight to take
ये कोई फ्लाइट निकाल के लिए घुमा रहे होते
This must have happened when the bombing happened in 2001
होंगे ये जब 2001 में बॉम्बिंग की थी
When they brought down the twin towers
इन्होंने जब ट्विन टावर नीचे गिराए थे तो
then they use F2 raptors to bomb right
देन दे यूज़ F2 रैप्टर्स टू बॉम्ब है ना
People didn't even know Iraq was rappers back then
इराक तो तब रैपर्स पता भी नहीं था लोगों
what happens to them, they already had these
को होता क्या है तो इनके पास थे ऑलरेडी ये
They should have made this ending 20-30 years ago
20 30 साल पहले बना लेते हैं ये एंड बताते
no obviously because when I tell you then
नहीं ऑब्वियसली बिकॉज़ जब बता देंगे तो
What is the benefit Yes No Military strength
फायदा क्या है हां नहीं मिलिट्री स्ट्रेंथ
You must be keeping any guarantee, I dont believe it
रखते होंगे ना गारंटी मैं मान ही नहीं
can because my American military
सकता क्योंकि जो मेरे अमेरिकन मिलिट्री
I had friends in the college where I studied
में दोस्त थे मेरे जिस कॉलेज में पढ़ाई
I used to do infusion from military there as well
करता था वहां पे मिलिट्री से भी इन्फ्यूजन
I used to get a lot of attention from the faces of those people
आता था काफी अभी अ तो उन लोगों के चेहरे
But brother, there was relaxation regarding the war
पे जो भाई रिलैक्सेशन थी ना वॉर को लेके
It was a different kind of relaxation for them
वो एक अलग रिलैक्सेशन थी उन्हें उन्हें
You know, you don't know what we
पता है तुम्हें तो पता ही नहीं हमने क्या
It has been suppressed. And the stories I got from them
दबा रखा है। और उनसे जो कहानियां मैंने
I have heard about the weapons they have used
सुनी है अबाउट वेपन्स दे हैव यूज्ड इट्स
Just unreal out of this world kind of
जस्ट अनरियल आउट ऑफ दिस वर्ल्ड काइंड ऑफ़
Stuff. They have access. So yes and
स्टफ। इनके पास एक्सेस रहता है। तो हां और
If there is any military power then it will be the most
कोई भी मिलिट्री पावर होगी तो वो सबसे
First she will think that you should keep such weapon hidden
पहले ये सोचेगी ना ऐसे वेपन रख लो दबा के
The guy might not even know. May be you don't even know. also know
साले पता भी ना हो। पता भी ना हो। पता भी
no, because when the chance comes we will attack
ना हो क्योंकि जब मौका आएगा मारेंगे दबा
Of. And America is at the top in this matter.
के। और अमेरिका इस मामले में बहुत टॉप पे
Is. Very top, very. So now you will tell me
है। बहुत टॉप, बहुत। तो अब आप बताओगे
Why? you are spending billions on
क्यों? यू आर स्पेंडिंग बिलियंस ऑन
Research. Your military budget is only this much
रिसर्च। आपका बजट ही इतना है मिलिट्री का
Then why would you tell me? that and what you sell
तो फिर आप क्यों बताओगे? वो और जो तुम बेच
Countries like Pakistan are getting their F16
रहे हो पाकिस्तान जैसे देशों को F16 उसका
So you will break it like this if you are at war
तो तुम यूं तोड़ दोगे अगर तुमसे वॉर हो गया
So that's you then I mean that's from your childhood
तो वो तो तुम तब मतलब वो तुम्हारे बचपन के
There are toys. toys from the 1960's and 40's
खिलौने हैं। 1960 और 40 के खिलौने हैं
Your. now you are reusing them
तुम्हारे। अब तुम उनको रीयूज़ कर रहे हो कि
Friend, sell it somewhere else and buy it. You are selling it.
यार कहीं और बेच के खरीद लो। बेच रहे हो।
The technology remains. a mine plant
टेक्नोलॉजी बनी हुई है। एक मेरा प्लांट
The setup is . Come on brother, who wants to buy, buy
सेटअप है। चलो भाई किसको खरीदना है खरीद
Take. Right right right right right right. I
लो। राइट राइट राइट राइट राइट राइट। मैं
I was recently watching a video on how
अभी रिसेंटली एक वीडियो देख रहा था ऑन हाउ
Nuclear weapons were acquired by all
न्यूक्लियर वेपन्स वर एक्वायर्ड बाय ऑल
Countries. Of all the countries. So theirs is that
कंट्रीज। सारी कंट्रीज का। तो इनका तो वो
what was that project manhattan
था क्या है उस प्रोजेक्ट मैनहटन
project. Then how did Russia
प्रोजेक्ट। फिर किस तरीके से रशिया ने
They both caught him, how did the Germans catch him?
इसको पकड़ा दोनों ने पकड़ा कैसे जर्मन
Soldiers o German Scientist German
सोल्जर्स ओ जर्मन साइंटिस्ट जर्मन
Scientist, she did all the research
साइंटिस्ट सारी सारी रिसर्च साली इन्होंने
The Nazis had captured them
कर रखी थी नाजियों ने उनको पकड़ पकड़ के
They did this work, then how
इन्होंने ये काम किए फिर किस तरीके से
South Africa Israel Israel is confirmed
साउथ अफ्रीका इजराइल इजराइल तो कंफर्म ही
What does India not do after India?
नहीं करता है इंडिया इंडिया के बाद क्या
There was a sensation on that and still India has it
सेंशंस लगे उस पे और अभी भी इंडिया के पास
Pakistan has 200 nuclear war heads
200 न्यूक्लियर वॉर हेड्स हैं पाकिस्तान
has 150 something and this one has 25 thousand
के पास 150 कुछ हैं इसके पास 25 हजार हैं
which it has declared, the US has just
जो इसने डिक्लेअर किए हैं यूएस ने सिर्फ
And Russia has declared more than this
और रशिया ने इससे ज्यादा डिक्लेअर कर रखे
Yes, but the US will have many more. Which one
हैं बट यूएस के पास और बहुत होंगे। कौन सा
He was prepared that Russia had more war plans
वो तैयार बैठे कि रशिया के पास ज्यादा वॉर
There will be AIDS.
एड्स होंगे।
have you ever flown in a weird sector
आपने कभी किसी वियर्ड सेक्टर फ्लाई किया
Just like these issues had happened recently.
ऐसे जैसे अभी बीच में ये इशू हो गए थे।
Cannot fly over Pakistan.
पाकिस्तान के ऊपर फ्लाई नहीं कर सकते।
etsetra etsetra have you had some weird
एटसेट्रा एटसेट्रा हैव यू हैड सम वियर्ड
No, then if Pakistan gets blocked
नहीं पाकिस्तान ब्लॉक हो जाता है तो फिर
Let us leave from Ahmedabad below. Good
नीचे अहमदाबाद से हो के निकलते हैं। अच्छा
If you go out from the Gulf after crossing the entire Gulf
गल्फ से पूरा गल्फ से हो के निकलते हो तो
Your flight time increases. More
फ्लाइट टाइम बढ़ जाता है आपका। ज्यादा
You take the fuel with you. But not that weird
फ्यूल लेके जाते हो। बट ऐसा वियर्ड नहीं
I have flown in the weather many times. We
वेदर में बहुत बार फ्लाई किया है। हम
What is happening truly in turbulence?
व्हाट इज़ हैपनिंग ट्रूली इन टर्बुलेंस?
Like we only feel tremors
लाइक हम लोग तो सिर्फ झटके महसूस करते
Are. What do you guys see that we are looking at from the clouds
हैं। आप लोग क्या देखते हो कि हम बादल से
They are leaving. When the friend shakes a little bit
निकल रहे हैं। यार थोड़ा बहुत जब हिलता है
Neither is that ok. butt just like up
ना तो वो ठीक होता है। बट एकदम जैसे ऊपर
When you go you call him CB Clumlow
आप जाते हो तो उसको बोलते हैं सीबी क्लमलो
Nimbus clouds are very dangerous
निंबस क्लाउड्स वो बड़े खतरनाक होते हैं
They look big. there is no friend in it
वो दिखते हैं बड़े-बड़े। उसमें यार नहीं
We would have entered. well one thing that is said
घुसते हम। अच्छा एक चीज जो बताई जाती है
Us. Don't get into this, brother. That is not Chul
हमें। इसमें ना घुसना भाई। वो ना चूल ना
Go and see. Please don't show so much. They
जा के देखो। इतना मत दिखाना प्लीज। वो
It will destroy your ship. whatever happened indigo
जहाज तोड़ देगा आपका। जो भी हुआ ना इंडिगो
In the flight to Srinagar. yes yes in which
श्रीनगर वाली फ्लाइट में। हां हां जिसमें
It burst from the front. yes so right now the pilots
वो फटा आगे से। हां तो अभी पायलट्स को
It was grounded. And now DDC has
ग्राउंड कर दिया था। एंड अभी डीडीसी ने
His investigation has been completed.
उसकी इन्वेस्टिगेशन कंप्लीट किया है।
He asked for corrective training
उन्होंने करेक्टिव ट्रेनिंग के लिए बोला
to the pilots and according to the news
पायलट्स को और जिस हिसाब से न्यूज़ है
the way he worded it if you
उन्होंने जिस हिसाब से वर्डिंग आई अगर आप
If you read it you will understand. He too in
पढ़ोगे तो आप समझ में आ जाएगा। वो भी इन
some words are saying such that friend no
सम वर्ड्स ऐसा बोल रहे हैं कि यार नहीं
Should have gone. Look, your mistake has crept in
जाना चाहिए था। देखो घुस गए तुम्हारी गलती
Is. After that, whatever year you
है। उसके बाद जो तुम जिस साल में तुमने
You have landed that award
लैंड किया है वो तुम्हें अवार्ड मिलना
Needed There is appreciation too. We are brothers, very
चाहिए। अप्रिसिएशन भी है। हम भाई वो बहुत
how in difficult situations like theirs
डिफिकल्ट सिचुएशन में कैसे जैसे उनके तो
Half the thing had failed. Unreliable Air
आधी चीज तो फेल हो गई थी। अनरिलायबल एयर
Speed failed, this failed, that failed brother, how to land
स्पीड हो गई ये फेल वो फेल भाई कैसे लैंड
what did he do i.e. the trump card pilot who
किया उन्होंने मतलब तुरमखा पायलट ने जो
He landed but why did he go, brother?
लैंड कर दिया लेकिन गए ही क्यों भाई वो
How did you get in? Why did you get in? Meaning you got in
घुसे कैसे उसमें क्यों घुसे मतलब घुस गए
well you got in yes and this one like that is in it
अच्छा घुस गए हां और ये वैसे वाला इसमें
There were storms and torrents, what was in it?
तूफान टॉरेंट्स थे ना क्या था उसमें उसका
I also made a video so what happened in that
भी आई मेड अ वीडियो तो उसमें क्या हुआ जा
You are there, you saw the weather in front of you
रहे हो आप सामने आपको दिखा वेदर आ गया
There is a whole mountain range on the right side
राइट साइड में तो पूरी माउंटेन रेंज है
Pakistan is on the left side, we are
लेफ्ट साइड में पाकिस्तान है हम तो
He said if we want deviation then you
उन्होंने कहा हमें डेविएशन चाहिए तो आप
The person you are talking to says friend
जिस से बात कर रहे होते हो वो कहता है यार
go to the military the military says
मिलिट्री के पास जाओ मिलिट्री कहता है
You are a civil aircraft, Pakistan
तुमसे सिविल एयरक्राफ्ट हो तुम पाकिस्तान
Talk to Civil. They have
के सिविल से बात करो। इनके पास
There was no frequency. He is back in Delhi
फ्रीक्वेंसी नहीं थी। ये वापस दिल्ली के
Passed by. Asked for frequency from Delhi
पास गए। दिल्ली से फ्रीक्वेंसी मांगी
His. I called him. Now they also say
उसकी। उसको कॉल किया। अब वो भी कहते हैं
He must have called the military from behind
उन्होंने पीछे फोन लगाया होगा मिलिट्री को
Brother, what should I do? He is asking for it. They
भाई क्या करूं? ये मांग रहा है। उन्होंने
He might have refused. so brother if your
मना कर दिया होगा। तो भाई अगर तुम्हारा
Even if the weather had come 20 miles, all this would have happened
वेदर 20 माइल भी आ गया तो ये सब होते तो
You have reached 20 miles. You are at his doorstep
तुम 20 माइल पे पहुंच गए। तुम उसकी दहलीज
You are standing there. So he said he will not let me go.
पे खड़े हो। तो उसने कहा नहीं जाने देंगे।
So, brother, what should I do now? left hand to
तो कहा भाई अब क्या करें? लेफ्ट हैंड तो
I just entered. So you entered and then you got inside
घुस ही गए। तो घुस गए तो फिर अंदर हो गया
Scandal. So
कांड। तो
No turn back till today due to weather
आज तक कोई भी टर्न बैक वेदर की वजह से
It did not happen. So he is saying that they should
नहीं हुआ। तो वही कह रहे हैं कि दे शुड
have turned back. Delhi was very far away
हैव टर्न बैक। दिल्ली ज्यादा दूर तो था
I would not have gone away. half an hour more than that
नहीं चले ही जाते। आधा पौना घंटा उससे भी
The entire flight takes at least half an hour.
कम आधा पौना घंटा तो पूरी फ्लाइट होती है।
should we go back or else people are saying that
वापस चले जाते या फिर लोग कह रहे हैं कि
I could have dropped you somewhere there. So maybe let's go
वहीं कहीं उतार देते। तो हो सकता है चलो
I assume that there was weather in the whole thing, so no
मैं मान लो कि पूरे में वेदर था तो नहीं
came to my mind. but if you are safe
दिमाग में आया। लेकिन अगर अगर तुम सेफ
You are playing right and you have played extra
प्ले कर रहे हो ना और तुमने एक्स्ट्रा
Burned the fuel. Passenger Inconveniences
फ्यूल बर्न कर दिया। पैसेंजर इनक्वीनियंस
It also happened. Anything can happen. bro a little bit
भी हो गई। कुछ भी हो गया। भाई थोड़ा बहुत
why would you be interested in the company but if this happens
होगा आप कंपनी की क्यों लेकिन अगर ऐसा
If a scandal happens then it will become nation wide news
कांड हो जाए ना तो फिर नेशन वाइड न्यूज़ बन
She goes. we are actually now after this there
जाती है। हम एक्चुअली अब आफ्टर दिस देयर
There is a lot of news that there is no such and such flight
इज अ लॉट ऑफ़ न्यूज़ कि फलानी फ्लाइट नहीं
flew. Did such and such flight raise any issue?
उड़ी। फलानी फ्लाइट ने कोई इशू रेज कर
Gave. It was a British Airways flight. I
दिया। एक ब्रिटिश एयरवेज की फ्लाइट थी। आई
Think to Chennai. london chennai tha sector
थिंक टू चेन्नई। लंदन चेन्नई था सेक्टर
Don't know which one it was. any why on that too
पता नहीं कौन सा था। उस पे भी कोई व्हिच
Is again a Boeing, it is of the same make.
इज अगेन अ बोइंग उसी उसी मेक का है वो।
And why is that happening? why do you
एंड व्हाई इज़ दैट हैपनिंग? व्हाई डू यू
Think? I can't say about the British why
थिंक? आई कांट से अबाउट ब्रिटिश ने क्यों
Did? But what I know is that Air India
किया? बट जो मुझे ये पता है कि एयर इंडिया
Brother, some of the pilots are upset right now. upset
में भाई थोड़े से पायलट्स अभी खफा हैं। खफा
Is. Plus they also feel a little bit that
है। प्लस थोड़ा सा उनको ये भी लग रहा है कि
Friend, we are sitting in an airplane. Yes
यार साला जहाज में तो हम बैठे हैं ना। हां
Right. The management is sitting downstairs. Right?
राइट। मैनेजमेंट तो नीचे बैठी है। राइट?
Engineering is also sitting down. Roasting also
इंजीनियरिंग भी नीचे बैठी है। रोस्टिंग भी
She is sitting down. and we are in the ship so we
नीचे बैठी है। और साला हम जहाज में तो हम
I am sitting. so if you if you're giving me
बैठे हैं। तो अगर तुम इफ यू आर गिविंग मी
A okay aircraft. i will not take a
अ ओके एयरक्राफ्ट। आई विल विल नॉट टेक अ
Ok aircraft also now. give me a
ओके एयरक्राफ्ट आल्सो नाउ। गिव मी अ
The Perfect Aircraft to Fly. Why should I
परफेक्ट एयरक्राफ्ट टू फ्लाई। मैं क्यों
Should I take it? There are three M's in it. one of mine
लेके जाऊं? उसमें तीन एम है। एक मेरा
friend says that friend so there are two packs
दोस्त कहता है कि यार सो देयर आर टू पैक्स
In the aircraft. Pax Means Air
इन द एयरक्राफ्ट। पैक्स मतलब एयर
There are conditioning packs. and a pack
कंडीशनिंग के पैक्स होते हैं। और एक पैक
I run two CAKes as backup. Cabin Air
को बैकअप में दो कैक चलाते हैं। कैबिन एयर
What do you say about pressure controller? Boeing
प्रेशर कंट्रोलर क्या बोलते हैं? बोइंग
I probably say this. so two packs end
में शायद ये बोलते हैं। सो टू पैक्स एंड
Two caiques behind a pack. So that makes four cakes.
एक पैक के पीछे दो कैक। तो चार कैक हो गए।
He says Sir one cage is bad. Two CAGs
वो कहता है सर एक कैग खराब है। दो कैग
It is bad. Take it. ML says take it. One
खराब है। ले जाओ। एमएल कहता है ले जाओ। एक
You can do sector. are you going to delhi and
सेक्टर कर सकते हो। दिल्ली जा रहे हो और
That was an outbound flight. so from there
वो बाहर की फ्लाइट थी। तो वहां का
The engineer also says sir don't park here
इंजीनियर भी कहता है सर यहां मत खड़ा करो
ship. And you know, a lot goes into irrigation
जहाज। और पता है इरिगेशन में बहुत चलता
Is. Sir don't write this because you will write it
है। सर इसको लिखो मत क्योंकि तुम लिख दोगे
So I will have to go through the whole procedure. Sir
तो मुझे पूरा प्रोसीजर करना पड़ेगा। सर
don't write. I will give you the okay for this as well
लिखो मत। मैं इसको भी आपको ओके करके दे
I am keeping the status. You take him away. you this
रहा हूं स्टेटस। आप ले जाओ उसको। आप ये
Station the ship in Delhi. Yours in Delhi
जहाज दिल्ली खड़ा कर दो। दिल्ली में आपकी
There is a company. She will make it. all the parts are there
कंपनी है। वो बना देगी। पार्ट्स भी है सब
There is something. This is one. The engineering and
कुछ है। ये एक होता है। ये इंजीनियरिंग और
Pilots' all time runs. The pilots say
पायलट्स का ऑल टाइम चलता है। पायलट्स कहता
yes I will write it. Sir don't write the list
है मैं लिखूंगा। सर लिस्ट को लिखो मत
Please. The flight will be delayed. come to me
प्लीज। फ्लाइट डिली हो जाएगी। मेरे पे आ
Will go. And look friend, this is one thing out of 100
जाएगा। और यार देखो 100 बात की एक बात यह
So now the companies also have to change a bit
तो थोड़ा कंपनीज़ को भी अब चेंज करना
It will have to be I don't want to live life for even a minute
पड़ेगा। एक-ए मिनट की जिंदगिरी नहीं करनी
Needed Companies are very important that 1 minute
चाहिए। कंपनीज़ आर वेरी एडममेंट कि 1 मिनट
that there should be no delay and he is the ground staff
की डिले भी ना आए और वो ग्राउंड स्टाफ है
No, he carries too much
ना वो बहुत ज्यादा लेके चलता है वो
Because I think they would have been killed a lot
क्योंकि मुझे लगता है उनकी बहुत मारी जाती
is behind this thing that there is a delay of 3 minutes
है इस चीज के पीछे कि 3 मिनट का डिले हो
Went. They might have killed him. Us
गया। उन शायद उनकी मार लेते होंगे। हमें
So I don't know whether they will kill me or not. But the
तो नहीं पता मारते हैं कि नहीं। लेकिन जिस
According to them, that is their thing, not their behavior
हिसाब से उनका वो होता है ना कि बिहेवियर
Brother, they are always torn. We Sir Delay
भाई उनकी फटी पड़ी रहती है। हम सर डिले
It should not come. delay come over me delay
नहीं आनी चाहिए। डिले मेरे ऊपर डिले आ
will go. So that one minute delay is what the poor guy is waiting for
जाएगी। तो वो एक-ए मिनट की डिले को बेचारे
They keep trying to do okay so that it doesn't happen
ओके करने में लगे रहते हैं कि वो ना हो
Had to cut. yes yes what do they say sir
काटना पड़े। हां हां वो क्या कहते हैं सर
don't write it in this, post it on etsy
इसमें लिखो मत आप एटीसी पे डाल देना
So you can tell me that the ship arrived on time
कि आप कह दे ना कि जहाज टाइम पे मिल गया
I called ATC and the ATC called
था मैंने एटीसी को कॉल दी एटीसी ने
Clearance was not given, put it on ATC
क्लीयरेंस नहीं दी एटीसी पे डाल देना
Because if you post it on ATC then there will be no inquiry
क्योंकि एटीसी पे डालोगे तो कोई पूछताछ
nothing will happen okay okay so
नहीं होगी कुछ नहीं होगा ठीक ठीक हां तो
Sometimes friend, we get so much that
कभी-कभी यार हमें इतना हो जाता है ना कि
Bhai means why are you working this pressure
भाई मतलब व्हाई आर यू वर्किंग ये प्रेशर
But I mean you don't even need crores of rupees
लेके मतलब ऐसा भी तेरे को कोई करोड़ों
The company is not paying the money, brother, that is correct
रुपए नहीं दे रही कंपनी भाई सही बात सही
This is true, these are not the stakes of life
बात सही बात ये ये तो जीवन के स्टेक नहीं
It should be yours, yes right, yes whatever it is
होने चाहिए तेरे हां राइट हां चल जो भी है
And the guy who is working in this position
और जो बंदा वो काम कर रहा है इस पोजीशन
He gets a normal salary brother
में उसको एक नॉर्मल सैलरी मिलती है भाई
Brother yes, for that brother take so much pressure
भाई हां उसके लिए तो भाई इतना प्रेशर ले
It happens every day, be it one day or two days
रहा है वो भी हर दिन एक दिन हो 2 दिन हो
It's an everyday story, brother.
हर रोज की रोज की कहानी है भाई रोज की
The story is that there is a fight of two minutes, sir
कहानी है दो-दो मिनट की लड़ाई होती है सर
don't put it on me, put it on ATC
मेरे पे मत डाल देना एटीसी में डाल देना
The engineer down below says, Sir, don't bother me
वो नीचे इंजीनियर कहता है सर मेरे में मत
put it in ATC that is a fight
डालना एटीसी में डाल देना वो फाइट होती है
yes and it happened to me you were 3 minutes late
हां और मेरे साथ हुआ है 3 मिनट लेट हो
You go, you land, you get an email from the company
जाते हो आप लैंड होते हो मेल आता है कंपनी
why explain this 3 minute delay brother one thing
का एक्सप्लेन दिस 3 मिनट डिले भाई एक बात
Tell me, as a consumer, I feel that
बताओ एज अ कंसूमर हमें तो लगता है कि
Flights are more than happy to be like you
फ्लाइट्स आर मोर दैन हैप्पी टू बी लाइक आप
I sit here for two to four to five hours
सारे बैठ मैं तो दो-दो चार-चार पांच घंटे
I am sitting, flight is not flying, yes, yes and
बैठा हूं फ्लाइट नहीं उड़ हां हां और
Consumers we learn which flights not to take
कंज्यूमर वी लर्न कौन सी फ्लाइट नहीं लेनी
Because all this will definitely get delayed.
है क्योंकि यह तो सारी डिले होगी ही होगी।
Yes, look, it could be like Air India's
हां देखो हो सकता है जैसे Air I इंडिया का
This might happen but friend Indigo that
ऐसा होता होगा लेकिन यार इंडिगो वो तो
She is very strict about time, she is Indigo
काफी स्ट्रिक्ट है टाइम पे वो तो इंडिगो
is the only flight you take
इज़ द ओनली फ्लाइट जो आप लेते हो वो तो
These are the people who beat you up every couple of minutes
एक-ए दोद मिनट पे डंडा कर देते हैं लोग है
no it happens there or not
ना तो वहां पे तो चलता है ऐसा कि नहीं
If you want then post it on Etsy or
होना चाहिए तो एटीसी पे डाल देना या डाल
But in that case, friend, there is a lot of pressure
देना बट तो उस चक्कर में यार प्रेशर काफी
much remains on the whole system that
ज्यादा पूरे सिस्टम पे बना रहता है कि
have to do have to do have to do have to do
करना है करना है करना है करना है करना है
If you want to do it, then there shouldn't be that much pressure
करना तो वो प्रेशर इतना भी नहीं होना
no so you are saying now pilots are
चाहिए नहीं सो यू आर सेइंग नाओ पायलट्स आर
not okay with flying and okay yes yes so
नॉट ओके विद फ्लाइंग एंड ओके हां हां तो
I was telling you there that friend, he says
वो मैं वहां कह रहा था कि यार वो कहता है
Sir sir, I will give it to you after giving it okay. You
सर सर मैं इसको ओके करके देता हूं। आप
don't write. don't write. You tell me that this
लिखना मत। लिखना मत। आप बोल देना कि ये
Failure came in the air. Ok. So on this
फेलियर इन एयर आया था। ठीक है। तो इस पे
There will be no responsibility. Yes. That
नहीं बनेगी रिस्पोंसिबिलिटी। हां। कि
That failure occurred after take off. and to everyone
आफ्टर टेक ऑफ वो फेलियर आया था। और सबको
Do you know where that take off failure occurred? Air
पता है वो टेक ऑफ फेलियर कहां आया था। एयर
India also knows it. He also knows this.
इंडिया को भी पता है। इसको भी पता है।
All the airlines know it. Everyone knows.
सारी एयरलाइन को पता है। सबको पता है।
Because it is recorded by the system
क्योंकि वो तो रिकॉर्डेड है ना सिस्टम
In. Right. So that's what I say when DDC
में। राइट। तो वही मैं कहता हूं जब डीडीसी
Only Air India 171 conducts audit
ऑडिट करता है ना तो सिर्फ Air इंडिया 171
It does not open. But all these scandals come to light.
नहीं खुलता। पर ये सारे कांड खुलते हैं।
What the hell are you doing in maintenance.
तुम साला मेंटेनेंस में कर क्या रहे हो।
And I'm saying it might happen
और मैं कह रहा हूं कि हो सकता है ऐसा हुआ
yes. Yet I say that I
हो। मैं फिर भी वो कह रहा हूं कि मुझे
I don't know whether it will happen or not.
नहीं पता कि होता होगा कि नहीं होता होगा।
But the stories that I am getting to hear, brother
बट जो स्टोरीज सुनने को आ रही है तो भाई
He took off. A brother said
ने उसने टेक ऑफ किया। एक भाई ने कहता है
Friend, I had two cakes blown away. Still it
यार मेरे दो कैक उड़े हुए थे। फिर भी इट
It's okay to fly with two cakes. in the air
इज ओके टू फ्लाई विद टू कैक्स। हवा में
Went. A cacique flew into the air. now now one
गया। एक कैक हवा में उड़ गया। अब अब एक
I am blowing it on the cake. So he had some
कैक पे उड़ा रहा हूं मैं। तो उसने किसी
Had decked off from the station. now it is very
स्टेशन से डेक ऑफ किया था। अब इट इज़ वेरी
Hard for the aircraft to maintain
हार्ड फॉर द एयरक्राफ्ट टू मेंटेन
Aircraft cabin pressure no. those 10 12 feet
एयरक्राफ्ट कैबिन प्रेशर ना। वो 10 12 फीट
He must have reached there. He got a warning. He
पे पहुंचा होगा। उसको वार्निंग आ गई। उसने
Said I will not climb at 3000 feet.
कहा मैं 3000 फीट पे नहीं क्लाइम करूंगा।
Maybe it is not safe that we could not maintain it
होगा इट इज़ नॉट सेफ कि नहीं मेंटेन कर पाए
pressure then i will design emergency
प्रेशर तो फिर मैं इमरजेंसी डिजाइन करूंगा
I am right, he is back at his base
हम सही बात वो वापस आ गया अपने बेस पे मैं
Why should I not take a chance, this is the thing
चांस लेना ही नहीं क्यों लूं हम तो बात ये
that friend now if again in this
है कि यार अब फिर से इसमें अगर
There will be an investigation and that pilot
इन्वेस्टिगेशन होगी और उस उस पायलट को
you were penalized for this
पीनलाइज किया गया था इस चीज के लिए तुमने
Why did we turn back the Cabin CAG
टर्न बैक क्यों कर दिया हम कैबिन कैग की
There won't be any warning, he would have gone away saying
वार्निंग तो नहीं आएगी ना चले जाते वो कह
Sir I was being safe, we are the only one left
रहे हैं सर आई वास बीइंग सेफ हम एक ही बचा
There was no warning but if it came my friend
है वार्निंग तो नहीं आई लेकिन अगर यार आई
I'm not feeling safe lest I blow one
एम नॉट फीलिंग सेफ ना कि मैं एक पे उड़ाऊं
Buddy
यार
We are ML, right ML brother, ML only then
हम जो एमएल होती है ना एमएल भाई एमएल तभी
It is valid as long as you are on ground.
तक वैलिड होती है जब तक आप ऑन ग्राउंड हो।
Once you take off ML has no
एक बार आप टेक ऑफ करके एमएल हैज़ नो
Meaning. Then you can make a practical decision
मीनिंग। फिर तो आप प्रैक्टिकल डिसीजन
practical so practical means if
प्रैक्टिकल तो प्रैक्टिकल मतलब अगर
If you want to fly an aircraft then let's go in the aircraft
एयरक्राफ्ट चलना है तो चलो एयरक्राफ्ट में
If you get a warning, come back. But one of yours
वार्निंग आई तो वापस आओ। बट एक आपका
There is also experience, isn't it, brother?
एक्सपीरियंस भी तो होता है ना भाई कि चार
there is one. Should I take off? Long Sector
है एक है। मैं टेक ऑफ जाऊं। लंबा सेक्टर
Is.
है।
A brother says there are two radars in the weather Boeing
एक भाई कहता है वेदर बोइंग में दो रेडार
There are. We have a weather radar that says
होते हैं। हम तो वेदर रेडार कहता है एक
I was a failure. Nml allows you to dispatch with
फेल था। एन एमएल अलाउस यू टू डिस्पैच विद
one field aircraft he dispatched
वन फेल्ड एयरक्राफ्ट उसने डिस्पैच किया एक
The wind has turned and whatever is blowing seems to be like this
हवा मुड़ गया और जो चल भी रहा होगा वो ऐसा
By clicking OK the status, the status is found and OK
ही स्टेटस ओके करके स्टेटस फाउंड एंड ओके
And dispatch sends it with the same tape
एंड डिस्पैच वही टेप लगा के भेज देता है
which we call the one that turned in the air
जो हम एक उसका हवा में मुड़ गया कहता है
I am sitting on top of Iran so God knows that
मैं ईरान के ऊपर बैठा हूं तो भगवान का वो
The weather was clear, there was no weather at that time
था कि वेदर क्लियर था उस समय कोई वेदर
was not from my position to Delhi
नहीं था फ्रॉम माय पोजीशन टू दिल्ली
The weather was clear and the depth was 2 feet (2000 feet).
क्लियर वेदर था और नीचे भी 2 फीट 2000 फीट
There was a ship below so I thought if there was one ahead
नीचे जहाज था तो मुझे लगा आगे अगर होगा भी
Then after seeing him I will go away
तो उसको देख देख के चला जाऊंगा मैं उसको
So brother you can talk to him below
तो भाई उससे बात कर सकते हैं नीचे वाले
From. Yes you can do it. you can say that butt
से। हां कर सकते हो। यू कैन से कि बट करते
no because there is a lot of traffic
नहीं है क्योंकि बहुत वो ट्रैफिक होता है
Not on frequency. Right? good beans
ना फ्रीक्वेंसी पे। राइट? अच्छा सेम
The frequency is the same frequency, right?
फ्रीक्वेंसी सेम फ्रीक्वेंसी होता है ना।
Well If You're Long Down to One Two 1.7
अच्छा इफ यू आर लॉन्ग डाउन टू वन टू 1.7
So everybody is on two one7 so everybody is on that
तो एवरीवन इज़ ऑन टू वन7 तो सब लोग उस पे
Let's talk. Then you can talk to ATC.
बात करते हैं। तो आप एटीसी से बात करते
yes. Many times it has happened that no one comes.
हो। बहुत बार ऐसा हुआ है कि कोई नहीं आता।
When we go to Guwahati etc.
हम लोग यार जब गुवाहाटी वगैरह जाते हैं
There is a lot of military activity there.
वहां पे मिलिट्री एक्टिविटी काफी होती है।
Those people are flying at low level sometimes
वो लोग ना लो लेवल पे कभी-कभी उड़ रहे
There are. So there is no ATC contact.
होते हैं। तो एटीसी कांटेक्ट नहीं होता।
He says that friend tell him that here
वो बोलता है कि यार इसको बोलना कि यहां
Let's go. I tell him no.
चला जाए। नो बोल देता है उसको।
Interesting. ATC is saying go here
इंटरेस्टिंग। एटीसी कह रहा है यहां चला
let's go. Because we're on top. we can catch
जाए। क्योंकि हम ऊपर हैं। हम पकड़ सकते
He has it. ATC and he both were on low level
हैं उसको। एटीसी और वो दोनों लो लेवल पे
Are. If it is interesting then you can talk about it
हैं। इंटरेस्टिंग तो बात तो कर सकते हो
In such situations it is normal to talk but we
ऐसी सिचुएशन में तो हो जाती है बात बट हम
And this Airbus is a French company Being is
एंड दिस एयरबस इज अ फ्रेंच कंपनी Being इज़
American Company American Company and How Do It
अमेरिकन कंपनी अमेरिकन कंपनी एंड हाउ डू
They match up like from a pure Airbus
दे मैच अप लाइक फ्रॉम अ प्योर एयरबस
What Runs Versus Boeing Perspective
वर्सेस बोइंग पर्सेक्टिव क्या चलता है
How does it run in such a narrow body
कैसे चलता है सो नैरो बॉडी में तो काफी
The competition was 737 vs Airbus 320
कॉम्पटीशन था इनका 737 वर्सेस एयरबus 320
ok this narrow body narrow body means single
अच्छा ये नैरो बॉडी नैरो बॉडी मतलब सिंगल
Seat like this in the island Seat like this white
आईलैंड में इस तरह सीट इस तरह सीट वाइट
There are two oils in the body, I understood it correctly
बॉडी में दो ऑइल होती ठीक समझ गया मैं तो
Their flagship is 737 and this one has just 320
इनका है फ्लैकशिप है 737 इसका है बस 320
Now 320 has been upgraded to Neo, bring less
अब 320 ने अपग्रेड कर दिया Neo ले आए लेस
15 to 20% fuel savings are there in it
15 टू 20% फ्यूल सेविंग्स उसमें भाई धड़ले
Orders came from there, there is a little left out in these
से ऑर्डर आ गए इन पे वो थोड़ा लेफ्ट आउट
I started feeling something and she told me to do something too
फील्स करने लगा उसने कहा मुझे भी कुछ करना
so if they brought the 737 max then this was a
है तो वो 737 मैक्स लेके आए तो दिस वाज़ अ
Typical Boeing vs Airbus competition
टिपिकल बोइंग वर्सेस एयरबस कॉमटीशन तो
If you are going to the airport, look at
एयरपोर्ट पे अगर आप जा रहे हो तो देखना
If there is any Airbus then it is a little higher
कोई भी एयरबस होगा तो थोड़ा इट्स हायर
From the ground, we are Boeing 767
फ्रॉम द ग्राउंड हम है ना तो बोइंग थोड़ा
take if you see side by side then air bus this
लो इफ यू सी साइड बाय साइड तो एयर बस ये
If it is Boeing then it's here, so the wings are down
है तो बोइंग यहां पे है तो विंग्स भी नीचे
We will be there. So the engine ground clearance
होंगे हम। तो इंजन का ग्राउंड क्लीयरेंस
The engines are also lower, under the wings. R Little
भी कम विंग्स के नीचे इंजन है। आर लिटल
Closer to the Ground We're a Little Bit Closer to the Ground
क्लोजर टू द ग्राउंड हम एयरब्स के थोड़ा
Up to the ground. So Airbs has liberty
ऊपर टू द ग्राउंड। तो एयरब्स हैज़ लिबर्टी
To make a slightly bigger engine. We to this
टू मेक अ स्लाइटली बड़ा इंजन। हम तो इसको
It is called turbo fan engine. Hum Sleep Turbo
बोलते हैं टर्बो फैन इंजन। हम सो टर्बो
They are more fuel efficient in fans. they make
फैन में दे आर मोर फ्यूल एफिशिएंट। दे मेक
Less noise and 80% of the air bypasses the
लेस नॉइज़ एंड 80% ऑफ द एयर बायपासेस द
engine. They are high bypass ratio enj. We
इंजन। दे आर हाई बाईपास रेशियो इंज। हम
Only 20% old jets if you look hard
ओनली 20% पुराने जेट्स अगर आप देखो बहुत
military jets make big noises there
मिलिट्री जेट्स बड़े शोर करते हैं दे आर वै
Loud hum because they are pure jet engines
लाउड हम बिकॉज़ दे आर प्योर जेट इंज आर
Turbo fan engines are not pure jet engines
टर्बो फैन इंज आर नॉट प्योर जेट इंजन
Because 80% of the air bypasses the core
क्योंकि 80% एयर बायपासेस द कोर
Interesting so they cushion the sound
इंटरेस्टिंग तो वो साउंड को कुशन कर देते
Are. So there was no space on the Boeing because
हैं। तो बोइंग पे ना जगह नहीं थी क्योंकि
That guy is already downstairs. then they did not
साला ऑलरेडी नीचे है वो। तो दे डिड नॉट
Have space to make a high bypass ratio. So
हैव स्पेस टू मेक अ हाई बाईपास रेशियो। तो
This is the wing. This is the wing. Ok? these wing
ये विंग है। ये विंग है। ठीक है? ये विंग
Is. You are installing the engine here. So he
है। आप इंजन यहां लगा रहे हो। तो उन्होंने
Said we will not plant it here. we are the engine
कहा हम यहां नहीं लगाएंगे। हम इंजन ऐसे
Will enclose. Ok? Is it okay? and we will
लगा देंगे। ओके? ठीक है ना? एंड वी विल
make a big engine and let's compete
मेक अ बिग इंजन एंड चलो कमपीट कर देंगे
With Air Bus. and we will also give you
एयर बस के साथ। एंड वी विल आल्सो गिव यू
15 The 20% Fuel Saving Was Named 737 Max
15 20% फ्यूल सेविंग 737 मैक्स नाम था
His. Yes. So friend there is immense power and an engine
उसका। हां। तो यार इमेंस पावर ना एक इंजन
Imus produces power. When you're on Imus
इमस पावर प्रोड्यूस करता है। जब आप इमस
If you produce power, even a little
पावर प्रोड्यूस करते हो तो थोड़ा सा भी
You will have vectors which contain force
आपका जो वेक्टर्स पड़े होंगे जिसमें फोर्स
the vector of force coming from here and here
का वेक्टर यहां से आ रहा है फोर्स और यहां
It is coming from. then it will give you a certain
से आ रहा है। तो इट विल गिव यू अ सर्टेन
Delta. Right? We will change your thrust,
डेल्टा। राइट? हम आपका थ्रस्ट चेंज होगा,
The torque will change. Many things will change.
टॉर्क चेंज होगा। बहुत चीजें चेंज होंगी।
Hmm. So how to do it now? they said it was
हम्। तो अब उसको कैसे करें? दे सेड इट वाज़
Producing Ah A Slightly Pitched Up
प्रोड्यूसिंग अह अ स्लाइटली पिच अप
Attitude. when you put full power it was
एटीट्यूड। व्हेन यू पुट फुल पावर इट वास
Giving the aircraft a slightly pitch-up
गिविंग द एयरक्राफ्ट अ स्लाइटली पिच-अप
Attitude. So he said how to correct it
एटीट्यूड। तो उसने कहा उसको करेक्ट कैसे
do? Let's do one thing. we have made a
करेंगे? एक काम करते हैं। वी हैव मेड अ
Software Wherever You Put Full Power in the
सॉफ्टवेयर व्हेनएवर यू पुट फुल पावर द
The aircraft will automatically put its snows
एयरक्राफ्ट विल ऑटोमेटिकली पुट इट्स स्नोज़
Down. Got it. So that counter balance
डाउन। गॉट इट। तो वो काउंटर बैलेंस कर
will give. now it this function was called am
देगा। नाउ इट दिस फंक्शन वाज़ कॉल्ड एम
Cash. Pull up my cash. What is M Cash?
कैश। पुल अप करियो एम कैश। एम कैश क्या
It happens? Full form. Yes, it is watching
होता है? फुल फॉर्म। हां, यह देख रहा है
The engine that he had photographed was behind
उसने जो इंजन जो उसने फोटो लगाई थी पीछे
Look at this Boeing, it's a little down. and Airbus
यो बोइंग ने देख थोड़ा नीचे है। और एयरबस
The clearance is above. it's still not very
का क्लीयरेंस ऊपर है। इट्स स्टिल नॉट वेरी
clear. yes down down down down no. Yes
क्लियर। हां नीचे नीचे नीचे नीचे ना। हां
First Rear Left Left Left No Yes
फर्स्ट पीछे लेफ्ट लेफ्ट लेफ्ट नहीं हां
this this look this. Yes. So left is Airbus.
ये ये देख ये। हां। सो लेफ्ट इज़ एयरबस।
Yes. Right is Boeing. Airbnb Hire. Right? It
हां। राइट इज़ बोइंग। एयरब हायर। राइट? इट
Has more ground clearance. Right? So They Are Here
हेज़ मोर ग्राउंड क्लीयरेंस। राइट? सो द दे
Debert to Make Slightly Better Bypass
देबर्ट टू मेक स्लाइटली बेटर बायपास
Engines. Interesting.
इंजन्स। इंटरेस्टिंग।
Interesting. Please back once. Yes. MK
इंटरेस्टिंग। बैक करिए एक बार। हां। एमके
Search it. Search MK. MCS right? Yes
सर्च कर। एमके सर्च कर। एमसीएस ना? हां
Maneuvering Characteristic Argumentation
मैनुवरिंग कररेक्टरिस्टिक ऑर्गुममेंटेशन
The system has gone down so this is it
सिस्टम अच्छा नीचे आ गया ना ये सो ये
He said that we have this in the software
इन्होंने कहा कि हमने सॉफ्टवेयर में ये
When I put it on, he said this is not it
लगा दिया तो इन्होंने कहा दिस इज नॉट
Necessary for pilots to know okay this is
नेसेसरी फॉर पायलट्स टू नो ओके दिस इज
just a thing that the plane will do yes we did
जस्ट अ थिंग दैट द प्लेन विल डू हां हमने
it's a software and we have made
बनाया है इट्स अ सॉफ्टवेयर एंड वी हैव
Embed that in the systems and pilot it
एंबेड दैट इन द सिस्टम्स एंड पायलट का
No input is required, it's an automatic feature
इनपुट चाहिए ही नहीं इट्स अ ऑटोमेटिक फीचर
which will counter balance the excess
व्हिच विल काउंटर बैलेंस दी एक्सेसिव
Pitchup Got It Pilot also knows about it
पिचअप गॉट इट पायलट को उसकी जानकारी भी
no and he said that the 737 which flies
नहीं की और उन्होंने कहा कि 737 जो फ्लाई
Does the 737 Max have to fly?
करता है 737 मैक्स फ्लाई करने के लिए इट
just to our ground class is enough same
जस्ट टू आवर ग्राउंड क्लास इज इनफ सेम है
You fly everything, only the pilots know
सब कुछ तो फ्लाई करो आप तो पायलट्स को पता
no what is m cash then do it twice
नहीं एम कैश क्या होता है तो दो बार ऐसा
m cash mail function is done brother
हुआ एम कैश मैल फंक्शन हो गया भाई
So what does mcsh do with mcsh mail function
तो एम कैश मल मैल फंक्शन ये एमcsh क्या कर
he is putting his nose down and this one and I
रहा है नोज़ डाउन डाल रहा है हम और इसने
gave the nose down command
नोज़ डाउन कमांड दे दिया
And the plane went down, o the pilots knew
और जहाज नीचे चला गया ओ वो पायलट्स को पता
no what is MC does it count this
ही नहीं एमc होता क्या है इसको काउंट इसको
Could have countered as well. some such system
काउंटर भी कर सकते थे। कुछ ऐसा एक सिस्टम
tha which you move but it was you need ims to
था व्हिच यू मूव बट इट वा यू नीड इमस फ़ टू
Move. Later it was done in SIM also.
मूव। बाद में सिम में भी किया गया।
Humanly an average male cannot move that.
ह्यूमनली एक एवरेज मेल कैन नॉट मूव दैट।
It takes that much force because it's good friend
उतना भी फोर्स लगता है बिकॉज़ अच्छा यार ये
All the movements that happen with the aircraft
सब जो मूवमेंट्स होते हैं ना एयरक्राफ्ट
that these electronically and hydraulically
के ये इलेक्ट्रॉनिकली और हाइड्रोलिकली जब
Flash flaps move hydraulically
फ्लैश फ्लैप्स मूव हाइड्रोलिकली मूव होते
Are. In a small aircraft you do the labour yourself
हैं। छोटे एयरक्राफ्ट में तुम खुद लेबर
Do you move? when you're flying with a
मूव करते हो। व्हेन यू फ्लाइंग विथ अ
Speed of 200 nautical miles and 250 knots.
स्पीड ऑफ़ 200 नॉटिकल माइल्स और 250 नॉट्स।
There is an air pressure. I am, right? Right.
देयर इज़ अ एयर प्रेशर। हम् है ना? राइट।
so you can't move a surface when there is
तो यू कैन नॉट मूव अ सरफेस व्हेन देयर इज
So much air pressure. not by human force
सो मच एयर प्रेशर। ह्यूमन फोर्स से नहीं
You can do it. We do that even in the sim
कर सकते आप। हम तो वो उन्होंने सिम में भी
I tried it. It was not possible. But
ट्राई किया। पॉसिबल नहीं था। बट
Interesting thing happened again that this MKS
इंटरेस्टिंग वो फिर हुआ कि यार ये एमकेएस
How did you pass it? So he said that
पास कैसे कर दिया? तो उन्होंने कहा कि
He passed the FSA in a hurry
जल्दी-जल्दी में उन्होंने एफएसए पास करा
Diya because they were losing the race to air bus.
दिया बिकॉज़ दे वर लूजिंग द रेस टू एयर बस।
Okay, okay, ICIC. Yes. so this
अच्छा ओके ओके आई सी आई सी। हां। तो ये
Race also has a direct impact, brother.
रेस का भी फिर डायरेक्ट इंपैक्ट है भाई।
Like means safety and the symptoms are
लाइक मतलब सेफ्टी और जो सिम्प्टम्स है वो
Then it depends on humans and pilots. Yes. So
फिर इंसानों पे और पायलटों पे है। हां। तो
There were two crashes. Liner 610 down. We and
दो क्रैश हुए थे। लाइनर 610 नीचे। हम और
An Ethiopian bean also crashed. a there
एक इथोपियन भी क्रैश हुआ था सेम। एक देयर
there is one more thing i think which is worth
इज़ वन मोर थिंग आई थिंक व्हिच इज़ वर्थ
Talking about. Brother you were telling me what
टॉकिंग अबाउट। भाई आप बता रहे थे किस
Pointing out pilot error in a way is very
तरीके से पायलट एरर पॉइंट करना इज़ वेरी
Convenient for all parties involved.
कन्वीनिएंट फॉर ऑल पार्टीज इन्वॉल्व्ड।
because then Boeing or Air India
क्योंकि फिर बोयंग को या एयर इंडिया को
No investigation needs to be run.
कोई इन्वेस्टिगेशन रन नहीं करनी।
Insurance money can be obtained very easily.
इंश्योरेंस का पैसा बड़ा ईजी मिल जाता है।
Say something to that effect. because i think
से समथिंग टू दैट इफ़ेक्ट। बिकॉज़ आई थिंक
People don't understand this. Consumers
पीपल डोंट अंडरस्टैंड दिस। कंज्यूमर्स
don't understand this aspect of flying
डोंट अंडरस्टैंड दिस एस्पेक्ट ऑफ़ फ्लाइंग
et all. So like I told you about the Goat incident
एट ऑल। सो जैसे मैंने गोअर वाला इंसिडेंट
I told you. Hmm. That is you making a pilot error
आपको बताया। हम्म। वो आप पायलेट एरर कर
You can, but you should go and check their history.
सकते हो बट उनका आप जा के हिस्ट्री तो
Study to see if they got enough rest, friend
स्टडी करो कि उनको यार इनफ रेस्ट मिला भी
Was it there or not? Right. what safety
था कि नहीं मिला था। राइट। क्या सेफ्टी
What were the cultures? How is the training done?
कल्चर क्या थे? ट्रेनिंग कैसे होती है?
Is training just about signing a paper?
क्या ट्रेनिंग सिर्फ एक पेपर पे साइन करके
Is it happening or is it even happening? the same standard
हो रही है या हो भी रही है? उसी स्टैंडर्ड
that hmm. That is also very important, right? so if
की हम्म। वो भी बहुत जरूरी है ना? सो इफ
You have 100 aircrafts on order. You
यू हैव 100 एयरक्राफ्ट्स ऑन ऑर्डर। यू
Don't want them to sit on the ground, right?
डोंट वांट देम टू सीट ऑन ग्राउंड, राइट?
You need people to fly them. so are you just
यू नीड पीपल टू फ्लाई देम। सो आर यू जस्ट
Many times friend, in my college we have
बहुत बार यार हमने यार मेरे कॉलेज में ना
When I failed in my B.Tech project
जब मेरा बीटेक प्रोजेक्ट में मैं फेल हो
When I went there the professor told me to do one thing
गया था हम तो वो प्रोफेसर कहता है एक काम
Anyway, you should wait for two months
कर वैसे तो देख तुझे दो महीना रुकना
I will have to do it in 5 days because
पड़ेगा 5 दिन में कर ले मैं भी क्योंकि
I also don't want to stop brother, yes it is right, right?
मुझे भी नहीं रुकना भाई हां सही सही है ना
This happens even if you are on leave
ऐसा होता है ना भी छुट्टी में है है ना
That's what happens, isn't it? So that's that culture.
वही ऐसा होता है ना तो वो वो वो कल्चर है
In your airline if the trainer fails
आपकी एयरलाइन में कि अगर ट्रेनर फेल कर
If he gives it then the trainer will have to come again, right?
देगा तो ट्रेनर को ही दोबारा आना है ना
He will come in just two hours and says come on friend
थोड़ी ना दो घंटा आएगा वो कहता है चल यार
You do it right this time, I'm telling you
तू इस बार ठीक से कर दियो मैं बता रहा हूं
So is that the culture in your airline or
तो क्या वो कल्चर है आपकी एयरलाइन में या
Proper training standards. so you have to
प्रॉपर ट्रेनिंग स्टैंडर्ड। सो यू हैव टू
Take deep to understand to go to the root cause
टेक डीप टू अंडरस्टैंड टू गो टू द रूट कॉज
Of the accident. It would have been much easier from the top
ऑफ द एक्सीडेंट। ऊपर ऊपर से बड़ा इजी होता
You should blame me that yes, it is an error,
है ब्लेम कर देना कि हां इसका एरर है,
Its an error or engineering error. the one who
इसका एरर या इंजीनियरिंग का एरर है। वो जो
I told you about the spy jet from Kolkata
मैंने आपको कोलकाता का स्पाई जेट का
Told the incident. We will tell him
इंसिडेंट बताया। हम वो बोल देगा
This is an engineering error. The procedure is that
इंजीनियरिंग एरर है। प्रोसीजर है कि
you should talk on headset then someone
तुम्हें बात करनी चाहिए हेडसेट पे तब कोई
The button should be pressed. But why doesn't he follow
बटन दबाना चाहिए। बट वो क्यों नहीं फॉलो
Happened? Is the culture like that? She has her own
हुआ? क्या कल्चर वैसा है? उसने अपने
You must have seen seniors doing similar things
सीनियर्स को देखा होगा ऐसे ही काम करते
happened. That's why he is also doing it. Seniors scored 10
हुए। तभी वो भी कर रहा है। सीनियर्स ने 10
Nothing happened for a year. do the same
साल तक करा कुछ नहीं हुआ। वो भी ऐसे ही कर
Used to be. So what is culture? The three right now
रहा है। तो कल्चर क्या है? अभी जो तीन
People were fired upon in Air India
लोगों को एयर इंडिया में फायर किया गया
They are not decision makers from rostering
रोस्टरिंग से दे आर नॉट डिसीजन मेकर्स
The decision makers are singing here
डिसीजन मेकर आर सिंग हियर
Friend, he is not taking the profit home
यार वो प्रॉफिट घर थोड़ी ना लेके जा रहे
They are from the company, they are getting salary
हैं कंपनी का उनको तो सैलरी मिल रही है
right so whatever command is coming from above
राइट तो जो कमांड आ रहा है ऊपर से उसको
He is following right now he is following the command
फॉलो कर रहे हैं वो राइट अब वो कमांड फॉलो
to do that they were sacked who
करने के लिए उनको सैक कर दिया गया जिसने
I gave the command give us your city comfortably hmm
कमांड दिया था दे आर सिटी कंफर्टेबली हम्म
I understand brother India is in India
मैं समझ रहा हूं भाई इंडिया में इंडिया
I dont know, globally, but I am from India
में क्या पता ग्लोबली भी बट इंडिया का मैं
I can tell this after seeing many times whose throat was slit
कह सकता हूं देख के कई बार जिसका गला काटा
She goes away, she remains an escape goat, it always happens, brother
जाता है वो स्केप गोट रहती है भाई होता ही
That means now we have to show it to the public
वो ना मतलब कि अब दिखाना भी तो है पब्लिक
To say that you are doing something. not to me
को कि कुछ तो कर रहे हैं। मेरे को नहीं
I don't know whether its details are like this or not. But
पता इसकी डिटेल्स ऐसी है कि नहीं। बट
People should know that sometimes
लोगों को ये बात पता होनी चाहिए कि कई बार
The man whose effigies were burnt in public
जिस आदमी को पब्लिक में जलाया जिसके पुतले
That man is actually jealous of her
जल रहे होते हैं ना वो आदमी एक्चुअली उसका
It is not as big a crime as any other
इतना बड़ा गुनाह नहीं होता जितना किसी और
What happens by sitting in the back? So
का होता है पीछे बैठ के। तो
yes and that's it the pilots aren't there
हां और ये बात तो है द पायलट्स नॉट देयर
To defend themselves. yes so me too
टू डिफेंड देमसेल्व्स। हां तो मुझे भी
I don't know if you call it pilot error
नहीं पता चलता कि अगर आप पायलट एरर कहते
If yes, then claiming insurance is also a little easy
हो तो इंश्योरेंस भी क्लेम करना थोड़ा इजी
remains. Right? Sooner Hughes I think Hughes
रहता है। राइट? जल्दी ह्यूज आई थिंक ह्यूज
incentive in this comes quickly yes it
इंसेंटिव इन दिस जल्दी आ जाता है हां इट्स
A huge incentive, yes, nothing light
अ ह्यूज इंसेंटिव हां कुछ हल्की बात नहीं
That would be a very good insurance
होगी बहुत अच्छा खासा इंश्योरेंस का वह
it would happen and then the blame has been rested
होता होगा एंड फिर ब्लेम हैज़ बीन रेस्टेड
on the pilot you do you do you do you don't have
ऑन द पायलट यू डू यू डू यू डू यू डोंट हैव
to do anything to keep everybody safe
टू डू एनीथिंग एनीथिंग एवरीबडी सेफ्ड
Because friend the other parties are involved
क्योंकि यार जो बाकी पार्टीज इनवॉल्व्ड
do they have to continue their business right
हैं दे हैव टू कंटिन्यू देयर बिज़नेस राइट
they can't they can't shut down right if
दे कैन नॉट दे कैन नॉट शट डाउन राइट अगर
If any blemish or black spot appears then
कुछ भी ब्लेम या ब्लैक स्पॉट आता है तो
Then their business will be impacted and they
फिर उनके बिज़नेस इम्पैक्ट होगा एंड दे
don't want that right then may be they will say that
डोंट वांट दैट राइट तो मे बी दे विल से कि
It's okay friend, there were only pilots and there are lots
यार ठीक है पायलट्स ही थे एंड देयर आर लॉट
of ah stakeholders now at this point of
ऑफ़ अह स्टेक होल्डर्स नाउ एट दिस पॉइंट ऑफ
This accident became a very big case because
दिस एक्सीडेंट बिकॉज़ बहुत बड़ा केस बन गया
Buddy. It is not a small case. It did not come
यार। छोटा केस थोड़ी ना है। ये नहीं आई
Don't think so. and infact since then joe
डोंट थिंक सो। एंड इनफैक्ट सिंस देन जो
General level of people regarding flights
जनरल लेवल ऑफ लोगों का फ्लाइटों को लेके
Having anxiety I've been tracking on
एंग्जायटी रहना आई हैव बीन ट्रैकिंग ऑन
Twitter to extend whatever I mean since
Twitter टू व्हाटएवर एक्सटेंड आई मीन सिंस
Then the new cycle has changed a lot. But
देन न्यू साइकिल बहुत चेंज हो गई है। बट
two for a large while i was like that bhaiya
टू फॉर अ लार्ज व्हाइल आई वाज़ लाइक कि भाई
here in this plane they said that we will not
यहां पे इस प्लेन ये दे सेड कि वी विल नॉट
Fly and That Pilot Is Saying We Will Not
फ्लाई और दैट पायलट इज़ सेइंग वी विल नॉट
Fly and this side had to come down. Yes,
फ्लाई और दिस साइड हैड टू कम डाउन। हां,
for a long while, probably, organically,
फॉर अ लोंग वाइल, प्रॉबब्ली, ऑर्गेनिकली,
Problem, because it was coming to me
प्रॉबब्ली, बिकॉज़ मेरे उसपे आ रहा था
On Twitter. I was following that. and one
Twitter पे। आई वाज फॉलोइंग दैट। एंड एक
General sense of consciousness has increased. I
जनरल सेंस ऑफ़ कॉन्शियसनेस बढ़ गई है। आई
Don't know if it will last. it is a very
डोंट नो इफ इट विल लास्ट। इट इज़ अ वैरी
Interesting thing. i think its quite a good thing
इंटरेस्टिंग थिंग। आई थिंक काफी बढ़िया बात
that pilots are refusing to fly okay
है कि पायलट्स आर रिफ्यूजिंग टू फ्लाई ओके
Aircraft. Because we as consumers we
एयरक्राफ्ट। बिकॉज़ हम एज कंज्यूमर्स वी
Never. Yes, I think they should do it.
नेवर। हां, मुझे लगता है इनको करना चाहिए।
they should put their food down and say that yaar
दे शुड पुट देयर फूड डाउन एंड से कि यार
I will write this. Clearly correct, isn't it?
ये तो मैं लिखूंगा। साफ सी बात है ना?
Yes, that's right. Hey it happened to me.
हां, सही बात है। अरे मेरे साथ हुआ था।
I was taking a walk around once and I
मैं एक बार वॉक अराउंड कर रहा था एंड आई
Saw some blood stains on the wing.
सॉ सम ब्लड स्टेंस ऑन द विंग।
o what does it mean bird bird b
ओ व्हाट डस इट मीन चिड़िया चिड़िया ब
strike by strike or whatever lands
स्ट्राइक ब स्ट्राइक या तो वो जो लैंड हुआ
it happened only then it happened at what speed tell me
है तब हुआ है तभी हुआ कितनी स्पीड से कह
Sir, I will clean it up, take it away, I said
रहा सर साफ कर देता हूं ले जाओ मैंने कहा
brother what yes that is correct friend means if
भाई क्या हां सही बात है यार मतलब अगर
How to fix a problem if a bird has entered the engine
इंजन में चिड़िया घुसी हुई है तो कैसे ले
should I go, anything can happen, yes brother I
जाऊं कुछ भी हो सकता है ना हां भाई मैं
Where I'm taking the flaps in the air I didn't come
जहां हवा में फ्लैप ले रहा हूं नहीं आया
So yes, his feather is stuck inside
तो हां फिर अंदर उसका पंख फंसा हुआ है
The bird is stuck in the trap, it is not clear
चिड़िया काटी फंसी हुई है वो तो साफ नहीं
will be able to do it yes right second jyoti sir
कर पाएगा हां राइट दूसरी ज्योति सर
Write in the next sector that there is a delay
नेक्स्ट सेक्टर में लिख देना अभी डिले हो
they are getting delayed right now because
रहे हैं अभी डिले हो रहे हैं क्योंकि
The aircraft was already delayed and now it is very late
एयरक्राफ्ट पहले से डिले आया था अभी बहुत
Taking one hour in the next sector
ले रहे नेक्स्ट सेक्टर में एक घंटे का
Write about the haltage ship there. I haven't
हॉल्टेज जहाज का वहां लिख देना। मैंने ना
Then I stopped doing all this. I said
फिर बंद कर दिया था ये सब करना। मैंने कहा
Alright brother, a lot of work has been done brother. yes means
ठीक है भाई बहुत काम चला है भाई। हां मतलब
Do it brother, do it. If I get any email
करो भाई करो। मेरे पास कोई मेल आएगा तो
I will answer it. And I said friend that
मैं जवाब दे दूंगा। एंड मैंने कहा यार वो
You have a best attitude. means you
एक बेस्ट एटीट्यूड होता है आपका। मतलब आप
I say that you do your job properly
मैं तो कहता हूं आप ये अपना काम ठीक से
Will you do it? then you need to take tension
करोगे ना? तो आपको टेंशन लेने की जरूरत
It is not there, friend. At least psychologically free
नहीं है यार। एटलीस्ट साइकोलॉजिकली फ्री
yes. Hey, you are free in every way friend. What to do
हो। अरे हर तरीके से फ्री हो यार। क्या कर
had been? You have come to do your work only and that is it
रहे हो? अपना काम ही तो करने आए हो और वही
you actually feel you are not doing it properly
ठीक से नहीं कर आप एक्चुअली आपको लगता है
You are helping someone. you help
आप किसी की हेल्प कर रहे हो। आप हेल्प
I am not doing it. you're ruining their work
नहीं कर रहे। आप काम खराब कर रहे हो उनका
And you are taking tension on yourself as well
भी और अपना भी और अपने ऊपर टेंशन ले रहे
Yes you are. Because brother this has happened many times
हो आप। क्योंकि भाई ऐसा हुआ है बहुत बार
The pilots tried to help
पायलट्स ने हेल्प करने की कोशिश की है
Management Key and Something When Goes Around
मैनेजमेंट की और समथिंग व्हेन गोज़ अराउंड
No, the DG only grabs the pilot by the throat
ना डीजी से तो पायलट का ही गला पकड़ता है
Brother. hum hum because what is your license
भाई। हम हम क्योंकि तुम्हारा लाइसेंस क्या
Then you can't fly? We are the Management
तुम फ्लाई नहीं कर सकते फिर? हम मैनेजमेंट
Still the suspension will be for 15 days.
वाला तो फिर भी सस्पेंशन होगा 15 दिन का।
I will come again for a month. You
एक महीने का फिर दोबारा आ जाएंगे। तुम
you won't be able to fly because you need something
फ्लाई नहीं कर पाओगे क्योंकि तुम्हें कुछ
There is no other work except flying an airplane.
काम और आता नहीं है जहाज उड़ाने के अलावा।
Right?
राइट?
You only know how to do one thing and that is without you
तुम्हें एक ही काम आता है और वो तुम बिना
Can't do it without license. we think so i
लाइसेंस के नहीं कर सकते। हम तो मुझे लगता
that is let's play safe and that's everyone's
है कि लेट्स प्ले सेफ और उसमें ही सबका
It is fine and there is no problem. Meaning
भला है और कोई दिक्कत नहीं होती। मतलब
I have seen it many times friend, even I myself when
मैंने देखा यार बहुत बार ना मैं खुद भी जब
I would be flying somewhere there would be fog
मैं फ्लाई कर रहा होता हूं कहीं फॉग होती
Nothing happens to that poor staff
है कुछ होती ना बेचारी उस स्टाफ से लोग
They are fighting. So I go and meet the staff
लड़ रहे होते हैं। तो मैं जाके स्टाफ का
I will take this side. Maam that ship is not there
ही साइड लेता हूं। मैम वो जहाज इसलिए नहीं
came because from there I came to try
आया क्योंकि वहां से आई ट्राई टू
explain to them that I don't know what
एक्सप्लेन टू देम कि मुझे पता ना क्या
Why not? So many times I defend
क्यों नहीं होता। तो बहुत बार मैं डिफेंड
I do it too. We are the passengers
भी करता हूं। हम मैं ही पैसेंजर्स को
I am pacifying myself at the airport and
पैसिफाई कर रहा होता हूं एयरपोर्ट पे और
You are becoming a big leader. I said sir
तू बड़ा चौधरी बन रहा है। मैंने कहा सर
no but it is like that because he
नहीं बट ये क्योंकि ऐसा है क्योंकि वो
He says that other airlines take take-land
कहता है यार बाकी एयरलाइंस तो टेक लैंड कर
Indigo is not flying or any other airline
रही है इंडिगो नहीं कर रही या फिर कोई एयर
India is not doing it. I said sir that
इंडिया नहीं कर रही। मैंने कहा सर वो उस
Coming from the airport. take off there
एयरपोर्ट से आ रही है। वहां पे टेक ऑफ
The minima are different. She is coming from Delhi.
मिनिमा अलग है। ये दिल्ली से आ रही है।
Take off minima is different in Delhi. so
दिल्ली में टेक ऑफ मिनिमा अलग है। इसलिए
It is landing here. she couldn't land
यहां लैंड कर रही है। वो लैंड नहीं कर पाई
The one from Amritsar. So people didn't know that
अमृतसर वाली। तो ये नहीं पता होता लोगों
To. Yes, I don't know. Isn't it? we so we
को। हां नहीं पता होता। है ना? हमें तो हम
So let's make sure if the flight is late
तो श्योर करते हैं अगर फ्लाइट लेट होती है
So. Yes. We were just getting angry
तो। हां। हमें तो सिर्फ गुस्सा आ रहा होता
Is. Because friend, other airlines are coming
है। बिकॉज़ यार बाकी एयरलाइन की तो आ रही
Is. Yours is not coming. Sir its Delhi
है। तुम्हारी नहीं आ रही। सर उसका दिल्ली
The ship which must have been there has arrived. the weather is fine there
का जहाज होगा वो आ गया। वहां पे वेदर ठीक
Is it done or you can go there even in 100 meters
हो गया या फिर वहां पे आप 100 मीटर में भी
You can take off. It was to come from Amritsar.
टेक ऑफ कर सकते हो। यह अमृतसर से आना था।
1000 meters are required in Amritsar. the weather is bad
अमृतसर में 1000 मीटर चाहिए। वेदर खराब है
Everywhere. So he can't take off
हर जगह। तो वो टेक ऑफ ही नहीं कर सकता
From there. Now he can't take off because of boredom.
वहां से। अब बोर से वो टेक ऑफ ही नहीं कर
Can. So the general public does not know. so yes
सकता। सो जनरल पब्लिक डजंट नो। तो हां
Right right. well
राइट राइट। वेल
I mean bro
आई मीन भाई
here i this is one of those things about real
ये आई दिस इज़ वन ऑफ़ दोज़ थिंग्स अबाउट रियल
Life. Where there is no closure. to me
लाइफ। वेयर देयर इज़ नो क्लोज़र। मेरे को
It seems that some of the things are like this
ऐसा लगता है कि यह कुछ चीजें ऐसी होती हैं
And there probably aren't four such things in the whole year.
और पूरे साल में ना शायद ऐसी चार चीजें
There are things that we should talk about openly
होती हैं जिनके बारे में बात खुल के करनी
and let them hang in the air
चाहिए और उनको हवा में टंगने देना चाहिए
for them to be late for people to consume
फॉर देम टू बी लेट फॉर पीपल टू कंज्यूम
and for people to understand and to just
एंड फॉर पीपल टू अंडरस्टैंड एंड टू जस्ट
you know sit with it this is one of those things
यू नो सिट विथ इट दिस इज़ वन ऑफ़ दोज़ थिंग्स
frankly there is no right answer that
फ्रैंकली देयर इज़ नो राइट आंसर दैट
everything ends in sadness everything ends
एव्रीथिंग एंड्स इन सैडनेस एवरीथिंग एंड्स
in confusion but if it seems like an accident
इन कन्फ्यूजन लेकिन अगर जैसे यह एक्सीडेंट
Now if it happens then it will be investigated as well
हुआ ना अब इसकी इन्वेस्टिगेशन भी होगी तो
Accidents don't happen with just one mistake
एक्सीडेंट डोंट हैपन विद जस्ट वन मिस्टेक
that he did something wrong or an engine failed
कि उसने गलत कर दिया या फिर एक इंजन फेल
Done. It has a Swiss cheese with no cheese
हो गया। उसमें ना एक चीज के एक स्विस चीज
Let us teach you a model. That happens.
के एक मॉडल पढ़ाते हैं हमको। वो होता है।
so there are lots of holes you know what tom
तो देयर आर लॉट ऑफ़ होल्स यू नो चीज़ जो टॉम
And Jerry eats cheese. ji to all the holes
एंड जेरी खाता है चीज़। जी तो ऑल द होल्स
have to align at one point at one day at that
हैव टू अलाइन एट वन पॉइंट एट वन डे एट दैट
Instant for that accident to happen. Lot
इंस्टेंट फॉर दैट एक्सीडेंट टू हैपन। लॉट
of things go wrong. because that's what I'm saying
ऑफ़ थिंग्स गो रोंग। बिकॉज़ मैं वही कह रहा
hmm friend aircraft are really beautiful
हूं यार एयरक्राफ्ट आर सच ब्यूटीफुल
Machines. They just don't fail like that. To them
मशीनंस। दे जस्ट डोंट फेल लाइक दैट। इनको
I twisted it a lot and took a lot of advantage
बहुत तोड़ा मरोड़ा और बहुत एडवांटेज लिया
Must have gone. There will also be a human factor. that day
गया होगा। ह्यूमन फैक्टर भी होगा। उस दिन
Some mistake might have happened at the airport also. Long
एयरपोर्ट पर भी कुछ गलती हुई होगी। लॉन्ग
There might also have been a history of scheduling.
हिस्ट्री ऑफ़ स्केेड्यूलिंग भी रही होगी।
Management also has to do with when that happens and not
मैनेजमेंट की भी व्हेन वो होता है ना कि
Really bad day. [ __ ] everything aligned on the same day
रियली बैड डे। साला सब कुछ उसी दिन अलाइन
Done. what happens sometimes is that you
हो गया। हम कभी-कभी क्या होता है कि आप
you are not rested but first officer arrested
रेस्टेड नहीं हो बट फर्स्ट ऑफिसर अरेस्टेड
or did you see something. something was given
था या आपने कुछ देख लिया। समथिंग वाज़ दी
Another save but that day everything aligned. We
अदर सेव बट दैट डे एवरीथिंग अलाइन। हम
Right right.
राइट राइट।
Thank you so much for your video. infact
थैंक यू सो मच फॉर योर वीडियो। इनफैक्ट
Even what was your response to Captain Steve
इवन जो आपका रिस्पांस था कैप्टन स्टीव को
but I think you conducted yourself very well
लेके आई थिंक यू कंडक्टेड योरसेल्फ वैरी
Gracefully and as a very good healthy
ग्रेसफुली एंड एज अ वेरी गुड हेल्दी
Example from the aviation sort of side of
एग्जांपल फ्रॉम द एिएशन सॉर्ट ऑफ़ साइड ऑफ़
Things in the public and media side. thank you
थिंग्स इन द पब्लिक एंड मीडिया साइड। थैंक
You are so much for doing that. Thank you so much
यू सो मच फॉर डूइंग दैट। थैंक यू सो मच
For taking out time for this conversation.
फॉर टेकिंग आउट टाइम फॉर दिस कॉन्वर्सेशन।
Thank you brother. this has been i have learned
थैंक यू भाई। दिस हैज़ बीन आई आई हैव लर्न
A lot. it's still very sad but I have
अ लॉट। इट्स स्टिल वैरी सैड बट आई हैव
Learn a lot. Absolutely. I some thing
लर्न अ लॉट। अब्सोलुटली। मैं कुछ-कुछ चीज
It happens that I am not able to understand. I
होती है ना कि समझ में नहीं आ रहा। मैं
I still think about it, my friend, I still see that
अभी भी सोचता हूं तो यार आई स्टिल सी दैट
The aircraft is going down and I imagine that I
एयरक्राफ्ट गोइंग डाउन एंड इमेजिन कि मैं
what could I do if I were there and the
क्या कर सकता अगर मैं वहां होता एंड द
The answer every time I get it is probably nothing
आंसर ए्री टाइम आई गेट इज शायद कुछ नहीं
Maybe I am the only God in that sim
शायद सिर्फ भगवान हैं मैं वो सिम में
It was evaluated and also recreated again
इवैलुएट भी किया दोबारा भी आई रिकक्रिएटेड
that
दैट
It was not a mistake that he lost and could not do anything
फर्ट तो नहीं थी कि वो हारा कुछ नहीं कर
I could but if he was real then what would I do
सकता बट अगर वो सही में होता तो मैं क्या
I would be screaming or what would I be doing
मैं चिल्ला रहा होता या मैं क्या कर रहा
It just happens when it's your last 10 seconds
होता जस्ट वो जब आपके लास्ट 10 सेकंड होते
In life, whom would I be remembering?
लाइफ के तो आप किसको याद कर रहा होता मैं
is he scary bro or
क्या वै स्केरी ब्रो या
thank you so much brother i hopefully see you
थैंक यू सो मच भाई आई होपफुली सी यू वै
Soon for a brighter conversation, thank you
सून फॉर अ ब्राइटर कन्वर्सेशन चलो थैंक यू
so much thank you thank you brother
सो मच थैंक यू थैंक यू भाई